<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Pliny's panegyricke: a speech in Senate: wherein publike thankes are presented to the Emperour Traian, / by C. Plinius Cæcilius Secundus Consul of Rome. Translated out of the originall Latin, illustrated with annotations, and dedicated to the prince, by Sr Rob. Stapylton Knight, Gent. in Ordinary of the Privy Chamber to His Highnesse.</title>
            <title>Panegyricus. English</title>
            <author>Pliny, the Younger.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 255 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90783</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2579</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E283_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200055</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860858</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860858</idno>
            <idno type="VID">158486</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90783)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 158486)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 47:E283[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Pliny's panegyricke: a speech in Senate: wherein publike thankes are presented to the Emperour Traian, / by C. Plinius Cæcilius Secundus Consul of Rome. Translated out of the originall Latin, illustrated with annotations, and dedicated to the prince, by Sr Rob. Stapylton Knight, Gent. in Ordinary of the Privy Chamber to His Highnesse.</title>
                  <title>Panegyricus. English</title>
                  <author>Pliny, the Younger.</author>
                  <author>Stapylton, Robert, Sir, d. 1669.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 60 [i.e. 66] [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[H. Hall],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare 1644. [i.e. 1645]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Wing has publication year 1644[5]; Thomason catalogue lists under 1645.</note>
                  <note>Numerous errors in pagination.</note>
                  <note>With a final errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 13 1645".</note>
                  <note>The frontispiece portrait of Charles II as a young man in the Thomason copy "is only one of a set of similar oval plates used for illustrating books"--Madan.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Trajan, --  Emperor of Rome, 53-117 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:158486:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Charles by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of God Prince of Wales, Duke of Cornwell, etc.</head>
                  <byline>G:G:</byline>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Charles, Prince of Wales</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:158486:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PLINY'S <hi>Panegyricke:</hi> A Speech in Senate: Wherein publike thankes are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the EMPEROUR TRAIAN, By <hi>C. Plinius Caecilius Secundus</hi> Conſul of ROME.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of the Originall Latin, illuſtrated with Annotations, and dedicated to the PRINCE, <hi>By</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> ROB. STAPYLTON Knight, Gent. in Ordinary of the Privy Chamber to His Highneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed in the yeare 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:158486:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:158486:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE CHARLES, PRINCE OF GREAT BRITAINE, DVKE OF CORNWALL AND ALBANY, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y duty (that moves alwaies to your preſence, as the flame to heaven) is now more imboldned, becauſe in the preſent eruption of <hi>Licentious Pamphlets,</hi> I conceive it ſeaſonable to publiſh a <hi>modeſt worke,</hi> and neceſſary to intitle it to inviolable protection. Humbly therefore I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate to your Highneſſe <hi>Pliny's</hi> Panegyricke, which hath lived many Ages with conſtant appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation in his Dialect, and even in my rude expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions (being cheriſhed with your gracious ſmile) may have the honour to out-live all thoſe abor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives
<pb facs="tcp:158486:3"/>
of the Preſſe, that (like their compeeres the vipers) are curſt into fruitfulneſſe.</p>
            <p>Such as his Booke, ſuch was the Author, uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally approved of; for what merit, appeares by his advancement in thoſe times when merit onely was preferr'd, his prudence, erudition, and integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of life advancing him to the Conſulſhip of <hi>Rome,</hi> and yet higher, to the impartiall eſtimation of his Prince, for whoſe favours gratefull <hi>Pliny</hi> to this day payes tribute: For now when <hi>Trajan's</hi> Annals lye in fragments, when thoſe imperiall Statues and Triumphall Arches, that ſhould have immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed him, have confeſſed their owne mortality; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold (in this Panegyricke) that beſt of <hi>Caeſars</hi> from his Aſhes reaſcends his Throne, where he ſtill go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernes the world, as an example.</p>
            <p>But, Sir, you have (and long may you have) a living example, the abſolute paterne of all virtues, His Sacred Majeſtie, whoſe Heroicall and Divine Principles we know are written in your heart, becauſe we read them in your actions. From hence flowes your particular regard to the deſerving, from hence your generall affability, and (which in your Spring of yeares we behold with greateſt admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) your love to Iuſtice equalls your love to Men; and both theſe Affections are ſteered by Iudgement, great as your Birth and Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:158486:3"/>What fitter wiſh can I make to ſo much good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, then that of the Romane Senate to their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours? May you be<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eutropius.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſque ad noſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aetatem non ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in Senatu Principibus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clametur, niſi foelicior <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſto,</hi> melior <hi>Trajano.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>happier then Auguſtus, better then Trajan:</hi> to whom you are now ſo juſt a Paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel, that I preſent his Character as a marke of your owne height in honour; whereon if your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe pleaſe ſometimes to caſt your eye, you may diſcerne how you out-grow him in thoſe perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, vvhich render you the Modell of your Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Parents, and the joy of all their Loyall Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; among the faithfulleſt whereof, as my ſtudy, ſo my hope is ever to be number'd:</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your Highneſſe's moſt obedient and moſt faithfull ſervant <hi>ROBERT STAPYLTON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:158486:4"/>
            <head>The Preface to the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the Booke may preſent leſſe diſtraction from the margent when you carry the ſubject in your memory, give me leave to prepare you with a ſhort view as well of <hi>Trajan's</hi> private condition, and the publique ſtate of the Empire when he was elected, as of his Conqueſt of the King of <hi>Dacia</hi> juſtly occaſioned by this <hi>Panegyricke, Veſpaſian Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> had now declared the Jewes Rebels, and accordingly denounced warre againſt them, when he ſent <hi>L. Trajan</hi> (father to <hi>Trajan</hi> the Emperour) then Tribune of the tenth Legion, with two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Foote and a thouſand Horſe againſt <hi>Aphaca</hi> in <hi>Galilee,</hi> a City naturally ſtrong, and fortified with a double wall: The <hi>Gali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laeans</hi> draw into the field, the Tribune gives them battaile, beats them within their firſt wall, and falls in pellmell with them. The City, fearing he would do the like at the ſecond wall, locke out their owne men, who were, by the <hi>Romanes,</hi> all put to the ſword to the number of twelve thouſand. <hi>Trajan</hi> hearing no more of the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, and preſently apprehending, that either none remained, or ſuch as durſt make no reſiſtance, reſerves the honour of taking <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaca</hi> for the Emperour himſelfe. <hi>Titus</hi> is ſent, who commanding the right wing, and <hi>Trajan</hi> the left, the Towne is Stormed; and the Tribune afterwards honoured with Triumphall ornaments, and made Conſul of <hi>Rome.</hi> This was the firſt eminent Riſe of <hi>Trajan's</hi> Family. Nor did the Fathers happy Starre finiſh its courſe in him, but came to a higher elevation in his ſonne, whom he trained under his command, as the Eagle breeds his Eaglet, firſt to looke up at heaven, and then to governe as Vice-Roy to the Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <hi>Spaine</hi> was young <hi>Trajan's</hi> Country, warre his cradle: when he was yet a youth he commanded in chiefe againſt the <hi>Parthians<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> nor did <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> imploy the father with a truer intention to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munerate
<pb facs="tcp:158486:4"/>
his ſervice, then <hi>Domitian</hi> imployed the ſonne onely to ſpeed his death upon the bed of honour, which was made for him in ſeverall and farre diſtant climates, <hi>Trajan</hi> being ſtill ſent away, where new danger threatned <hi>Domitian,</hi> who was carefull to pay the laſt hazard of his Generall's life with a freſh occaſion of a more deſperate engagement; but in vaine he laboured it, for a higher power both preſerved and retributed <hi>Trajan,</hi> not (like his father) with a Conſulſhip, but with that very Empire under which he ſo long and ſo injuriouſly had ſuffered. For <hi>Nerva</hi> ſucceeding <hi>Domitian,</hi> and <hi>M. Trajan</hi> (now Generall of the <hi>German</hi> Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) being at <hi>Colein,</hi> there happen'd, in the Pretorian Campe near <hi>Rome,</hi> a dangerous mutiny; which ſhaking the Imperiall Crowne on <hi>Nerva's</hi> head, made him ſettle it upon <hi>Trajan.</hi> The cauſe of the inſurrection was this. The Pretorians (the Emperours Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard) which were at firſt quartered ſcatteringly in <hi>Rome,</hi> had beene drawne out into a ſtanding Campe, when <hi>Sejanus</hi> was their Prefect: who poſſeſſed the Emperour <hi>Tiberius,</hi> that living in Towne debauched the Souldiers, whereas fixt in a body they would better obſerve diſcipline, and be readier for any preſent ſervice. What this cunning allegation meant, ſubtiller <hi>Tiberius</hi> ſoon found out, &amp; <hi>Sejanus</hi> as ſoon felt in his own deſtruction. Yet ſtill the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torians continued in a Campe, and howſoever the deſigne failed in the Individuall, yet it tooke in the generall; for though they made not <hi>Sejanus</hi> Emperour, yet they made Emperours afterward at their pleaſure. At this very time they were ſenſible of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their power, and therefore expected anſwerable Donatives from Princes, which <hi>Domitian</hi> poured into their hands. But <hi>Nerva</hi> was more provident for the publike, then to empty the Treaſury to fill private purſes, and the loyalty of the Pretorians more weake, then to ſtand firme without a golden buttreſſe. The ill humour, now ſtirred in them by their aged Emperours frugality, was fomented by their Prefect <hi>Aelianus Caſperius</hi> (made their Captaine by <hi>Domitian,</hi> and not removed by <hi>Nerva</hi>) who likewiſe miſſing his owne covetous hopes, quickened their inclination to
<pb facs="tcp:158486:5"/>
rebellion, giving them for a pious pretext the ſpecious colour of doing juſtice upon the conſpiratours againſt <hi>Domitian,</hi> not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding <hi>Nerva</hi> in the number (for they knew him innocent) but only requiring the lives of all that were actors in their maſters death; to whom <hi>Nerva</hi> had given a Prince's word for the indem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of their perſons, which ſurely is a ſufficient <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; yet to take away all Scruple (which might breed jealouſies, and conſequently cauſe diſturbances of the publicke peace) he had likewiſe paſt his oath to an Act of Oblivion in Senate. But the Prince's Act ſhall not binde them againſt their Captaines Proteſtation, <hi>Caſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> is their Legiſlator, and according to his Fundamentalls, they oppoſe the knowne Law, and clamour to have <hi>Domitian's</hi> mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers brought to condigne puniſhment, that is, they declare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves judges of the matter of fact, and in the ſame moment ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare as executioners, and were a great deale fitter for this office. <hi>Nerva</hi> withſtands them, and when he ſees no perſwaſion can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile, offers his owne boſome naked to their fury, that death might free him of his promiſe. But this was no part of their inſtructions, by which they punctually proceed, and execute all the men their Prefect had mark't out for ſlaughter. <hi>Nerva</hi> now finding that old-age rendred him contemptible to the ſouldier, not having an heire of his owne, conſiders only that which Electours ought only to conſider, merit, and having pitcht upon the man that already ruled in all mens hearts, he went to the Temple of <hi>Jupiter Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolin,</hi> and in the preſence of a great multitude that followed him, uttered theſe words <hi>Bona fortuna Senatûs Populique Romani &amp; mei ipſius, Marcum Ulpium Trajanum Nervam adopto. May it be happy to the Senate and People of Rome and to my ſelfe, I adopt Marcus Ulpius Trajan Nerva.</hi> Thus giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Trajan</hi> his name and adopting him for his ſonne in the Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tol, he immediately transferred his Soveraignty and declared him Emperour in Senate: Nothing now wanted to perfect the reeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of the late endangered Empire, but only to provide that an example of rebellion ſo deſtructive to government might not
<pb facs="tcp:158486:5"/>
with impunity be paſt over, by his ſonnes calmer temper. I ſhould wrong <hi>Nerva</hi> to conceive that his revenge could have any end but the publicke good; for had he beene vindicative, he had not ſuffered <hi>Craſſus</hi> with the other Conſpirators againſt his owne life to eſcape unpuniſhed; whom be was ſo farre from hindring in their intentions towards him, that as they ſate with him beholding the ſhewes preſented in the Circus, he made ſwords be brought them, and ſayd, <hi>Inſpicite ſi acuti ſint, Looke if they be ſharpe,</hi> plainely ſignifying (as <hi>Dion</hi> obſerves) that he cared not how ſoone they would diſpatch him. Without controverſie therefore it was the Empire, not himſelfe he ſought revenge for, writing with his owne hand to <hi>Trajan</hi> theſe words of <hi>Chryſis Apollo's</hi> preiſt (In <hi>Homer</hi>) praying to his God againſt the barbarous <hi>Greekes,</hi> that denyed him his daughter's freedome upon ranſome tendered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iliad.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Let thy ſhafts make the Greekes repent my teares.</hi> Every line in <hi>Homer</hi> was then by the <hi>Romans</hi> accounted ſacred; I am ſure this proved propheticall for <hi>Trajan,</hi> after his Father <hi>Nerva's</hi> deceaſe, ſent for <hi>Aelianus</hi> and his Praetorians, who came expecting great imployment which they deſerved not, and found the ignominious death which they deſerved. Nor did the Emperour <hi>Trajan</hi> only do exemplary juſtice upon rebellious Subjects, but likewiſe puniſhed a revolted Prince, <hi>Decebalus</hi> Kings of <hi>Dacia,</hi> who had formerly by his Embaſſadours ſued for Peace, and himſelfe in Perſon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate at <hi>Trajan</hi>'s feete accepted ſuch conditions as he pleaſed to give, <hi>viz.</hi> to lay downe armes, to yeild up his Engins and Engi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neeres, to deliver Fugitives, to ſlight all workes, to demoliſh all Fortifications, to depart from the lands he had intrenched upon, &amp; to eſteeme thoſe freinds or Enemies that were ſo accounted by the <hi>Romans.</hi> In purſuance hereof, after <hi>Trajan's</hi> returne to <hi>Italy</hi> the <hi>Dacian</hi> Embaſſadours come to <hi>Rome,</hi> and are admitted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Senate, where yeilding up their armes and joyning their hands after the manner of ſervants they ſupplicate in few words
<pb facs="tcp:158486:6"/>
and ſo the peace being confirmed, their armes are returned them, this done <hi>Trajan</hi> triumphes for his conqueſt over the <hi>Dacians,</hi> and is ſtiled <hi>Dacicus.</hi> But <hi>Decebalus</hi> cannot ſit quiet, nature <hi>(cuſtode potentior omni)</hi> ſtruggles to ſhake off the <hi>Roman</hi> fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, to which he lately had ſubmitted; for he being (as <hi>Dion</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers him) ingenious, and of great experience in the warre, nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to invade, or to retreate if need required, one that knew excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently how to lay ambuſhes, and to give battaile, to uſe a victory to his beſt advantage, and moderately to beare an overthrow, and having ſo often fought with the <hi>Romans,</hi> and evaded even their victories by his ſtratagems, relying upon his owne abilities (and conceiving that <hi>Trajan,</hi> whoſe perſon he more feared then his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, being now warme in the pleaſures of <hi>Rome,</hi> would hardly venture backe into the <hi>Dacian</hi> froſt and ſnow) he breakes all the articles of peace, takes up armes, entertaines fugitives, fortifies, by his Embaſſadours ſollicits his neighbours to revolt, and allready had poſſeſſed himſelfe of ſome of the country of the <hi>Jaziges</hi> [now the territory of <hi>Sibenburghen.</hi>] This newes the Senate had, when the Conſul <hi>Pliny</hi> made this Oration to <hi>Trajan,</hi> whoſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits he ſo inflamed againſt that King for his contempt of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, that he would not ſubſtitute any Generall, but undertooke the warre againſt <hi>Decebalus</hi> in perſon, and to accelerate the worke cauſed a ſtupendious bridge to be built over <hi>Danubius,</hi> in ſuch a part of the river where the torrent was ſo ſtrong, that there was no turning of the water; the Bridge conſiſted of <hi>20</hi> piles or pillars of ſquared ſtone, every piller (not reckoning the foundations) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>150</hi> foote long, <hi>60</hi> foote broad, diſtant from one another <hi>170</hi> foot, and arched above. Paſſing his army at this bridge he fought ſecurely with incredible celerity, and at laſt with much difficulty conquered. <hi>Decebalus,</hi> ſeeing his palaces and Kingdome poſſeſſed by the enemy, and fearing his owne turne would be next, ſlew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and though he had (according to his uſuall ſubtlety) turned a river to hide his wealth and drawne backe the ſtreame againe; for more ſecurity, cauſing the ſervants he had imployed in it to be
<pb facs="tcp:158486:6"/>
put to death, yet all that vaſt treaſure came to <hi>Trajan's</hi> hands, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing confeſſed by <hi>Bicilis</hi> after the fate of his great freind <hi>Dece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balus,</hi> whoſe head was brought to <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Dacia</hi> by <hi>Trajan</hi> made a <hi>Roman</hi> Colony.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Becauſe <hi>Pliny,</hi> through the whole frame of his Pane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyrick illuſtrates <hi>Trajan's</hi> virtues, by comparing them with <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitian's</hi> vices, leſt you ſuſpect him to be a flatterer for praiſing a good Prince eloquently, or thinke him a detractour for no leſſe eloquently diſpraiſing a bad, I ſhall give you the characters of both thoſe Emperours, as I finde them in the moſt authenticke Hiſtories; and firſt of the firſt in priority of time. <hi>Domitian</hi> was a bold and furious man, very full of tricks, and vaine, ſo that he was raſh on the one part, and crafty on the other, for much he laid waſte break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in like thunder, and againe he deſtroyed much upon plot and and premeditation. He never truly &amp; with his heart loved any but a few women, yet he alwaies made as if he affected him whoſe blood he thirſted for. So diffident he was in thoſe that gratified or flatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him in greateſt matters. that who preſented him moſt money, or accuſed moſt men, them he was ſure to ruine, eſpecially ſervants that informed againſt their Maſters. But though this was his carriage in his Empire, yet he exceeded himſelfe in caſting aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions on his father and brother, whom he hated becauſe they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded him in honour: to avoid which infamy (as he eſteemed it) be bragged, that they <hi>left</hi> not, but <hi>reſtored</hi> the Empire to him, which he had beſtowed upon them. He would mention his brother <hi>Titus</hi> with teares, as if he had beene acting his part upon the Stage, and lament his greateſt ſhare in the loſſe of that delight of mankind; but notwithſtanding he did all things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his determination, and tooke away the Circenſian games, meerly becauſe they were celebrated upon his birth-day; loving no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of his brother's but his daughter <hi>Julia,</hi> whom he forced to marry him, and his Eunuch <hi>Earinus;</hi> yet becauſe <hi>Titus</hi> had loved Eunuches, in ſcorne of him he forbad that any more ſhould be made within the limits of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire. Now and then he made great entertainments, and his wine flowed
<pb facs="tcp:158486:7"/>
in the night-time, which as it was ſure to pleaſe the people, ſo ſure were ſome of the Nobility to die for it, that he might recover his expenſes with a confiſcation: Men knew not, ſafely, either how to condole, or congratulate with him, leſt they ſhould or be a trouble to him, or ſeeme to take notice of his diſſimulation. Such his impatience of labour, and his timerouſneſſe, that when he lead his Army againſt the <hi>Dacians</hi> he himſelfe never ſaw the face of an enemy, yet ſuch his pride and vain-glory, that after the foule loſſe of almoſt all his men, he writ letters of his conqueſt to the Senate, and by their decree the world was filled with his ſilver and golden ſtatues: But what in him was worſt of all, though he writ himſelfe Lord and God, and coveted infinitely to be flattered, yet both they that did, and they that did not adore him were equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpleaſing, for in thoſe he held it to be <hi>flattery,</hi> and in theſe <hi>neglect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Trajan</hi> had a ſpirit ſo well tempered, that youth made him not raſh, nor old age ſlow. He envied none, ruined no man, graced all good men with honours and dignities. He gave no credit to detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours, had no furious paſsion, and was as farre from taking another's propriety, as another's life. His expenſes were vaſt, both in times of warre and peace, wherein he finiſhed many neceſſary Workes, as High-wayes, Havens, and Publique buildings, yet never ſhed any ones blood to defray the charges. He was by nature magnificent and magnanimous, and therefore when he had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged, and beautified the great ſhow-place, he ſet up an inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that he had perfected the <hi>Circus,</hi> that it might containe the people of <hi>Rome;</hi> from whom he more coveted love, then ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; carrying himſelfe with civility to the people, with noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the Senate. He was deare to his Subjects, terrible to his enemies. He hunted and feaſted with the <hi>Romanes,</hi> was preſent at their ſerious and merry meetings, where he often ſate downe the fourth gueſt, nay, many times, came without his guard to private houſes, and lay there all night. And though he affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted warre, yet he commanded ſo, that he broke his enemies, and increaſed his friends; for it never happened ſo to him (as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
<pb facs="tcp:158486:7"/>
it falls out in Armies) that his Souldiers ſhewed themſelves inſolent, ſo well and rationally he managed his affaires: nor was he ſo intentive to the Warre, that he omitted what belongs to Peace, but ſate in perſon in the Courts of Juſtice, and in the <hi>Forum</hi> of <hi>Auguſtus, Livia's</hi> Gallery, and divers other places heard and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined cauſes. To ſumme up all in his owne words atteſted by his actions, he was to private men ſuch an Emperour, as being him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a private man, he wiſhed an Emperour ſhould be to him.</p>
            <p>Thus having endeavoured to vindicate my author's worke from obſcurity and his fame from cenſure, I ſhall have an eye in the laſt place to my ſelfe to prevent the nicer Critickes, that will (I know) be buſie with my very firſt words, eſpecially when ſo ſtrong an objection lyes againſt them, as that thoſe very Senatours whom I call Lords, could not endure the title. I anſwer, the <hi>Romans</hi> underſtood the word <hi>(Lord)</hi> in a twofold notion, firſt as it had ſlave for the Correlative, and conſequently ſignified Tyrant; and then as it rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Subject or inferiour, and was the ſtile of one in Soveraign, or ſubordinate authority. So that <hi>Pliny</hi> himſelfe, who in the former ſenſe abhorres the ſtile of Lord in his Panegyricke, in the ſecond ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception ſtiles <hi>Trajan</hi> Lord in his Epiſtles: and I by the ſame rule intitling the Senatours Lords of the Senate, ſhall (I doubt not) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit my ſelf to the Learned, whereas the Conſull would have ſpoken like a <hi>Roman</hi> newly landed, ſcarce intelligible, if I had uſed Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript Fathers in the Concrete; and when I had come to the Abſtract Fatherhood or reverence, I ſhould have made a Colledge of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate. As in this part ſo in the whole take notice, I beſeech you, that I as induſtriouſly decline Latiniſmes, as <hi>Politian</hi> in his Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of <hi>Herodian</hi> profeſſes to ſhun Graeciſmes.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>A. Politianus in Praefat. ad Innocentium viii.</hi> Ne inepta peregrinitas, ne Graculae uſqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> figurae, niſi ſi quae jam pro re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptis habentur, <hi>Latinam</hi> quaſi polluerent c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtitatem.</note> 
               <hi>Leſt fooliſh forreigne words, ſhould as it were ſtaine the chaſtity of our Language.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude, I muſt deſire this favour, that if the <hi>Latin</hi> of your <hi>Pliny</hi> differ from my <hi>Engliſh,</hi> you will believe, that you and I have ſeverall Editions. So leaving you to entertaine your ſelves a while with <hi>Pliny's</hi> Life (his perfect Picture in the <hi>Antecamera</hi>) that being peruſed, you may be pleaſed to open the Senate houſe, and hear him ſpeaking.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb facs="tcp:158486:8"/>
            <head>THE LIFE OF <hi>C. PLINIVS COECILIVS SECVNDVS.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Learning of the <hi>Romanes</hi> and their Empire flouriſhed together, for about the time of <hi>Auguſtus</hi> and <hi>Trajan</hi> lived their moſt illuſtrious Writers, and among them the two <hi>Plinyes,</hi> whereof the younger (Authour of this <hi>Panegyricke</hi>) was ſonne to <hi>L. Caecilius</hi> by the ſiſter of that other <hi>Pliny</hi> the naturall Hiſtorian; who having no childe, and finding that his nephew would be heire to his knowledge made him (by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption) heire likewiſe to his name and fortunes. His Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours were <hi>Niceas</hi> the Prieſt, and <hi>Quintilian</hi> the Oratour. When he was military Tribune in <hi>Syria Euphrates</hi> the Philoſopher read to him. He was much delighted in tranſlating <hi>Greeke</hi> authours into <hi>Latine,</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi> into <hi>Greeke,</hi> which made him maſter of both the Languages. When he was very young he writ a <hi>Greeke</hi> Comoedy, and divers Poems which the <hi>Grecians</hi> themſelves applauded. At one and twenty yeares of age he pleaded in the <hi>Roman</hi> Courts of Juſtice in the <hi>Forum,</hi> and afterward in Senate defended Cauſes of high con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment. He was patron to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> in their accuſation of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius Maſſa,</hi> &amp; <hi>Caecilius Claſſicus,</hi> &amp; delivered the charge againſt the Proconſul of <hi>Africa, Marius Priſcus,</hi> whom his Province impeached of bribery and extortion. Being Praetour, according to the duty of his place, he ſet forth the uſuall Playes and Showes, but with more then uſuall magnificence; that he might appeare to <hi>Domitian</hi> onely to intend his pleaſures, wherein he diſguiſed himſelfe with better fortune, than poore <hi>Domitius Glabrio,</hi> who fought naked with the Lions in the ſame Emperours preſence, for <hi>Pliny</hi> (though with much difficulty) eſcaped the jealous and inquiſitive eye of that cruell Prince, who made it his maſter-piece, what maske ſoever was put on; firſt, to diſcover, and then to cut off Virtue. With great integrity and equall reputation, he diſcharged the Offices of the Emperour's Queſtour, Tribune of the People, Praefect of the Treaſury, and high Commiſſioner for the reparations of the <hi>Aemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> Way, and the Bay and Bankes of <hi>Tiber.</hi> The Collegue of his military Tribuneſhip was <hi>Caleſtrius Tyro,</hi> of his Praefectſhip and
<pb facs="tcp:158486:8"/>
Conſulſhip <hi>Cornutus Tertullus.</hi> In the Augur's dignity he ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Iulius Frontinus.</hi> He was ſent with Proconſular power to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne the Provinces of <hi>Pontus</hi> &amp; <hi>Bythinia,</hi> from whence he return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Rome:</hi> no leſſe honoured for his prudence, then for his indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry and moderation. An inſtance whereof, to his eternall honour, is that noble teſtimony of the behaviour of the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> living un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him, which he certified to <hi>Trajan,</hi> writing to this effect; that he perceived their number to increaſe, and leſt ſo many ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer death without the guilt of ſome enormous offence, he had tryed all meanes and wayes to diſcover the intent of their private aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyes, and found upon examination, <hi>That they met before day, onely to ſing hymnes to</hi> Chriſt <hi>as God, binding themſelves by Sacrament, not againſt the</hi> Roman <hi>Lawes, or to commit any crime; but to renounce theft, robbery, faith breaking, and denyall of Depoſitums intruſted to them, eating together at thoſe meetings, promiſcuouſly, but innocently.</hi> To his demand, what courſe he ſhould take with theſe men? <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jan</hi> anſwers. <hi>Conquirendi non ſunt.</hi> His pleaſure was they ſhould not be inquired after. Which gave a ſtop to that violent Perſecution, the onely ſpot in that cleare sky of <hi>Trajans</hi> fame; ſo prevalent with him were <hi>Pliny's</hi> words, who obtained of his Prince many favours and honours for his friends, and for himſelfe whatſoever he would make his ſuit. The great eſtate that came to him by inheritance, and was increaſed by his owne prudent induſtry, his noble nature muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficently beſtowed. Witneſſe his bounty to his Tutour <hi>Quintilian,</hi> to whom he ſent five hundred thouſand Seſtercii, taking the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his daughter's marriage, that he might buy her wedding clothes, and ſet her forth according to the quality of her husband; forcing the ſumme upon him, with this further complement, that he knew his minde was great, but his fortunes ſmall: that is, if com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to thoſe of <hi>Pliny:</hi> but that <hi>Quintilian</hi> (as ſome from that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle do inferre) wanted in his old age, I can hardly credit, when I remember how another of his ſchollers admires his wealth.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Juv. Sat. 7.</bibl> 
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde igitur tot</l>
               <l>Quintilianus habet Salius?</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>How got Quintilian ſo much land then?</hi> Where <hi>Iuvenal</hi> makes him, for his fortunes, the miracle, the <hi>white crow</hi> of Rhetorick-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. I rather believe therefore, and the magnificence of the guift it ſelfe declares, that this was no ſupply of wants to <hi>Quintilian,</hi> but the expreſſion of gratitude in <hi>Pliny.</hi> Many great bounties he conferr'd, as upon <hi>Comus</hi> and <hi>Firmus,</hi> whoſe eſtates he made up
<pb facs="tcp:158486:9"/>
3125 ſterling, being the <hi>Cenſus Equeſtris,</hi> and enabling them to claime all the Priviledges of Gentlemen of <hi>Rome.</hi> He was likewiſe munificent to his nurſe and to diverſe other particulars, not forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the publique, for at <hi>Novo-Comum,</hi> the towne where he was borne, he founded a Free-ſchoole, which he liberally endowed, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning a third part of the revenues to the School-maſter, and build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and furniſhing a Library for the benefit of the ſtudents. Briefly his Wealth was ſo farre from needing addition, that when <hi>Cornelia</hi> offered him two hundred thouſand Seſtercij, for a piece of ground, he conceived it a great indignity that ſhe ſhould thinke any ſumme (how vaſt ſoever) could purchaſe the leaſt part of his inheritance. And as he ſcorned to ſell ignobly, ſo he did to gaine unworthily, for in patroniſing Cauſes he not onely forbore preſents and ordinary guifts, but refuſed New-years guifts. His houſe in <hi>Rome</hi> ſtood (where the chiefe of the <hi>Patricians</hi> lived) in the <hi>Eſquilian</hi> Mount, of all his Country houſes his favorite Villa's was that ſeated in the plaine, which he named the Comoedy: and that ſtanding upon the riſing of a bill, which he ſtiled the Tragoedy. He much delighted (like the old <hi>Romanes, Numa Pompilius,</hi> the <hi>Piſos,</hi> and the <hi>Fabij</hi>) in gard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and tillage, which was the reaſon (as I conceive) that made him give for the impreſſe of his Seale, a Waine. He had two wives, the firſt <hi>Calphurnia,</hi> the ſecond <hi>Pompeia Celerina,</hi> with whom he lived very contentedly, though without iſſue. The moſt learned of his friends were the Poëts, <hi>Virginius Romanus, Silius Italicus,</hi> and <hi>Valerius Martialis;</hi> the Hiſtorians, <hi>Suetonius Tranquillus,</hi> and <hi>Cornelius Tucitus;</hi> the Civill Lawyers, <hi>Pomponius Saturninus, Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Ariſto,</hi> and <hi>Cornelius Mutianus;</hi> Among which <hi>Tacitus</hi> was his Counſellour, <hi>Suetonius</hi> his companion, and <hi>Martial</hi> his Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner. Of all his Freed-men he eſpecially affected <hi>Zoſimus,</hi> who hath his maſters teſtimony for an honeſt, ſerviceable, and very learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man. His name is immortaliſed as well in the Hiſtory of <hi>Tacitus,</hi> as in his owne workes both <hi>Latine</hi> and <hi>Greeke,</hi> though (to the great prejudice of learning) of all their number now no more are extant, but onely this <hi>Panegyricke,</hi> his Epiſtles, and a little Treatiſe of men famous for Military and Civill government. His conſtant courſe when he writ any thing, was, firſt to cenſure himſelfe, then to heare others read it to him, after that to deſire his friends opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if he were not then ſatisfyed, to conſult two or three more; laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he would read his workes in a full Audience of the learned, which they now challenge by preſcription.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:158486:9"/>
            <head>PLINY'S<note n="a" place="margin">A <hi>Panegyrick</hi> is a publique Speech made in praiſe of any one <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifying praiſe and conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> Panegyricke.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lords,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ell and wiſely our fore-fathers inſtituted, that as our<note n="b" place="margin">The <hi>Romanes</hi> began their Actions with conſulting the gods by an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Inſtitute. <hi>Val. Max l.</hi> 1. That they ſo prefaced their Speeches, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by thoſe in <hi>Livy</hi> moſt of them begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Quod foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix fauſtumque ſit SPQR.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>actions</hi> ſo our <hi>ſpeeches</hi> ſhould begin with <hi>prayer;</hi> becauſe nothing can be rightly or providently begun by <hi>men,</hi> without the aſſiſtance, counſell, and honour of the <hi>Gods.</hi> Which cuſtome who is more concerned to practiſe, then the<note n="c" place="margin">Pliny.</note> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſul? or when ſhould it rather be received and obſerved, then now, when by command of <hi>Senate,</hi> and authority of the <hi>Republique</hi> we are enjoyned to preſent our thankes to the<note n="d" place="margin">Trajan.</note> beſt of <hi>Princes.</hi> For what more excellent or greater bounty of the gods, than a chaſt, reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, and a godlike Prince. And were there yet a doubt whether <hi>fortune</hi> or <hi>providence</hi> gave Rulers to the earth, it would be cleare howſoever, that the Deity<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Princes are of Jupiter. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. Iliad. β. <hi>The Caeſars are of God</hi> Vegetius.</note> beſtowed our Prince upon us; for not by the <hi>ſecret</hi> power of Fate, but <hi>publiquely</hi> and <hi>openly</hi> he was pointed out by <hi>Jupiter</hi> himſelfe, being elected betweeen the<note n="f" place="margin">The places for the 3 degrees of <hi>Roman</hi> Sacrifices were, to the Infernall Denyes <hi>Scrobieuli little furrowes,</hi> to the Terreſtriall, <hi>Arae</hi> the <hi>ſacred pavement</hi> or <hi>floore,</hi> to the Coeleſtiall <hi>Altaria</hi> named <hi>Altars</hi> from their <hi>exaltation.</hi>
               </note> ſacred pave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the Altar, in the very<note n="g" place="margin">The Temple of <hi>Jupiter</hi> in the Capitol, which had on each hand (within the ſame walls) the Temples of <hi>Juno</hi> and <hi>Minerva,</hi> and over all three one artificiall Eagle ſpread his wings.</note> place where that God is as preſent and reſident, as in the heaven and ſtarres: And therefore as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Religion, and this more particular Providence obliges us, we pray thee, <hi>Jupiter</hi> the<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jupiter</hi> was ſtiled Beſt for his favours to <hi>Rome.</hi> Greateſt for his owne power. <hi>Cicero pro domo ſua.</hi>
               </note> Beſt and Greateſt, formerly the<note n="i" place="margin">Founder of the Empire ſo, as they eſteemed him fountaine of the Deity, and primary Cauſe of all things.</note> 
               <hi>founder,</hi> now the <hi>preſerver</hi> of our Empire, that I may ſpeake things worthy the <hi>Conſul,</hi> the <hi>Senate,</hi> and the <hi>Prince;</hi> that in all I ſay there may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare freedom, integrity, and truth; and that the thanks I give may be as far from <hi>ſhew</hi> or <hi>colour,</hi> as they are from the <hi>neceſſity</hi> of flattery. Indeed not the <hi>Conſul</hi> only, but the whole <hi>State</hi> ſhould (as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) endeavour to ſay nothing of our <hi>Prince</hi> that may be applyable to another. Away therefore with thoſe expreſſions which our feare extorted, let us not ſpeake as formerly, becauſe we ſuffer not as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:158486:10"/>
nor let our publique addreſſes to the Prince be ſuch as once they were, becauſe our private whiſpers are not ſuch: let the diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of times be diſcerned in our Orations, and let the forme and manner of our thanks make it appeare to whom. For hitherto they have been directed as to a<note n="k" place="margin">In the ſecond Conſulſhip of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lpius Trajan,</hi> and <hi>Glabr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o</hi> (ſaith) A <hi>Caſſi ador<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> the ſtile <hi>Dominus et Deus, Lord</hi> and <hi>God,</hi> was aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian.</hi>
               </note> God, now no place is guilty of that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile blaſphemy. For we are not now to ſpeake of a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> but of a <hi>Patriot,</hi> not of a<note n="l" place="margin">Such a Lord as <hi>Domitian,</hi> a Lord of ſlaves.</note> 
               <hi>Lord</hi> but a <hi>Father;</hi> he eſteemes himſelfe one of us, and therefore tranſcends and excells us more, becauſe he eſteemes himſelfe but one of us, no leſſe remembring that he is a man, then that he is to governe men. Let us therefore underſtand our good, and prove our ſelves worthy ſuch a governour, often revolving in our hearts, whether we ſhould tender more ready obedience to Princes that delight in the ſervitude, or in the liberty of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. And accordingly with loud ſhouts the people of <hi>Rome</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaud the election of this Prince; with as perfect a conſent, as before they called<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Domitian,</hi> who under a faire outſide diſguiſed a ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannous Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</note> another handſome, they pronounce this valiant; and with the ſame acclamations wherewith they cryed up the <hi>voice</hi> and <hi>geſture</hi> of<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nero,</hi> who ſung and acted on the common Stage, both in <hi>Italy</hi> &amp; <hi>Greece.</hi>
               </note> another, they admire in this, his <hi>piety, continence,</hi> and <hi>mildneſſe.</hi> What ſhall we our ſelves, (my Lords) ſhall we likewiſe celebrate (as love and joy tranſported us) our Prince's divinity or humanity, temperance and facility of acceſſe? Now, what ſo ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, what ſo<note n="o" place="margin">The Senates decree for this ſurname of Beſt, the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſhoutes, and <hi>Trajan's</hi> teares, in this place but lightly touched are fully hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led neare the cloſe of the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negyricke.</hi>
               </note> Senatory, as that ſurname we give him of the beſt, which is made peculiar and proper to him, by the arrogance of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Princes. For how juſt it is, that we proclaime our ſelves happy and him happy, thus let him do, this he muſt heare, as if we would not <hi>ſay</hi> it unleſſe he would <hi>do</hi> it, ſo reciprocall are our votes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at his teares and frequent bluſhes ſpring; for he is ſenſible, that 'tis ſpoken to <hi>himſelfe,</hi> not to the <hi>Prince;</hi> the meaſure therefore that we together kept in theſe ſhoutes, the ſudden heat of piety, let us ſeverally obſerve in our premeditated ſpeeches. For we muſt know there is no kinde of thankes more ſincere and acceptable, then to emulate thoſe acclamations which have not time to be diſſembled. For my owne part, I will labour to ſubmit my diſcourſe to the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty and moderation of the Prince, and will no leſſe conſider what his eares can ſuffer, then what is due unto his virtue. A great and unuſuall glory of a Prince, to whom being to preſent our thankes, I do not ſo much feare that he ſhould thinke me too ſparing, as too prodigall in his praiſes; this care, this difficulty onely interpoſeth. For, my Lords, 'tis eaſy to give thankes to a deſerving man; becauſe there is no danger that when I mention his humanity, he ſhould ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:158486:10"/>
I taxe his pride; when I name his frugality that I meane his luxury; when his bounty, his avarice; when his goodneſſe, his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice; when his continence, his luſt; when his labour, his ſloath; when his valour, his cowardiſe. Nay, I do not ſo much as feare that I ſhall ſay too much or too little, for I obſerve, the Gods themſelves are not ſo much delighted with the accurate prayers of their adorers, as with their innocence and ſanctity, and do better accept of him that to their Temples brings a pure and chaſt minde, then a ſtudied verſe. But we muſt obey the <hi>Senate,</hi> which have pleaſed to decree for the publique good, that by the mouth of the <hi>Conſul</hi> under the title of Thankes, <hi>good</hi> Princes may know what they <hi>are</hi> to do, <hi>bad</hi> what they <hi>ought</hi> to do. And this is now more ſolemne and neceſſary, becauſe our parent hath forbidden our private, and would likewiſe have diſcharged our publique thankes, if he could have taken to himſelfe a liberty of prohibiting what the Senate hath commanded. In either (<note n="p" place="margin">The <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours had the ſtile of <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> from <hi>Juli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> from <hi>Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius</hi> of <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> or Sacred, which the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate decreed him, placing in his perſon the veneration and priviledge of conſecrated places, called <hi>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ca auguſta.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi>) you have ſhewen your moderation, both that elſwhere you would not ſuffer thankes, and that here you would. For this honour is not your ambition, but the action of your honourers, you give way to our deſires: nor are we compelled to ſpeake your deſerts, but you to heare. My Lords, I have often in my ſilent meditations thought of what compoſition he ought to be, who at his pleaſure ſhould diſpoſe of the Sea and Land, peace and warre; but when I formed and fancied to my ſelfe a Prince, I never, no not in my wiſhes, could conceive the like to him we now behold. Some one hath ſhined in <hi>warre,</hi> but gathered <hi>ruſt</hi> in <hi>peace;</hi> another wore his <hi>gowne</hi> with honour, but not his <hi>ſword;</hi> another inforced the people to a reverence by terrour, another courted them with humility; that loſt abroad the glory he had got at home; this at home what he had wonne abroad; to conclude, there hath as yet been none whoſe virtues were not ſoiled by confining upon ſome vice. But in our Prince how great a concord, how great a harmony of praiſes meets, inſomuch as his <hi>ſeverity</hi> takes off nothing from his <hi>affability,</hi> his <hi>gravity</hi> nothing from his <hi>candour,</hi> his <hi>Majeſty</hi> nothing from his <hi>humanity.</hi> Now his ſtrength and height of body, the honour of his head, the noble features of his face, adde to theſe the<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pliny</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count that make onely three diviſions of the Ages of Man, to wit, Childhood, Youth, &amp; old Age, for <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jan</hi> was 41, or (according to <hi>Dion</hi>) 42 when he began his Reigne.</note> prime of his yeares, nor without the ſpeciall bounty of the gods, the<note n="r" place="margin">Theſe gray haires to his young face, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt coſt <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jan</hi> his life, for the <hi>Agarenes</hi> kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w him in the battaile by thoſe markes, &amp; ſhot ſo well, as they killed the horſeman next him, <hi>Dion.</hi>
               </note> enſignes of age thus early ſpread upon his haires to increaſe his Majeſty; do not all theſe limne out a Prince in faireſt colours? ſuch he ought to be whom not civill warre, not the Common-Wealth oppreſſed with armes, but whom peace, and adoption, and appeaſed heaven would
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:158486:11"/>
beſtow upon the earth. Was it not fit there ſhould be a difference betwixt an Emperour, choſen by <hi>men,</hi> and one created by the <hi>Gods?</hi> whoſe choice of and favour to you <hi>Caeſar,</hi> even when you were to go Generall to the army, appeared ſhining, and that in a ſtrange manner. For other Princes had their happy preſages, conſulting ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the over-flowing bloud of ſacrifices, or the<note n="ſ" place="margin">Here Siniſter ſignifyes hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, for the right hand was held fortunate onely in humane things, but in Divine, the left.</note> ſiniſter flight of birds; but you going to your<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Trajan</hi> (then a private man) before he went to the Army being at his cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomary devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitol, a ſudden impulſion of ſpirit tooke the people without the Temple who cryed the Beſt, the Beſt, meaning <hi>Jupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> but deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Trajan</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward choſen in the ſame place, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with the ſame title.</note> accuſtomed devotions in the Capitol, the people though not intending it, even then ſaluted you their Prince, for the whole multitude that ſate at the Temple-gate, being ſhut when you were entred, as it was then ſuppoſed, ſaluted the God; but, as the event taught us, you their Emperour; ſo all under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the Omen, except your ſelfe, for you did refuſe the Empire, and it was well for us you did refuſe one that would not be denyed; you therefore were to be compelled, but compelled you could not be, ſave onely in the threatned change of the Common-Wealth, for you were obſtinate not to accept of the Empire upon any other tearmes, but to preſerve it. And to that end I verily beleive that fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and<note n="u" place="margin">By the <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torian</hi> muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neers; See the occaſion and carriage of that tumult in the Preface.</note> commotion happened in the Campe, becauſe a great vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and a great terrour was to be uſed to overpower your mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty. But as whirle-windes and tempeſts commend the calm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er temper of the skie, ſo to augment the graces of the peace, you brought, I do ſuppoſe that tumult to have uſhered it. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of man hath theſe ebbes and flowes, that adverſity may be<note n="*" place="margin">If it be good (ſaith <hi>Seneca</hi>) to know, then we muſt have both Proſperity and Adverſity, becauſe we cannot know the one without the other.</note> knowne by proſperity, and proſperity by adverſity; the ſeeds of both God ſo conceales, that commonly the cauſes of good and evill lye hidden under the contrary appearences. It was a great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front to the age, a great wound to the State, that an Emperour the parent of mankinde ſhould be aſſaulted, laid hands on, and kept pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, the power taken from the good old man even of giving<note n="x" place="margin">Of this in the Preface.</note> pardons; the Prince deprived of that which makes it happineſſe to be a Prince, to be<note n="(y)" place="margin">For Princes are lyable to no earthly power.</note> compelled to nothing. But yet if this alone was the reaſon that brought you to the publique preſervation, I could almoſt cry out, 'twas worth it. The diſcipline of warre was cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted that you might be the reformer, the worſt example was brought in, that the beſt might be oppoſed to it. Laſtly, the Prince was enforced to condemne thoſe he would have ſaved, that he might give us a Prince that could not be inforced. You ought long ſince to have been adopted, but we had not knowne how much the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:158486:11"/>
Empire is obliged to you, if you had been adopted ſooner. Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity waited for you, till it might be manifeſt that you had not ſo much received, as beſtowed a benefit. The trembling State fled for ſanctuary to your boſome, the ſhaken Empire ready to fall upon the Emperour, was by the Emperour's vote conferred on you; you were <hi>implored</hi> and <hi>ſent</hi> for to your adoption, as of old, great Generals when they were called home from a forraigne warre to aſſiſt their Country; ſo the ſonne and the father in one and the ſame inſtant ſhewed their higheſt mutuall gallantry: he gave the Empire to you, you returned it to him. You being as yet the onely man, that by <hi>receiving</hi> ſo great a favour hath <hi>requited</hi> it, and obliged the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; for you joyning with <hi>Caeſar,</hi> as his Imperiall Adjutant, <hi>you</hi> became more <hi>troubled,</hi> he more <hi>ſecure.</hi> O new and unheard of way unto a throne! not your owne ends, not your owne feare, but ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ends, another's feare made you a Prince. And howſoever you appeared to have attained the higheſt point of humane felicity, you did relinquiſh a farre happyer condition, ceaſing to be a private man under a good Prince, being aſſumed to the participation of his paines and cares; nor did the cheerfull and proſperous, but the ſharpe and hard times of the Empire compell you to accept it; you did receive it, when another repented him that he had received it. No tye of alliance or of friendſhip betwixt the Adoptour and the Adopted, but onely that both were beſt; the one worthy to <hi>chooſe,</hi> the other to be <hi>choſen.</hi> You therefore were adopted not as ſuch, or ſuch a one for his wives ſake, not a<note n="z" place="margin">As <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> who adopted his ſtep-ſonne <hi>Tiberius</hi>
               </note> ſtep-father, but a Prince adopted you into his family; the ſame minde made divine <hi>Nerva</hi> to become your father, that made him father of us all: nor ought a ſonne to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe aſſumed, that is aſſumed by a Prince. Were you to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the Armyes, Provinces, and Confederates of <hi>Rome,</hi> would you chooſe a ſucceſſour out of your wives boſome? and only look for an adoptive heire to the ſupreme power on earth, within the wals of your owne houſe? would you not caſt your eyes upon the City, &amp; eſteem him your neareſt Kinſman, him your deareſt friend, whom you found beſt, and likeſt to the Gods? He that muſt be choſen to command all, ought to be choſen out of all. For you are not then to give your ſervants a maſter, that you muſt leave them to your<note n="a" place="margin">There are in the Imperiall Law three ſorts of heires. The <hi>extraneus et voluntarius,</hi> who being a ſtranger may accept or refuſe to be heir. The Servant who is <hi>neceſſarius et involuntarius,</hi> for he hath not the liberty of refuſing. And the ſonne <hi>in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtate patris,</hi> who is <hi>neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius et ſuus,</hi> bound to be Heir by Law, but if he appeale to the Praetour may free him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in Equity.</note> neceſſary Heire. But you an Emperour are to bequeath a Prince to <hi>Rome.</hi> It were Pride and Tyranny to adopt any but one who you know muſt governe, if you had not adopted him. This <hi>Nerva</hi> did, conceiving no difference betwixt <hi>generation</hi> and <hi>election,</hi> if chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:158486:12"/>
ſhould be <hi>choſen</hi> with no more judgement, then they are <hi>begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten;</hi> ſave onely that the people with more patience ſuffer the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy iſſue,</hi> then the <hi>ill choice</hi> of Princes. He therefore, carefully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined this errour, nor men onely, but even the Gods likewiſe, were of counſell with him; not therefore in the<note n="b" place="margin">Where <hi>Livia</hi> and <hi>Agrippina</hi> had wrought their ſecond huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands <hi>Auguſtus</hi> and <hi>Claudius,</hi> to adopt their firſt husbands ſons, <hi>Tiberius</hi> and <hi>Nero.</hi>
               </note> bed-chamber, but in the Temple, not before the Geniall pillow, but before the cuſhion of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi> the Beſt &amp; Greateſt was the Election paſt, whereon at length, not our ſervitude, but our liberty, and preſervation, and ſecurity is founded. For the Gods challenge to themſelves this glory, it was their worke, it was their command: <hi>Nerva</hi> was but their Miniſter, both, as well he that elected, as you that were elected ſhewed your obedience. A<note n="c" place="margin">Letters of <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jan's</hi> victory o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the <hi>Panno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> or <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>garians,</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Roman</hi> cuſtome to ſtick Laurell in Pac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing newes of conqueſt, and feathers in ſuch as mentioned overthrowes, as I have noted in the end of the 4. <hi>Sat.</hi> of <hi>Iuven.</hi>
               </note> Lawrell was brought out of <hi>Pannonia,</hi> the Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to honour the Inauguration of our invincible Emperour with a marke of his owne victory. This the Emperour <hi>Nerva</hi> ſtuck in <hi>Jupiters</hi> boſome, when on the ſuddaine, there being a greater and more reverend aſſembly, then uſuall both of men and Gods, he aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med you for his ſonne, that is, for the ſupport of his ruinous Empire. From thenceforth with what ſecuritie, with what glory did he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy himſelfe, having laid downe his Soveraignty? For what diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence whether Soveraignty be <hi>laid downe,</hi> or <hi>divided,</hi> onely this is the more difficult. Then leaning as it were upon you, with your ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders he ſupported <hi>himſelfe</hi> and <hi>Rome;</hi> with your youth, with your ſtrength, he recovered his; immediately the tumult ceaſed, which was not the worke of the <hi>adoption,</hi> but of the <hi>adopted;</hi> and therefore <hi>Nerva</hi> had done raſhly had he pitched on any other. Do we forget, that lately after an adoption, the ſedition ended not, but began? It had beene a provocation to their fury, a firebrand to the tumult, unleſſe it had fallen on you. Who knowes not, that Emperour cannot give away his <hi>Empire,</hi> that hath loſt his <hi>reverence.</hi> This was effected by your authority, upon whom it was beſtowed. You were made a <hi>Sonne, Caeſar, Emperour</hi> and <hi>Collegue</hi> of the <hi>Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitian</hi> power, all theſe together, which not long ſince a reall<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Veſpaſian,</hi> who is here cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>reall,</hi> to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh him from an <hi>adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> father.</note> father conferred by parcells, only upon<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Titus,</hi> who only was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by his father <hi>Veſp.</hi> (and that at ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall times) to triumph with him, to be his Collegue in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, his fellow <hi>Cenſour</hi> and <hi>Tribune,</hi> and to ſigne letters and edicts with his name, yet <hi>Veſpaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> had another ſonne, ſuch as he was, <hi>Domitian.</hi>
               </note> one of his owne ſonnes. A migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty argument it was of your moderation, that you did not only pleaſe when you were a ſucceſſour, but when you were a ſharer &amp; compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in the Empire, for you muſt have been his <hi>ſucceſſor</hi> whether you would or not, but his <hi>companion</hi> not unleſſe you pleaſed. Will po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity beleive, that one who had a <hi>Patrician, Conſular,</hi> and <hi>Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phall</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:158486:12"/>
               <note n="f" place="margin">How <hi>Trajan's</hi> father merited his Triumph &amp; Conſulſhip, ſee the Preface.</note> father, being himſelfe <hi>Generall</hi> of a ſtrong, mighty, &amp; affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Armie, was not by that <hi>Army</hi> created Emperour? To whom when he commanded in chiefe our <hi>German</hi> Legions, the name of<note n="g" place="margin">Conquerour of the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes.</hi> This Inſcription in <hi>Trajan's</hi> coine, <hi>Iuvenal</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorates <hi>Sat.</hi> 6. (in the Brides firſt night's preſent) when ſhining in rich plate ſhe muſt behold <hi>Dacian</hi> and <hi>German Caeſar</hi> cut in gold. How the other ſtile of <hi>Dacicus</hi> was decreed him, ſee the preface.</note> 
               <hi>Germanicus</hi> was ſent from hence? he doing nothing to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe Emperour, but onely that he deſerved and obeyed: for <hi>(Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar)</hi> you obeyed, and came to your <hi>Soveraignty</hi> by <hi>duty,</hi> you never did any thing more with the mind of a <hi>Subject,</hi> then when you became a <hi>Prince.</hi> Now you are made <hi>Caeſar,</hi> now <hi>Emperour,</hi> now <hi>Germanicus</hi> in your abſence without your knowledge; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all theſe titles in what concernes your ſelfe a private man: It would ſeeme ſtrange if I ſhould ſay, you knew not you ſhould be an Emperour, you were an Emperour and knew it not. When the Meſſenger of your Fortune came, you had rather have continued what you were; but it was not in your power; ought not a <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> to obey his <hi>Prince,</hi> a <hi>Lieutenant</hi> his <hi>Generall,</hi> a <hi>ſonne</hi> his <hi>father?</hi> or elſe where were diſcipline, where the precedents ſhewed us by our Progenitors of undergoing contentedly whatſoever their Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals enjoyned? What if he had commanded you from Province to Province, from warre to warre? Do you thinke he cannot uſe the ſame authority to recall you to the Empire, that he uſed when he ſent you to the Armies? no difference, whether he command you to go forth the Emperours Lieutenant Generall, or to returne Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour; ſave onely that the glory of his obedience is the more, who does a thing againſt his will. It increaſed the authority of the Commander, that his authority had beene ſo dangerouſly diſputed, and it made you more<note n="h" place="margin">Good ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects the more they ſee others faile in their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, the more do they their duty.</note> inclinable to obedience; becauſe you ſawe others ſo averſe. Beſides, you heard the conſent of the Senate, and the People: That election was not onely <hi>Nerva's</hi> Judgement, for, whereſoever there are men their votes concurred; he onely by the right of Princes preceded, and did that firſt which all were about to do; queſtionleſſe it could not univerſally have pleaſed when it was done, if it had not pleaſed before. But, good Heaven! with what temper did you moderate your power and fortune? an <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour</hi> in <hi>ſtile, effigies,</hi> and <hi>ſtatue,</hi> but in <hi>modeſty, labour,</hi> and <hi>vigilancy,</hi> a <hi>Generall,</hi> a<note n="i" place="margin">In every Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes</hi> had a <hi>Praetour</hi> or chiefe Iuſtice to heare and determine cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and a <hi>Conſul</hi> or Generall for the warre, who if he ſtayed the ſecond yeare was called <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſul.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Proconſul,</hi> a <hi>common Souldier;</hi> while even then, you lead on your colours and Eagles by a long ſpace the formoſt man. Nor out of that adoption did you aſſume any thing more to your ſelfe, then the piety and obedience of a ſonne, you wiſhing to that name a long life, a long glory. The providence of God had raiſed you to the firſt place, yet ſtill you were contented with the ſecond,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:158486:13"/>
and your praier was that you might therein grow old: nor did you ever thinke your ſelfe Emperour while the other lived. Your praiers were heard, but ſo farre as was conſiſtent with the benefit of that beſt and Saint-like old man; whom the Gods called to Heaven, leſt after that divine and immortall act, he ſhould do any mortall buſineſſe: for this veneration is due unto the <hi>greateſt</hi> worke, that it ſhould be the <hi>laſt,</hi> and the Author immediately Deifyed, that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after poſterity might inquire if he were not a God when he did it. Thus he having no better right to the title of our common Parent, then by being yours, now great in glory, great in fame, when by clear experience he had found how well the Empire ſate upon your ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, he left the earth to you, and left you unto the earth; for that very reaſon dear &amp; wiſhed for by all men, becauſe he had provided that he might<note n="k" place="margin">Which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly that good old Prince had been, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he had choſen an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour.</note> not be wiſhed for. Whom as a ſonne you firſt honoured with your teares, then with a<note n="l" place="margin">The deifyed <hi>Caeſars</hi> had Temples dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to them, and Colledges of Prieſts na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med after them, of <hi>Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinus, Quiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nales,</hi> of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus, Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtales,</hi> of <hi>Ner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va, Nervales.</hi> The other rites of Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication read in <hi>Blondius</hi> his 2 booke of <hi>Rome</hi> Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant.</note> temple, not imitating thoſe that did the ſame, but with a different intention. <hi>Tiberius</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">All that <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius</hi> did, was (it ſeemes) thought to be done for ends, when his reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious offices eſcaped not juſt and probable cenſures.</note> Deifyed <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus,</hi> but to intaile the Majeſty of godhead upon the Crowne. <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi> Deifyed <hi>Claudius,</hi> but to<note n="n" place="margin">Witneſſe <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca's</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, [<hi>Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius his ridiculous Deification</hi> or purging to Heaven by a poiſoned <hi>Muſhrom</hi>] written no doubt to pleaſe his Pupill <hi>Nero.</hi>
               </note> laugh at him; <hi>Titus</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Who expected it, his words (when he thought he ſhould dye) being theſe, <hi>Vt puto Deus fio. I think I am turning God, Suetonius.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Vespaſian, Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian Titus,</hi> but that to appeare the ſonne, and<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Domitian</hi> who after h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s brothers death deifyed him that he himſelf might in his life-time be worſhipped as a Deity.</note> this the brother to a God. You have inſerted your father among the ſtarres, not to beget feare in men, not to put an affront upon the Gods, not to honour your ſelfe; but becauſe you beleived him to be a Deity. It takes off from ſuch an act, when it is done by thoſe that thinke themſelves are Gods. But although you have conſecrated to him Altars, Cuſhions, Carpets, and a<note n="q" place="margin">A Prieſt, named <hi>Flamen</hi> of his Miter or Tiara, which in old Latine was called <hi>Flama.</hi>
               </note> Flamen, you have not made or proved him a God in any thing ſo much, as that you your ſelfe are like him; for in a Prince that dyes when he hath choſen one to ſucceed him, the onely and aſſured faith of his Divinitie is a good ſucceſſour. But hath this immortality in your father bred any arrogance in you? do you imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the late ſloathfull and proud kinſmen to Divinity? or do you e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulate the Ancients that founded this Empire, which our foes have lately invaded and ſcorned? of whoſe overthrow and flight, we have had no other proofes, but meerly the<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Domitian,</hi> under the name of conquer'd enemies, triumphed for his owne army loſt in <hi>Daeia. Oroſius.</hi>
               </note> ſight of triumphes: therefore they have got ſpirit and ſhooke off their yoke; nor did they now contend with us for their owne liberty, but for our ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:158486:13"/>
not ſo much as admitting of a truce, but upon equall tearmes, and gave whereas they ſhould receive the law. But now all return to their feare and terrour, and deſire of obeying; for they now behold a Roman<note n="ſ" place="margin">Trajan.</note> Generall of the old ſtraine, one of thoſe that gained the<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Imperator</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a <hi>Generall,</hi> or one that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in Chiefe.</note> Imperiall title by fields covered with ſlaughter, and ſeas ſtained with victories; therefore we <hi>receive</hi> hoſtages, we do not <hi>buy</hi> them; nor with infinite loſſe and exceſſive preſents do we make our peace. As if we had already conquered them, they petition they ſupplicate, we grant, we deny; both proceeding from the Majeſty of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire; they give thankes if their ſuits be granted, nor dare they if denyed complaine: for how ſhould they dare, that know you have curbed a hardy<note n="u" place="margin">The <hi>Germans.</hi>
               </note> people in a ſeaſon moſt favourable to them, moſt inſufferable to us, when the river of<note n="*" place="margin">Known like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by the name of <hi>Ister,</hi> and in old time called <hi>Mato<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Danubius</hi> made a bridge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt his bankes, and being frozen over bore upon his backe a mighty warre: when that fierce Nation was not more armed with their darts, then with their <hi>aire</hi> and <hi>climate.</hi> But at our approaches as if the ſeaſon had been changed, they kept within their holes and caves, and our partyes marched along the bankes, and would you have permitted us to make uſe of their advantages, we had with joy turned upon the Barbarians their owne winter. You were in this veneration with your enemies, what with your Souldiers? what ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration did you gaine, and how? when with you they were a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie; with you they ſuffered thirſt; when in the very excerciſing of your Troopes you mingled the Generals duſt and ſweat with theirs, differing from the reſt in nothing, but in excellency of ſtrength and ſpirit, freely charging, and receiving the charge: now ſhaking your pile in a cloſe encounter; now ſtanding while another darted his, encouraging the valour of your men, and rejoycing when they ſtrucke the heavieſt blowes upon your ſheild or helmet. For your ſelfe commended the bold charger, and praiſed him into farther boldneſſe; and what did they not dare, when they had you for a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctatour and judge of their firſt skirmiſhes; you viewing if their armes were fixed, weighing their darts, &amp; if any thought his pile too heavy, throwing it your ſelf? What! when you comforted the weary, and releived the hurt? it was never your faſhion to enter your own pavilion till you had viſited your fellow-Souldiers tents, nor to take repoſe, but laſt of all. Nor ſhould I ſo admire our Generall, if he had been ſuch among the<note n="x" place="margin">Theſe fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies (the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricij, Scipio's</hi> &amp; <hi>Camilli</hi>) were not more famed for valour, then formoderation, being in all their conqueſts onely inriched with honour.</note> 
               <hi>Fabricij,</hi> the <hi>Scipio's,</hi> or <hi>Camilli,</hi> for then it had been the heat of imitation, and happily ſome one better then himſelf might have inflamed him. But after the profeſſion of armes
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:158486:14"/>
was fallen from the hand to the eye, from labour to pleaſure; when we had to<note n="y" place="margin">The Romans were firſt taught to uſe their armes by <hi>P. Rutilius</hi> the Conſul.</note> traine and exerciſe us no <hi>Veteran,</hi> [no old <hi>Roman</hi> Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier] that had wonne the<note n="z" place="margin">The Morall Crowne was beſtowed on him that firſt ſcaled the wals, and therefore reſembled bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlements.</note> 
               <hi>Murall</hi> or the<note n="a" place="margin">The Civicke or Oaken Crowne, was given by the Generall to him that reſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Citizen of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſo its here under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood; but in proceſſe of time it was likewiſe given by the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to the Generall, if he ſpared a Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens life when it was forfeited by Martial Law.</note> 
               <hi>Civick</hi> honour, but a pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty fine<note n="b" place="margin">The Greekes ('tis <hi>Plutarch's</hi> note) ſtudied the arts of fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and wraſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſo long, till they loſt their Country. And now thoſe wits live upon the little Gambers, that ruin'd them. Read the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a hungry <hi>Greeke, Juvenal. Sat.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Greeke</hi>-Maſter, how ſtrange it is now, to ſee one of all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting in the manners of his Country, and without a rivall or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, ſtriving and contending with himſelfe; and as he reignes alone, ſo he alone to deſerve to reigne! Were not you <hi>(Caeſar)</hi> bred up to theſe gloryes from your infancy? while yet a youth, adding your <hi>Parthian</hi> lawrell to your fathers honours, you even then me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited the title of <hi>Germanicus?</hi> when the borderers informing you of the <hi>Parthian</hi> in roads, you quenched their pride &amp; cruelty with a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty terrour, joyning in admiration of you the rivers of<note n="c" place="margin">A river that runs through <hi>Cappadocia, Meſopotamia, Aſſyria,</hi> and the midſt of <hi>Babylon. Tigris,</hi> this, and <hi>Ganges</hi> are the nobleſt rivers of <hi>Aſia.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Euphrates,</hi> &amp; the<note n="d" place="margin">The famous river that parts <hi>Germany</hi> from <hi>Belgia,</hi> and after a courſe of 300 miles, fals into the <hi>Moſe</hi> and the <hi>German Ocean.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Rhene;</hi> yet then, you never marched ſo farre in <hi>Perſon,</hi> as in <hi>fame,</hi> appearing ſtill greater, and more glorious in your laſt quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Yet hitherto you were not Emperour, hitherto not ſonne unto a God: and though <hi>Germany</hi> is guarded with a multitude of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent people, made defenſible by nature with infinite ſpaces of deſert earth, bulwark'd with the<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> Alpes <hi>divide</hi> Germany <hi>and</hi> France <hi>from</hi> Italy; the Pyrenaan <hi>moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines,</hi> Spaine <hi>from</hi> France.</note> 
               <hi>Alpes,</hi> and <hi>Pyrenaean</hi> mountaines, and diverſe other mighty hils, if not compared to theſe. Yet when through all this tract you <hi>lead</hi> your Army or rather (ſuch was your ſwiftnes) <hi>tranſported</hi> it, you never ſo much as called for your Coach or Horſe, which was a hunting nagge and followed after, not for uſe, but ornament; for you had no ſervice for him, unleſſe upon a <hi>Stative</hi> day [when you had pitched your battaile] you made it your recreation to gallop over the adjacent fields. Shall I wonder at the beginning of your induſtry, or the end? 'tis much you ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere, but more that you never fear'd, you were not able to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere. Nor do I doubt but that<note n="f" place="margin">Domitian.</note> he (who commanded you his beſt protection) then as farre off as <hi>Spaine,</hi> to undertake the <hi>German</hi> warre, he being a ſloathfull Generall, and envying others virtues, which himſelfe had uſe of, conceived as great an admiration of you, not without ſome feare; as once that<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hercules,</hi> ſon to <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Alcmena,</hi> whom the tyrant <hi>Eryſtheus</hi> enjoyned thoſe 12 labours that inſtead of deſtroying him (as they were intended) immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taliſed his name, now given as a title of honour to the indefatigable Conquerour.</note> ſonne of <hi>Jupiter</hi> having per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed his labours ſtrucke into his Prince, when after all his hard commands he ſtill returned victorious, and unwearyed: while you
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:158486:14"/>
being put upon one expedition after another were ſtill found wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of new imployment, When you were a <hi>Tribune</hi> in your tender yeares, you marched through many ſeverall Countryes, with the vigour of a man, fortune even then inſpiring you to know by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, what you ſhould command at once. You not contenting your ſelfe to view the Campe at diſtance, as with a proſpective-glaſſe, and to ſlubber over a ſhort warre, but performing the office of<note n="h" place="margin">A M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>litary Tribune, whoſe office was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to that of our Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant Major Generall.</note> a <hi>Tribune,</hi> that you might immediately deſerve to be a <hi>Generall;</hi> and that you might have nothing to <hi>learne</hi> at the time wherein you ſhould be called to <hi>teach.</hi> By tenne [annuall]<note n="i" place="margin">This Pay cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſtipends, the Souldiers had either half-yearly, or (as in this place) yearely.</note> ſtipends you knewe the manners of people, ſituations of Countries, opportunities of places; and by your patience made the diverſe tempers of their water and ayre as familiar to your body, as your owne Country ſprings, as your owne Country climate. How often [as publique preſents to your merit] have you changed your victorious horſe and armes? the time ſhall come therefore that poſterity ſhall go themſelves, and take their ſonnes along with them, to ſee what field hath drunke your ſweat, what tree hath canopyed your meat, what caves have beene your bed-chamber; laſtly, what houſe hath entertayned ſo great a gueſt, as then in many places you your ſelfe were ſhewed the ſacred ſteppes of mighty Generals. But this was long ago, now, he is accounted an old Souldier, that hath been your fellow Souldier. For where is he, whoſe fellow Souldier you were not, before you were his Generall? This is the reaſon why you call almoſt all your Army by their names: that you your ſelfe are the Chronicle of every private Souldiers valiant acts; no one can ſhew you a wound received for his Country, to which you were not a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and a praiſer when 'twas made. But your moderation is rather to be inſiſted on, that you being bred to warres, do yet love peace. Nor do you (becauſe you had a triumphall father, or becauſe your owne lawrell was conſecrated to <hi>Jupiter Capitoline</hi> on the day of your adoption) on all occaſions therefore ſeeke for triumphes; you <hi>feare</hi> not the war, nor <hi>provoke</hi> it. 'Tis a mighty matter, (moſt dread Emperour) a mighty matter to ſtand upon the banke of <hi>Danubius,</hi> if you paſſe, certaine of triumph, yet not ambitious to force them to battaile that decline it; the one whereof is the act of valour, the other of moderation; for your moderation was the cauſe that you would not fight; your valour that the<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Decebalus</hi> King of <hi>Dacia,</hi> of whom in the Preface.</note> enemy would not: neither did any thing but the contempt of the Empire ever make us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours. The Capitol therefore ſhall receive no counterfeit Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:158486:15"/>
no falſe<note n="l" place="margin">As thoſe Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues (in the Preface) which for a falſe-na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Victory over <hi>Decebalus</hi> were decreed to <hi>Domitian,</hi> who made ſhow of triumph after his returne to <hi>Rome,</hi> but (as <hi>Dion</hi> notes) the people ſaid he celebrated the funerals of his Army loſt in <hi>Dacia.</hi>
               </note> pictures of victory, but ſhall be filled (our Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour bringing home true and ſolid glory) with peace, and the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged homage of our foes, ſo, as there will be no one to be conquered: this is beyond all triumphes. But if ſome<note n="m" place="margin">Meaning <hi>Decebalus.</hi>
               </note> Barbarous Prince ſhall grow to that inſolence and madneſſe as to merit your indignation. Let him be ſure whether he be defenced with vaſt ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, or mountainous precipices; he ſhall finde all theſe as ſubmiſſe, and yeilding to your virtues, as if the rivers were<note n="n" place="margin">This may ſeeme high Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbole and meer ſpeculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at firſt ſight, but it was glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly reduced into act by <hi>Trajan's</hi> mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous bridge over <hi>Danubius,</hi> as in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face.</note> drained, the mountaines levelled, the ſea it ſelfe ſwallowed up, and our fleet not landed, but our land it ſelfe brought over to him. Me-thinkes I now behold a triumph not heavy laden with the ſpoiles of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, or gold extorted from our Confederates, and allyes; but with hoſtile armes, and chaines of captive Princes. Me-thinkes I heare our men running over alowd the high and mighty names of Generals, and pointing to the bodyes ſutable to thoſe names. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinkes while with their hands bound they paſſe on foot, you fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in your chariot, as treading on the neckes of conquered nations, and before you the ſheilds, which you your ſelfe have pierced. Nor ſhall you want the ſpoiles<note n="o" place="margin">The <hi>Spolia O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pima</hi> [the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals Armes] were ſtill by the Conquerour dedicated to <hi>Jupiter Fere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trius. Jove the ſtriker,</hi> becauſe it was beleived that without <hi>Jupiters</hi> ſpecial aſſiſtance, one Generall could not hit another.</note> Opime, [ſuch as one Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall wins that takes another] if there be a Prince that dares con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend. Nor ſhall the caſting of your darts alone, but of your eyes and frownes, make all the field, and the enemies whole Army tremble. You have deſerved by your late moderation, that when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the dignity of the Empire forceth you either to invade or to repell an enemy, that it ſhould not be thought you conquer, that you might triumph, but that you triumph becauſe you have conquered. One thing mindes me of another; how noble a worke it is that you have revived the decayed and extinguiſhed diſcipline of warre, curing the Evill of the former age, ſloath and contuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and the ſcorne of obeying. 'Tis ſafe to merit reverence; 'tis ſafe to merit love: nor is he a Generall that feares not to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, or that feares to be beloved; and ſo alike ſecure of hate and love they view the workes, are preſent when the Souldiers exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, they fixe the armes, the wals and men. For he is no Prince that thinkes thoſe ſtratagems deſigned againſt himſelfe, that are prepared againſt his enemies; which was a perſwaſion of theirs, that doing of hoſtile acts, feared the like meaſure. In that time, therefore not onely the military profeſſion and mens ſpirits langui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, but their bodyes too, ſwords were dulled, their edge taken off with neglect; while our Generals feared not ſo much the ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:158486:15"/>
of forraigne Kings, as of their owne Princes; nor their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies hands and ſwords ſo much, as their owne fellow Souldiers. It is the nature of the Starres, that the ſmall and meaner are obſcure when the great ones riſe; ſo by an Emperours preſence, the honour of his Lieutenants is eclypſed; but you were indeed greater then all, but without diminution to any: every one retayned the ſame authority when you were preſent, as when you were abſent; nay, many reſpected them more, becauſe you did reſpect them. Thus therefore you indeared your ſelfe to the higheſt, and the loweſt, thus you made your ſelfe a mixt perſon, a Generall, and a common Souldier: ſo as you both tooke an account of their exerciſes, and labours, as a Commander, and a Cenſour; &amp; as a fellow and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion releived them. Happy are they whoſe fidelity and induſtry is knowne not by meſſengers, and interpreters, but by your ſelfe; nor with your eares, but with your eyes: and that have gained this further favour, that when you are abſent, you will beleive no cenſure of an abſent Souldier ſooner then your owne. Now the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of <hi>Rome</hi> recalled you, and your love unto your Souldiers was vanquiſhed with the love you bare your Country. Your journey from the warre was calme and modeſt, as if you had returned from a well ſetled peace. Nor indeed will I inſert among your praiſes, that no father, no husband feared your comming: others have af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected chaſtity, in you it was inbred and naturall, and ſo to be num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred with thoſe virtues you cannot ſtile your owne. No tumult in exacting for your carriages; no nicetie in taking up your lodgings, ſuch yours as others diet; to this, your march was ſo quicke, and ſo free a progreſſe, as one would thinke it to be ſome great Generall (and eſpecially your ſelfe) going to the army. Such little or no difference was betwixt our Emperour before, and after his creation. How unlike to this was lately the march of<note n="p" place="margin">Domitian.</note> another Prince (if it was a march, not a deſigne of ſpoile and deſolation) when he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſed the owners of their houſes, burned downe, and laid waſt all on the right hand, and on the left, as if ſome enemy had fallen upon us; or thoſe very<note n="q" place="margin">The <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, Dacians,</hi> or <hi>Sarmatians,</hi> who had all foyled <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian.</hi>
               </note> Barbarians from whom he fled? the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces ought to have beene perſwaded that that was <hi>Domitians,</hi> not the <hi>Prince's</hi> Journey. And therefore not for your owne glory, but for the publique benefit you commanded that your edict ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly particulariſe the expences both of his and your owne <hi>German</hi> expedition. Let an Emperour accuſtome himſelfe to reckon with his Empire, ſo let him go forth, and ſo returne, as if he were to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:158486:16"/>
give in his accounts, let him caſt up what he hath ſpent; ſo he ſhall never ſpend what he may be aſhamed to ſpeake of. Beſides, thereby ſucceeding Princes whether they will or no ſhall under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, thus much it will coſt them: and two examples being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, they ſhall remember that men will accordingly conjecture of their diſpoſition, as they ſhall chooſe this, or that. For theſe, ſo many and ſo great merits did you deſerve no new honours, no new titles? nay, you refuſed the name of Father of your Country; what a long combate had we with your modeſty? how ſlowly did we overcome? that name which others inſtantly upon their Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation day, received as they did that of Emperour and <hi>Caeſar,</hi> you put off ſo long, till you your ſelfe, the ſevereſt Iudge of your owne merit, could not but confeſſe that you deſerved it. And therefore of all, it was your onely fortune, to <hi>be</hi> the <hi>Father</hi> of your Country, before you were ſo <hi>declared.</hi> For, you were ſo in our hearts, in our judgements: nor would the publique piety have ſtood upon the name, unleſſe to our ſelves we ſhould have appeared ingratefull, to call you rather <hi>Emperour</hi> and <hi>Caeſar,</hi> when we had by experience found you to be a <hi>Father.</hi> Which appellation, with what bounty, with what favour do you exerciſe! That you live with your people as a Father with his Children! That returning our Emperour, you carry your ſelfe towards us, we behave our ſelves towards you, as if you were that private perſon you went forth! you ſtill thinke both your ſelfe and us the ſame; you being ſuch as we are all, onely by ſo much greater then others, by how much better. And in the firſt place, what a day it was, how long wiſhed for, and expected, when you made your entrance to the City! Nay, the very manner of your entrance, how rare and pleaſing! For, whereas former Princes uſed to be brought and carried in, I do not ſay in their Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots, drawen with foure milke-white ſteeds, but which is more ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogant, on mens ſhoulders; You onely more conſpicuous, and more exalted then others by your height of bodie, did not make your triumph over our patience, but over the pride of Princes. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no age, no infirmity, no ſexe retarded any from feaſting their eyes with ſo unuſuall a ſight. The little Children were brought forth to ſee you, the young men gloried in you, the old men admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red you; even the ſicke neglecting the commands of their Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans crept into your ſight. as if that were their health. Some ſaid they had lived long enough now they had beheld you and waited upon you; others ſaid, that now was the beſt time of living. The
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:158486:16"/>
very women then tooke the greateſt joy in being Mothers, when they ſaw to what a Prince they had bred Subjects, to what a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall they had brought forth Souldiers. One might ſee roofes of houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es loaded, and labouring with the weight of people; not ſo much as that place vacant, where the adventrous ſtander ſeemed to fall; the ſtreets all over-crowded, onely a narrow paſſage left for you: the multitudes of both ſides cheerfull, every where like joy, like accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations. The rejoycing at your comming (being in all men as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall, as your carriage towards all) grew ſtill more as you came on, and increaſed almoſt at every ſteppe. It pleaſed all <hi>Rome</hi> that you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned that kiſſe unto the Senate, which they gave to you at parting; it pleaſed, that the <hi>Roman</hi> Knights received a greater honour then their order, while you ſaluted them by their names without a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancer. It pleaſed, that you would not onely take notice of your<note n="r" place="margin">Retainers to <hi>Trajan</hi> as a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate man; for Clients were dependent on the Nobility their Patrons, who were bound in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to protect them, as Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents were in duty and on paine of death to be faithfull to their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons.</note> 
               <hi>Clients,</hi> but added certaine markes of familiarity. But it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed moſt, that the people likewiſe were ſuffered to come near, nay e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to come cloſe to you, that the very firſt day you truſted your perſon to us all: you were not <hi>incloſed</hi> with your guard, but <hi>free</hi> and <hi>open</hi> for the whole towne to flow about you; now the Senate, now the order of Knights, according as either made the frequencie of their addreſſes. Your Lictours followed ſilent and quiet; as for your Souldiers, they differed not at all from the people in habite, civilitie, or modeſtie. But when you came to aſcend the Capitol, how com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable to all was the remembrance of your adoption, and what a particular joy to them who in that place had firſt ſaluted you Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. Nay, I beleive, the very God himſelfe tooke an eſpeciall plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in beholding his owne worke, but when you ſtood in the ſame place where your father did when he publiſhed that great ſecret of the Gods, how the aſſembly exulted through all the temple! how were the old acclamations revived? how like was that day unto the day that did beget it? how like were the Altars to themſelves exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Sacrifices for him upon whoſe health and ſafety ours de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends, all knowing they pray for themſelves and their children, when they pray for you! Thence you went indeed to your Palace; but with that looke, but with that moderation, as if you had reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into your private houſe, the reſt to their dwellings, every one there iterating the trueſt teſtimony of his joy, by rejoycing without witneſſes. Some Prince had beene undone by ſuch an entrance, but you daily grew more admirable, more worthy. Such, in a word, you are, as other Princes onely promiſe they will be; you therefore
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:158486:17"/>
are the onely Emperour whom length of time commends and addes unto you, joyning &amp; incorporating two formerly inconſiſtent things, the ſecuritie of a Governour, and the modeſty of a beginner; you do not caſt downe the imbraces of your ſubjects to your feet, nor ſuffer them to kiſſe your hand; our Emperour hath the ſame Civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie he had; he did uſe to go on foot, he goes ſo ſtill: he did rejoice in labour, ſo he doth. Fortune hath changed all about you, but hath not changed your ſelf. Tis free for every man when the Prince walkes abroad, to ſtand, to meet, to waite upon him, to paſſe by him; you come not by chance among us, and make your ſelfe familiar with us to upbraid us with it. Every one hath acceſſe unto your perſon; and his owne modeſty, not your pride, puts an end to his diſcourſe. We are indeed govern'd by you, and ſubject to you, but as we are unto the Lawes, for they regulate our wils and inordinate deſires, yet they converſe with us, and remaine among us. You are eminent and do excell, as honour and authority, which are indeed above men, yet to men they appertaine. Formerly Princes in ſcorne of us, and out of a certaine feare of equality had loſt the uſe of their legs, theſe therefore their ſervants neckes and ſhoulders carried over our heads: but you fame, glorie, and the piety of your ſubjects raiſeth above thoſe Princes; the earth lifts up you to heaven, ſo inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingled are our Prince's ſteppes with ours. Nor do I feare (my Lords) that you will thinke I ſpeake too long, ſince it is cheifly to be deſired that the things for which thankes are given to a Prince ſhould be many, which I might with more reverence leave untou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and intire to your memories, then paſſe them over ſlightly and abruptly; becauſe it often happens, that onely what we conceale is thought to appeare in its juſt proportions. Unleſſe you pleaſe to give me leave to touch briefly his inriching of the Tribes, giving the people their<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Congiary</hi> (a word derived from the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure <hi>Congius</hi> that held about a gallon and a Pynt) was properly the bounty of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours to the people, as <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>native</hi> was their Imperiall munifience to the Souldier.</note> 
               <hi>Congiary,</hi> and that whole, when the Souldiers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived but part of their Donative. Is it an argument of a common ſpirit to preferre them in his bounty, whom he might ſafer have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied? yet even in the making of this difference, the rule of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion was obſerved, for the Souldiers were equalled to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by receiving a part, but firſt; the people to the Souldiers by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in the ſecond place, but receiving all at once. Nay, how bountifully was it diſtributed? how carefull were you that none ſhould go without your bounty? It was given to thoſe it was not promiſed to, they being put in ſince your Edict in the place of names croſſed out. Some were detained with buiſineſſe, others with ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:158486:17"/>
he was at Sea, this upon the river, it was laid up for them, and provided, that no one ſhould be ſick, no one imployed, no one abſent, let every one come when he would, come when he could. <hi>Caeſar,</hi> it was magnificent and your owne, as it were to bring together farre diſtant Countries with a miracle of bounty, to contract vaſt ſpaces with your munificence, to prevent chance, to way-lay fortune, &amp; by your power to make it ſo, that none of the Commons, when you gave your Congiary, ſhould be more ſenſible of his being a <hi>man,</hi> then of his being a <hi>denizon</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> Upon the Congiary day it was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly the cuſtome for ſwarmes of Infants, the future people, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the Prince comming abroad, the Parents tooke great paines to ſhew him their little ones, to ſet them upon their ſhoulders, and to teach them words of ſoft and flattering Courtſhip, the children ſpake as they were prompted, and many times gabled to the deafe eares of the Prince with fruitleſſe praiers; neither knowing what they beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, nor what they had not obtained, till they grew ſo old as to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand their wants. You did not ſo much as ſtay to be petitioned, and though it was a moſt delightfull object to have the <hi>Roman</hi> off-ſpring in your eie, yet before they ſaw you, or came into your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, you commanded they ſhould all be taken notice of, and their names enrolled, that from their very infancie they might have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of your being their publique parent by their education: you would have them bred at your owne <hi>charges,</hi> that were bred for your owne <hi>ſervice,</hi> and ſo brought by your <hi>penſion</hi> to your <hi>pay:</hi> and that they might all owe as much to you, as every one doth to his particular parent. You doe wiſely. <hi>Caeſar,</hi> to beat the charges of perpetuating the <hi>Roman</hi> name, for there is no kind of expenſe more worthy a Prince, and that will more eterniſe his memory, then what is laid out upon poſteritie. To breed up their children the rich are encouraged by<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tacitus l.</hi> 15. Fathers [in the Nobility and Gentry] had right to ſtand for Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, to caſt lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s for Provinces, to be heires by Will, being (ſaies <hi>Juvenal Sat.</hi> 9) capable of all, whether pure Legacies, or conditionall. Theſe privile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges Bachelours wanted, and withall were fined for their contempt of Marriage. The Law <hi>de mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandis ordinibus</hi> was prefer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'d by <hi>Q. Metellus,</hi> revived by <hi>Aug. Caeſar.</hi>
               </note> great rewards and equall puniſhments, but the poore to take care for theirs have onely one reaſon, a good Prince. Now children borne for his ſervice, unleſſe with a munificent hand he cheriſh, feed, and embrace them, he haſtens the ſun-ſet of the Empire, the ſun-ſet of the State; in vain a Prince neglecting the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munalty, like a head to a defective body, maintaines a bulke ſtagger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with an unballanced weight. 'Tis eaſie to ſuppoſe what joy you tooke, when the ſhouts of parents and children, old men and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants entertained you. The firſt words that were ever ſpoken by your little ſubjects ſaluted your eare, on whom, when you beſtowed their education, you made your bountie greater, by not ſuffering them to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:158486:18"/>
aske. But 'tis beyond all your goodneſſes, that you your ſelf are ſuch, that to breed up their children under you they delight, nay they hold it neceſſary; no parents now feare their children, unleſſe they feare nature, and the accidents of humane frailty; nor among incurable diſeaſes is the Princes diſpleaſure numbred. It is indeed a great en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to educate children in hope of <hi>alimonie,</hi> in hope of Congiary, but 'tis a greater to breede them in hope of <hi>liberty,</hi> in hope of ſecurity. And therfore let the Prince giue nothing, ſo he take away nothing; let him not <hi>maintaine,</hi> ſo he will not <hi>deſtroy,</hi> yet we ſhall not want thoſe that will covet to have iſſue. Contrarily, let him give and<note n="u" place="margin">As <hi>Domitian.</hi> whoſe very fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings (as in his Character in the Preface) were defrayed with bloody confiſcations.</note> take away, maintaine and deſtroy, truely in a ſhort time he will cauſe all to repent not only their childrens but their own be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and their parents. Therefore in all your Bounty I commend no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more, then that you beſtow the Congiarie out of your owne, the Alimonie out of your owne, not feeding your Subjects (as wilde beaſts their young ones) with blood and ſlaughter, and which is moſt welcome to the receivers, they know what is <hi>given</hi> to <hi>them,</hi> is not <hi>forced</hi> from <hi>any,</hi> and for the inriching of ſo many, no one is made poorer, but the Prince alone; yet not hee neither, for hee who hath what all have, hee himſelfe hath as much as all. Your numerous glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry calleth me another way. another way? as how? Have I then ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently admired and honoured your beſtowing ſo much mony, not that conſcious of a crime you might ſtop the mouth of fame from fol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowing it againſt you, nor to divert mens black and ſad diſcourſes by offering them more comfortable matter; you redeemed no <hi>offence</hi> with your Congiary, no<note n="*" place="margin">As <hi>Nero</hi> (after poyſoning <hi>Germanicus</hi> &amp; the murthering of his mother <hi>Agrippina</hi>) who diſtributed mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ney, ſet forth ſhowes, &amp; gave rich preſents to particular men. <hi>Tacitus. Dion.</hi>
               </note> cruelty with your Alimony; neither was it the cauſe of your well doing, that what you had done ill might paſſe uncenſured; with all theſe ſummes it was <hi>love,</hi> not <hi>favor</hi> that you purchaſed, and the people of <hi>Rome</hi> departed from your Tribunall, <hi>obliged</hi> not <hi>appenſed;</hi> You offered your Congiary, joyfull to the joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſecure to the ſecure, and what other Princes caſt before the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſwelling ſpirits, to take off their odium, you gave the people with as innocent a heart as they received it. My Lords, little leſſe then five thouſand free-borne <hi>Romans</hi> were thoſe whom the bounty of our Prince ſought out, found, and enrolled. Theſe, the ſtrength of warre, the ornament of peace, are educated at his publique charge, and learne to love their Country, not as their Country, but their Nurſe. Out of theſe our armies are recruited, our tribes repleniſhed, out of theſe in time will ſpring ſuch as ſhall have no neede of Alimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. The Gods give you <hi>Caeſar</hi> the long life you merit, and <hi>keepe</hi> you
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:158486:18"/>
in that minde, which they have <hi>given</hi> you, and the greater you ſee the bead role of the Infants growen ever when you reade it (for it ſwels and increaſes daily, not becauſe children are dearer to parents, but Subjects to the Prince) give them Congiaries if you pleaſe, howſoever they are borne to ſerve you. As a perpetuall Congiarie I eſteeme the affluence of corne, the care whereof long ſince added no leſſe glory to<note n="x" place="margin">Who to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh <hi>Rome</hi> in a dearth, ſayled to <hi>Sicily, Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinia</hi> and <hi>Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> &amp; returning wi h plenty, when the Pylot durſt not put to Sea the ſtorme was ſo terrible, <hi>Pompey</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe went firſt aboard, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them to weigh Anchor, &amp; cryed. Tis ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſayle, not neceſſary to live <hi>Plut.</hi> in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta <hi>Pompeij.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Pompey,</hi> than his baniſhing ambition from the<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Campus Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> the <hi>Fields</hi> wherin Electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Magiſtrates was made wher <hi>Pompey</hi> would not ſuffer the ſale of Offices.</note> fields, beating the enemy from the Sea, and purging the<note n="z" place="margin">Where hee fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed the war, ſubduing <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tius Jarbus</hi> and all <hi>Africa</hi> in 40 dayes, for which <hi>Sylla</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named him the Great: And for the Weſt, he conquered <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rennius Perpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> and <hi>Serto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> in <hi>Spaine.</hi>
               </note> Eaſt and Weſt by Tryumphs. Nor indeed did he more civilly and humanely, then our parent by his authority, counſell and truſt, open the wayes, cleare the ports, reſtore the traveller to the high way, the Sea to the ſhore, and ſhore unto the Sea, ſo intermingling nations by commerce, as what ſprung any where, ſeemed to ſpring every where. Do we not evidently ſee that without injury to any, every yeare plentifully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes to our uſes; becauſe we rob not our freinds, as if they were the enemy, of their greene and periſhing harveſt, they bring to our granaries what their ſoile beares, what their ſtarre ripens, what the yeare affords; nor preſſed with new taxes doe they faile in their old tribute. The publique Treaſury buyes what it ſeemes to buy, from hence plenty, from hence proviſions of corne, the buyer and ſeller agreeing upon a price, from hence ſatiety here, famine no where. <hi>Aegypt</hi> ſo gloried in cheriſhing and multiplying ſeed, as if it were not at all indebted to the rayne or heaven, being alwaies watered with her owne<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nilus</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver that waters <hi>Aegypt</hi> like a garden, and is worſhipped as a God by the <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians.</hi>
               </note> river nor fatned with any other kind of water, but what was powred forth by the earth it ſelfe, yet was it cloathed with ſo much corne that it might (and as it were eternally) vie harveſts with the fruitfulleſt ſoyles of the whole world. This very Countrey with unexpected drought withered even to barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, becauſe dull <hi>Nilus</hi> roſe ſlowly and languiſhingly from his channel, he himſelfe being then to bee compared with other mighty rivers, ſo that a great part of the land accuſtomed to lie coole and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verflowed, was parched into deepe ſands. In vaine then <hi>Aegypt</hi> wiſhed for floods, &amp; lifted up their eyes to heaven, when the author of their fecunditie, <hi>Nilus,</hi> being leſſened and contracted, had brought their plenty into as narrow a compaſſe, as his owne aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance. Nor did that vaſt overflowing river ſo much as keepe within his conſtantly uſurped bounds, but from his levell and detaining bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſtole away like a fugitive with a ſoft and gentle ebbe, not moiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſo much ground as would maintaine the ſcorched land. The people therefore being defrauded of their inundation, that is, of their
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:158486:19"/>
fertility, ſo implored <hi>Caeſars</hi> helpe, and invocated him, as they uſe to doe their river, nor were they longer oppreſſed with their misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, then till ſuch time as they could ſignifie them. So ſwift, <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> is your power, and your goodneſſe upon all occaſions ſo intent and ready, that if your times have any ſadder accident, for the reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very and cure, it is enough to let you know it. Truely to all nations I wiſh plenteous yeares, and gratefull earth, yet I muſt beleeve, that fortune by putting <hi>Aegypt</hi> into this condition, did it only that ſhe might ſee a proofe of your power and vigilance: For though you deſerve to be fortunate every where, yet is't not manifeſt, that each ſadder chance doth but offer new matter and field-roome to your virtues? ſince proſperity declares man happy, adverſity great. It was (time out of minde) a generally received opinion, that <hi>Rome</hi> without the wealth of <hi>Aegypt</hi> could not eate and ſubſiſt, which made that windy and inſolent nation boaſt, that yet they fed the conquerors of the World, and that in their hands lay our abundance, or our want. We have poured back upon <hi>Nile</hi> its own proviſions, it hath received the corne it ſent, and exported the harveſts it brought in. Let <hi>Aegypt</hi> therefore learne and experimentally believe that ſhe affords us not <hi>ſuſtenance,</hi> but <hi>tribute,</hi> and know that ſhe is to the people of <hi>Rome</hi> not <hi>neceſſary,</hi> yet a <hi>ſervant.</hi> Hereafter let <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> if he pleaſe love his channell and keepe within his banks, 'tis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to <hi>Rome,</hi> ſcarce to <hi>Aegypt;</hi> only that from thence their ſhips will lanch out empty and unladed, as if they were returning, and goe from hence with their full fraight and burden, as they uſe to come. And the Sea having changed the copy of both our wiſhes, they may now pray for ſpeedy windes and a ſhort voyage <hi>hence. Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> it had been a miracle ſhould not the ſloath of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenneſſe of <hi>Nile</hi> have had their influence upon the proviſions of this City, which by your helpe and your care, hath abounded in that meaſure, as proved at once, <hi>we</hi> could want <hi>Aegypt, Aegypt</hi> could not want <hi>us.</hi> There had beene an end of that moſt fruitfull nation, if it had beene unconquered; they were aſhamed of their unaccuſtomed dearth, nor leſſe aſhamed of hunger that tormented them, when you together ſtopped both their neceſſity and bluſhes. Their husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that ſaw the barnes full of corne without their inning, won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred from what ground that harveſt came, and in what part of <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> there was another <hi>Nile.</hi> Thus your bounty tooke away the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity of their ſoyle, and <hi>Nile</hi> that formerly was ſerviceable to <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> never flowed higher to our glory. How happy it is now for all
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:158486:19"/>
Provinces, that they are come into our ſubjection and allegiance, ſince the world hath got a Prince, that now hither, now thither (as time and neceſſity requires) can paſſe and returne plenty! that could feede and maintaine a nation ſevered from us by the Ocean, as if it had beene part of the people of <hi>Rome.</hi> And while heaven is never ſo benigne, to cheriſh and make fruitfull in one yeare all ſoyles, but if not barrenneſſe it ſelfe, at leaſt the evill of barrenneſſe aflicts them, he importeth, if not plenty it ſelfe, at leaſt the good of plenty; hee with eternall intercourſe ties the Eaſt unto the Weſt, that what growes any where, and is elſewhere deſired, all nations together may enjoy, learning thereby, how much one Maſter is to be prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before diſcordant liberty. For whereas in Countries where the good is ſevered, the evills are their owne, being mixed and aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, particular evills belong to no particular, but all good to all. But whether there be a certaine divinity in their earth, or a Genius in their water, I hope that both their ſoyle and river contented with this bounty of our Prince, will hide our ſeedes in a ſoft boſome, and reſtore them multiplyed; not that we demand intereſt, yet let them thinke themſelves bound to pay it; and let the defrauded expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of one yeare, for all future yeares and ages excuſe it ſelfe, ſo much the more becauſe we exact it not. The neceſſity of your ſubjects and allies being provided for, you make us ſpectators of no weake, no idle<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Trajan</hi> ſet forth ſhowes that continued 123 dayes, wherein ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times were ſlain 1000 beaſtes wilde &amp; tame, ſometimes ten thouſand; like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Gladiators fought together <hi>Dion.</hi>
               </note> Shew, that may effeminate mens mindes; but ſuch as may beget a love of handſome wounds, and a contempt of death, when they behold a deſire of prayſe and ambition of victory, even in the bodies of ſlaves and men condemned to die. In ſetting forth this Show, how great your bounty, and your juſtice, eyther untouched, or above the power of paſſion! We obtayned what we asked, nay that was offered us we asked not, and he himſelfe was earneſt with us to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre our deſires, but ſo likewiſe we had many ſudden and unexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted ſights. Then how free was the beholders liking! how ſecure their favor! no impiety, as formerly objected unto any that he hated a ſword-player, no ſpectator made a<note n="c" place="margin">Made a Beſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arius, ſo they called them that fought with wilde beaſts; or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to be a Gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator, as <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus,</hi> whom they ſay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was very handſome, <hi>C. Caligula</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to bee taken from the ſword-play which hee ſate beholding, and compelled him 'th liſts, firſt to fight with a <hi>Thracian,</hi> then with one ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at all pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and <hi>Procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered both, <hi>Domitian</hi> made him be ſtript, bound, put into rags, ſhewed to the Ladies and then executed.</note> ſpectacle, payed for his miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable pleaſure, dragged by the hooke unto the fier.<note n="d" place="margin">Domitian.</note> Hee was a mad man and ignorant of true honour that gathered up high treaſon from the ſand within the liſts, interpreting that his Deity was deſpiſed and contemned, unleſſe we adored his gladiators, and that malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants in them blaſphemed his power and divinity; accounting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the ſame with the Gods, and his gladiators the ſame with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. But you, <hi>Caeſar,</hi> how faire a ſhew have you made us in ſtead of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:158486:20"/>
that execrable one? We ſee judgement paſſed upon informers, ſuch as upon out-lawes, ſuch as upon theeves. They lately were ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, not in<note n="e" place="margin">As in <hi>Juv. Sat.</hi> 4. For ſuch a Turbut who durſt ſell or buy, So many Inquiſitors and Informers nigh. Theſe Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weeds ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red on the ſhore.</note> unfrequented places, but in the<note n="f" place="margin">The Temple of <hi>Saturne,</hi> thought the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt place for the publique Treaſury, ſayes <hi>Alex. Neop.</hi> becauſe <hi>Saturn</hi> firſt invented brazen money, but with relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity of the Golden Age when <hi>Saturne</hi> reigned<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſayth <hi>Plutarch.</hi>
               </note> Temple and the Courts of juſtice, then no Teſtament would ſtand good, no condition be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, neither the childleſſe nor the parent. The avarice of Princes added to this evill, you tooke notice of it, and as before to the <hi>Feilds,</hi> ſo you now reſtored peace to the<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> Forum Romanum <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the Temple of</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne <hi>with the</hi> Comitium <hi>or</hi> Juſtice-hall, <hi>the</hi> Roſtra <hi>or</hi> pulpits for Oration, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Forum;</hi> you cut off this civill gangrene, and by provident ſeverity tooke order that the Citie <hi>eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed</hi> by law, ſhould not by Law be <hi>ruin'd.</hi> Notwithſtanding ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that aſwell your fortune as your bounty hath beſtowed, and ſtill beſtowes upon us, now mighty bodies of men with equall ſpirits, now the hugeneſſe of wilde beaſts, now their tameneſſe never known before, now thoſe<note n="h" place="margin">Hoorded by <hi>Domitian,</hi> beſtowed on the publique and upon the Gods, by <hi>Trajan. Martial. l.</hi> 12. What in th' <hi>Atcadian</hi> Palace ſhin'd, is to our eyes and Gods aſſign'd. And now with <hi>Jove</hi> we all are bleſt, But late, alas when 'tis confeſt, Into our cheekes 'twill bluſhes call. We with poore <hi>Jove</hi> were beggers all.</note> hidden and ſecret treaſures, firſt under you made publique, yet nothing is more pleaſing to us, nothing more worthy of the age, then what is added to theſe ſhews, the ſight of Informers dragged through the ſtreets with ſupine faces, and necks wryed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, we ſaw and joyed, when (as Sacrifices to expiate the ſolitude they had cauſed) they were drawne along with ſlowe and grieuous tortures: They were crowded aboard ſhips, preſſed upon the ſuddain and delivered over to the Tempeſts, that ſhould ſend them away and toſſe them from the continent, waſted and made deſolate by their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations; and if the ſtormes and billowes ſhould reſerve any for the rocks, he ſhould inhabit the naked ſtones, and the inhoſpitable ſhore, and live hardly and painfully, tormented with the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his being put out of the common protection of mankinde. A memorable ſight, the Informers fleete, expoſed to all windes, conſtreined to ſpread their ſayles to embrace Tempeſts, and to goe along with the angry waves till they daſhed them on a Rock. Oh twas a gallant proſpect, from the Port, to ſee that navy ſcattered, and in the very Sea thanking the Prince, that preſerving his clemencie, had commended the revenge of the earth &amp; men unto the ſea-gods. How much diverſitie of times could doe, is now eſpecially known, when to the ſame<note n="i" place="margin">In the Iſlands of the <hi>Cyclades,</hi> to which the Roman Emperors baniſhed many noble perſons, <hi>Juv. Sat.</hi> 13. Or to the <hi>Aegaean</hi> rocks that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine great exiles.</note> Rocks where formerly every innocent perſon, now only the guilty are confined, and all thoſe deſert Iſlands which late were filled with Senators are now planted with Informers,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:158486:20"/>
which you have not only taken away for the preſent, but ſuppreſſed for ever, making them lyable to a thouſand penalties. Doe any goe about to cheate others of their money? they muſt loſe their owne. would they out us from our houſes? they muſt from theirs be outed. Nor (as formerly) doe they hold forth that bloodleſſe and brazen forehead to bee marked with a cold<note n="k" place="margin">Pointing to the act of <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitian,</hi> who grievouſly pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhed the Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers of the Chequer, but incouraged the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> iron, laughing, and never hurt when they are ſtigmatized; but they ſee dammages paid anſwereable to the gayn that was expected, ſo, as they cannot have greater hopes then terrors, nor bee feared more then they feare. With a noble ſoule did the divine <hi>Titus</hi> looke upon our ſecurity and revenge; and we therefore deified him, but how much more (a long time hence) will you be worthy heaven, that have added ſo many things to thoſe for which we have made him a God? and it was ſo much the harder, becauſe the Emperor<note n="l" place="margin">Who baniſhed Informers from the City. <hi>Dion.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nerva</hi> (moſt worthy to have you for his ſon, you for his ſucceſſor) by making ſo many ſuperſtructures to <hi>Titus</hi> his Edict againſt Informers, ſeem'd to leave nothing for you to doe, who have ſo much enlarged it, as if nothing had been done before. The diſpenſation of each <hi>particular</hi> whereof, how gracious would it have ſhewed you! but you poured them forth all <hi>together,</hi> as the Sun and Day, whoſe light appeares not in <hi>part,</hi> but in <hi>whole,</hi> nor to one or two, but to all the world in common. What a bleſſing is it to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the treaſury ſilent and quiet, and ſuch as it was before there were Informers! Now the God is truely there; now it is a Temple, not the ſpoliarie of the Citizens, and receptacle of cruell and bloody plunder: In the whole orbe of the earth, there is yet one place where under a good Prince the good are too hard for the wicked. Yet ſtill the honour of the Law remaines, nothing is taken off from the publique benefit, nor the penalty remitted to any one, but our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge is added; and herein the change conſiſts, that now, not the Informers, but the Lawes are feared. But peradventure you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine not your Exchequer with the ſame ſeveritie as you doe our Treaſury, yes ſo much the more, as you beleeve you may take a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther liberty in what concernes your ſelfe, than in what concernes the publique. 'Tis ſaid to your<note n="m" place="margin">Actor and Procuratour were Officers of the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer (as this place imports) and the Procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, who was the Advocate, or Judge Fiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and the Actor as I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour's Attour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney generall.</note> Actor and likewiſe to your Procurator, come into the Court, appeare at the Tribunall; for a Tribunall is now ſet up, that vexeth them equall with others, more, if you mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure their torments by the greatneſſe of their qualities. The lot and<note n="n" place="margin">Lots inſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed with names were put into an Urne for the choyce of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrats, in imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof at this day the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians</hi> have balls.</note> urne aſſigne a judge to the Chequer-chamber, 'tis lawfull to reject him, 'tis lawfull to cry I will have none of this, hee is a timerous man, and underſtands not well the goodneſſe of the times; I will
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:158486:21"/>
have none of him, becauſe hee too paſſionately loves <hi>Caeſar; princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pality</hi> and <hi>liberty</hi> uſe the ſame Lawe. And which is your chiefe glory, the Exchequer is often foiled, whoſe cauſe is never <hi>ill</hi> but under a <hi>good</hi> Prince. A mighty merit this, but that farre greater, that you have thoſe Procurators, as commonly your Subjects deſire no other Judges, though it be free for any that diſputes his title, to ſay, I will have another Judge: for you annex no neceſſity to your gifts, as knowing the higheſt grace of Princes favors is, if wee likewiſe may not uſe them. The burdens of government compell decrees of divers Taxes, which as they are a <hi>benefit</hi> to the <hi>generality,</hi> ſo they are an <hi>injury</hi> to <hi>particulars.</hi> Among theſe the<note n="o" place="margin">When <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> had taken an account of the multitude of <hi>Roman</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, finding much money requiſite for the maintenance of all thoſe foote and horſe, he ordained that all inheritances or Legacies left by will to any (ſave to the nee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reſt of blood &amp; to the poore) ſhould pay the twentieth part, as if hee had found this tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute written in <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries. <hi>Dion</hi>
               </note> twentieth part was pitched upon, a tribute only tolerable and eaſie to<note n="p" place="margin">Strangers that had no relation of blood.</note> extraneous heires, but a grievance to domeſtick. Upon them it is therefore<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Auſonius</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions <hi>ſome</hi> of the twentieth part to be retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by <hi>Trajan,</hi> and tells us tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Gratian</hi> remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the <hi>whole.</hi>
               </note> impoſed, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe remitted. For as much as it was manifeſt with how much griefe men would ſuffer (or rather men would not ſuffer) any thing to be pared and ſhaved off from thoſe goods, which by deſcent and ſacred affinitie they had deſerved, and which they never accounted as other mens eſtates, and as fortunes to be hoped for, but as their owne, as things ever poſſeſſed and ſtill to be tranſmitted to the next of blood. This courteſie of the Law was reſerved only for the old denizons of <hi>Rome,</hi> but the new ones, whether they came in by the right of<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>jus Latij,</hi> the <hi>right of Latium</hi> priviledged thoſe [Aliens] that obtained it from taxes, <hi>Paulus</hi> de cenſibus F. l. and likewiſe put them into a capacity of being Magiſtrates.</note> 
               <hi>Latium,</hi> or by the favour of the Prince, unleſſe they had therewith granted to them the right of kindred, the Law looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them as greateſt ſtrangers, where they were moſt neare of kinne. Thus the greateſt right was turned into the greateſt injury, and the City of <hi>Rome</hi> was like to hatred, diſcord and privation of children, ſince by it the neareſt alliances (notwithſtanding their pietie) were diſjoyned; yet ſome were found to beare ſo great affection to our name, that they held the twentith part, &amp; the loſſe of their affinities, fully recompenſed with the title of Citizens of <hi>Rome,</hi> but it ought freelieſt to have been conferr'd upon thoſe, by whom it was ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly valued. It was therefore Decreed by your Father, that what out of the mothers goods came to the children, out of the childrens to the mother (though they had not received the right of<note n="ſ" place="margin">It appeares plainly that the ſtranger, notwithſtanding his Indenization was not freed from <hi>Auguſtus</hi> his Edict for the twentieth part, unleſſe hee had ſued forth the right of kindred, till <hi>Nerva</hi> diſpenſed with it.</note> cognation when they were made Citizens of <hi>Rome</hi>) ſhould not be liable to pay the twentieth part; the ſame immunity he granted to the ſonne in the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:158486:21"/>
goods of his Father (in caſe he were reduced into his fathers<note n="t" place="margin">A ſonne was reduced into his fathers power two waies, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th erif (being freed &amp; eman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipated by his Father) he did returne of his owne accord, or <hi>jure poſtli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minij</hi> if (being taken priſoner by the enemy) he came back to his Country, for that ſet him <hi>inſtatuquo</hi> and his father might be his heyre as before h s emancipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> power) thinking it unhoneſt and inſolent &amp; almoſt impious to put taxes vpon theſe relations, nor that without a kinde of ſacriledg theſe holy tyes could be cut in ſunder by the interpoſition of the twentith part. And that no neceſſary tax ought to be ſo preſſed, as to make Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Children ſtrangers. Thus farr he, perhaps more ſparingly then became the beſt Prince, but not more ſparingly then became the beſt Father, that being to adopt the Beſt, in this likewiſe as a moſt indulgent parent, was content to beginne, or rather but to ſhew the way, reſervinge for his ſonne a large and almoſt untouched mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of well-doing. Immediately therefore to his bounty your libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality added, that as the ſonne in the fathers, ſo the father ſhould be priviledged in the ſonnes inheritance, nor in the ſame mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ent that he ceaſed to <hi>be</hi> a Father, ſhould he loſe his <hi>having beene</hi> one. You haue done excellently, <hi>Caeſar,</hi> not to ſuffer the fathers teares to be tributa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. The father poſſeſſes his ſonnes goods without diminution, nor hath he a partner in his inheritance, that hath no partner in his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. None calls to account the freſh bleeding and aſtoniſhing loſſe of Children, compelling the Father to ſet forth what the ſonne left. Our Prince's guift appeares greater, when I ſhew this reaſon for his bounty. For it may be accounted ambition, vaine glory and profuſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and any thing rather then liberality, that is not conſonant to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. It was worthy therefore your compaſſion, <hi>Caeſar,</hi> to leſſen the affliction of parents now growne childleſſe, nor to ſuffer any that hath loſt his ſonne to be ſtricken with another greife; becauſe t'is mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery enough, for a father to be ſole heyre to his ſonne; what if he haue a Coheyre not of his ſonnes naming? Beſides, when divine <hi>Nerva</hi> had decreed, that for their fathers eſtates the children ſhould be free from payment of the twentith part, it was congruous and fit, that the ſame freedome ſhould be granted to parents in their ſonnes eſtates: for why ſhould children receive more honour, then Progenitours? and why ſhould not the ſame equity aſcend? You, <hi>Caeſar,</hi> haue taken away that exception, in caſe the ſonne be in his fathers power, having an eye (as I conceive) to the force and law of nature that ordereth children to be for ever in the power of parents, nor giveth, among men, as among beaſts, the power and command to the ſtronger. Neither was our Prince content to priviledge the firſt degree of blood from the twentith part, he likewiſe exempts the ſecond; with a proviſo that the brother in his ſiſters goods, and the ſiſter in her brothers, that the vncle and aunt in their nephewes
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:158486:22"/>
and neices eſtates, and contrarily, ſhould remaine untaxable. And to thoſe that by the Right of <hi>Latium</hi> were free of Rome, he graunted the ſame privilege, and rejoyned the rights of kindreds according to the courſe of nature. For which favours former Princes put par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons to petition, not ſo much with intention to grant, as to deny them. Whence we may underſtand, how great an act of bounty, and nobleneſſe it was, to collect and bind vp our ſcattered and (as I may call them) dilacerated familyes; to regraft, and bid them, as it were to ſpring a freſh; freely to offer, what had beene denyed, and give to all <hi>at once,</hi> what often <hi>ſeverally</hi> they could not obteyn. Laſtly to barre himſelfe of ſo many occaſions of doing fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and ſuch a copious ſubject for obligation to the thankfull, and imputation to the ingratefull: I conceive he thought it unfitting for men to aſke, what the Gods had given. You are ſiſters and brothers, grandfathers and grandchildren, why ſhould you, [becauſe you are ſo] be impoveriſhed with a tax? your relations are your privileges. The Emperour according to the reſt of his princely moderation, thinks it a matter of no leſſe envy, to grant vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> petition your own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritances to you, then to take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from you. With alacrity therefore ſtand for honour, ſue for office, let this blocke of <hi>lopt-off</hi> kindred ly in no mans way, all ſhall enjoy the ſame proximity of blood they did before, but in a better manner. The remoteſt degree of late-ceaſing affinity, ſhall not be compelled to pay in the leaſt quantity of the twentith part. For our common<note n="v" place="margin">Trajan, the father of his Country.</note> parent hath ſet downe a ſumme that is able to beare a tax. The twentith part ſhall not lye heavie upon a ſmall and weake eſtate, nay if the gratefull heyre ſo pleaſe, he may reſerve it all for the ſepulchre, all for the funeralls; no aſſiſtant, no ſuperintendent to overſee him. For whatſoever conſideration his legacy was left him, he may ſecurely injoy and quietly<note n="*" place="margin">For that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, to beſtow it upon the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralls of the bequeather.</note> poſſeſſe the mony. The law of the twentith part is now ſo penned, that there is no coming within compaſſe of it but by a great eſtate; injuſtice is turned into joy, and an injury into a longing, the heyre wiſhes the honour of paying the twentith part. It is likewiſe enacted by the ſame Edict that they who owe and have not payed the twentith part, ſhould not bring it in. Truly the time paſt the Gods them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves cannot help, yet you have helped it, and provided that <hi>now</hi> they ſhould ceaſe to owe, what they ſhould not owe <hi>hereafter.</hi> You have done that puts us into ſuch a Condition, as if we never had ſuffered under evill Princes, and how willingly (if it were poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) would the ſame goodneſſe of your nature, to ſo many ruined
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:158486:22"/>
and murthered men reſtore their blood and fortunes. You have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid the exaction of what begunne not to be due in your owne reigne. Another to ſhew his fury againſt the contumacious would have pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed ſlowneſſe of payment with a double, nay, a quadruple fine. You eſteeme it equall injuſtice, either to exact what is unjuſt, or to decree it. You take upon you <hi>(Caeſar)</hi> the <hi>Conſul's</hi> care and ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude; for when I conſider, that you alone have remitted our aſſeiſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, given the donative, offered the Congiary, baniſhed Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, mitigated our taxes, methinks I ſhould put the queſtion to you, have you ſufficiently caſt up the revenues of the Empire? or is there ſuch vertue in the frugality of a Prince, as that alone can be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for ſo much expenſe, ſo much munificence? for what can be the reaſon, why other Princes when they catched at all we had, and having caught, retained it as if they had got nothing, wanted all things; you, when you beſtow ſo much, and take away nothing, yet have all things in aboundance? Princes yet never wanted thoſe, that with ſowre lookes, and ſupercilious gravitie, were peremptory for the profits of the Exchequer; Even Princes themſelves of their owne inclinations were ſufficiently Coveteous &amp; rapacious, &amp; need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no inſtructours; Yet ſtill they learned many things of us againſt our ſelves. But your eares, as they are obſtructed to all inſinuations, ſo cheifly avaritious flattery can have no acceſſe. Therefore Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers are ſilent and quiet, and after, there is none to be perſwaded, there is none that offers to perſwade. Thus are we infinitely obliged to you, both for your goodneſſe and our owne. The<note n="x" place="margin">The <hi>Voconian</hi> Law forbad a woman (though an only daughter as <hi>S. Aug.</hi> 3. <hi>de Civ. Det.</hi>) to be heyre to an eſtate; that Iulian Law which he meant (for there were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny) forbad a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery upon paine of death and w s revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by <hi>Domiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> that lived in Inceſt. ſee <hi>Iuv.</hi> Sat. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Voconian</hi> and <hi>Iulian</hi> lawes, did not ſo much inrich the Treaſury and Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, as that one and only crime of high treaſon in the<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Domitian</hi> to inrich his cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers found ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny (upon ſtrange Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachments) guilty of high treaſon, ſome meerly becauſe th y had gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red exc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſive wealth, which begot diſdaine, made them hold their heads high and be diſobedient to the Lawes, one becauſe in his publike prayers for <hi>Domitian</hi> he did not ſtile him Sonne to <hi>Pallas,</hi> another becauſe he went into an Island as if he had killed his Fathe. <hi>Philoſtratus</hi> l. 7.</note> innocent. The fright whereof you have abſolutely taken away, not being jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of your greatneſſe, which none hath wanted more, then they that made majeſty a terrour. Fidelity is returned to freinds, piety to children, duty to ſervants; they feare and obey, and once againe have maſters, for now not our ſervants but we our ſelves are the Princes friends. Nor doth the Father of his Country more indeare himſelfe to, and put more confidence in others ſlaves, then his owne ſubjects. You have freed us all from our domeſtick accuſers, and giving the word (as I may ſay) of publike ſafety, you have put an end unto this<note n="z" place="margin">He compares the private bandying of ſervants informing againſt their maſters to the publike warre of ſlaves againſt <hi>Rome,</hi> begunne in <hi>Sicily</hi> by <hi>Ennus</hi> the <hi>Syrian,</hi>
               </note> ſerville warr: whereby you have not more obliged the maſters,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:158486:23"/>
then the ſervants; for you have made thoſe ſecure, theſe honeſt. Will you not be yet commended? well, put the caſe theſe were not commendable, ſure they are pleaſing, to them who remember a<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Domitian</hi> who incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ſervants to ſweare againſt their Lords and then (the juſt remarkable reward of Traytours) from thoſe hands that ſhould pay them for their ſervice, they (like <hi>Tarpeia</hi>) received their fatall blow.</note> Prince that incouraged ſervants to ſwear away their maſters lifes, and pointed them out the crime whereof they ſhould informe, that he might puniſh it; a great, inevitable, and ſtill experienced Evill, as oft as any had ſervants like the Prince. 'Tis to be placed in the ſame ranke rhat our laſt Wills and Teſtaments are now<note n="b" place="margin">Which had beene invaded by former Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours; <hi>Tibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> broke the heart of the rich Augur <hi>Lentulus,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he durſt not leave his eſtate to any but the Emp. The <hi>Primipila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rij</hi> or chiefe Centurions that dyed in the reigne of <hi>Tiberius</hi> and made not him heyre <hi>Caius</hi> called ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and <hi>Nero</hi> ordained that the Teſtaments of the ungratefull ſhould be confiſcated.</note> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, nor do you carry away all, becauſe you were once nominated an heyre. You are intituled to no falſe, no unjuſt Will; no ones an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, no ones impiety, no ones fury flies to you for refuge, nor are you named becauſe another hath offended, but becauſe you have merited. Your friends put you in, ſtrangers leave you out, no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt your being a private perſon and a Prince, but that now you are beloved of many more, becauſe you love many more. This courſe, <hi>Caeſar,</hi> you hold, and experience ſhewes, whether it be not more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall to a Prince, not only in prayſe but profit, that to make him their heyre men ſhould be rather deſirous, then compelled. Many donations in this kinde your<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nerva,</hi> who reſtored the rapines of <hi>Domitian,</hi> was bount full to the poore even out of his owne Eſtate, and ſo free to his freinds that <hi>Philoſtratus</hi> ſayes when <hi>Atticus</hi> (father to <hi>Herod</hi> the Rhetoritian) writt to <hi>Nerva</hi> that he had digged vp a great Treaſure and deſired to know how he pleaſed it ſhould be diſpoſed of, he writt back <hi>Vse it. Atticus</hi> anſwered his letter, that 'twas too great for a private condition, <hi>Nerva</hi> replyed, <hi>then abuſe it.</hi>
               </note> Father and you have granted: dyed he out of favour? yet dying ſo he leaves them that injoy his eſtate and you have nothing out of it, but glory. For a gratefull debter makes bountie ſweeter, an ingratefull, more conſpicuous. But who, untill your time, preferred this prayſe before that profit? What Prince but thought ſo much of our patrimony his owne, as had been gotten under him? as our Tyrants, ſo likewiſe our Princes boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes were they not like hookes bayted with food, like nets cover'd over with prey, till being ſwallowed &amp; laden with private mens for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, they drew backe with the whatſoever touched them. How be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall it is to come to proſperity through adverſity! You have lived with us, beene in danger with us, &amp; in feare, (which was the life of the innocent.) You know, &amp; have experience, how much Princes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt evill me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, though they themſelves do make them ſuch. You reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber your old wiſhes with us, &amp; your old greivances, for in the boſome
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:158486:23"/>
of a Prince you beare the judgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of a private man. Nay you are better then you wiſhed another Prince ſhould be. You have ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed us, that whereas before our higheſt ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was a Prince better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the worſt, now none will content us but the beſt. No man therefore is ſo ignorant of you, or of himſelfe, as to deſire that place after you. It is eaſier for one to be your ſucceſſour, then to<note place="margin">This was no propheſy of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian,</hi> for he wiſhed it, and by the favour of <hi>Plotina,</hi> wife to <hi>Trajan, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian</hi> ſucceeded him in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire.</note> 
               <hi>wiſh</hi> it; for who willingly would undergoe your weight of care? who will not feare to be compared to you? even you your ſelfe found how bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenſome it is to ſucceed a good Prince, and therefore would have beene excuſed from your adoption. Is it an ordinary Patterne eaſy to be matcht, that no man redeemes his <hi>ſafety</hi> with <hi>turpitude?</hi> all are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured both of life, and the dignity of life. Nor is he now conſiderate and wiſe, that obſcures himſelfe and lives in darkeneſſe, for virtue hath the ſame encouragements under our <hi>Prince,</hi> which it had in our <hi>liberty;</hi> nor is well doing onely rewarded by the Conſcience, but far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther recompenced. You love the conſtancy of your Subjects; and their lively and erected ſpirits you doe not (like others) deject and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, but cheriſh and raiſe. Honeſty preferres men that thinke it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough and more, if it hurt them not. To theſe you offer Honours, Preiſthoods, Provinces; theſe flouriſh by your freindſhip, by your eſteeme and Judgement. They are quickened by the price that is ſet upon Integrity and induſtry. The like and the unlike are attracted, for it is the reward of good and evill that makes men good or bad. There are naturally few by whom foule or faire ends are not propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or avoided, as they make for or againſt their benefit. The reſt, when they ſee the wages of labour paid to ſloth, of vigilance to drowſineſſe, of frugality to luxury, they aime at the ſame rewards by the ſame<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tacitus. l.</hi> 16. ſaith that <hi>C. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronius</hi> ſpent the day in ſleep, the night in waiting and wanton offices, and as induſtry raiſed others, ſo ſloath ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced him, who applying himſelfe to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or the imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of vices, got to be one of that ſmall Jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto that were in <hi>Nero</hi>'s fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour.</note> arts, wherewith they perceive others have attained them; ſuch as thoſe are ſuch theſe deſire to appeare, &amp; what they would on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeeme, they doe really become. And our former Princes, (your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther excepted) and one or<note n="f" place="margin">He meanes <hi>Auguſtus</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> whowere good, but <hi>Dion</hi> ſayes, the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes would ſcarce have thought them ſo, if <hi>Auguſtus</hi> had died ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, or <hi>Titus</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved longer. For the troubleſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e beginning of his Reigne made <hi>Auguſtus</hi> more cruell, who when things were ſetled proved gracious and noble; But <hi>Titus,</hi> at firſt ſtiled the delight of mankind, afterward did ſome barbarous acts; as when he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Aulus Caecinna</hi> (whom he invited to ſupper) to be murthered in his Dining roome.</note> two (I feare I have over numbred them) rather delighted in the vices, then the virtues of their Subjects. Firſt becauſe every one loves to ſee his owne nature in another, then thoſe whom they found more patient of bondage, thoſe whom it would not have become to be any thing but<note n="g" place="margin">Such was the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> ſlave <hi>Criſpinus,</hi> onely beloved by <hi>Domitian</hi> for the ſympathy of his vices, you have his graphike Character. <hi>Juv. Sat.</hi> 4.</note> ſervants, in their boſomes they heaped all their bounties; but the good, that in a long vacation of em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:158486:24"/>
were hidden, and, as it were, buried, them they never brought forth to the light and day, unleſſe by informations, and with danger. You chooſe your freinds out of the beſt, and truly it is juſt they ſhould be moſt in favour with a good Prince, that were moſt frowned upon by a bad. You know that as tyranny and Soveraignty are of different natures, ſo none love a <hi>Prince</hi> better, then they that moſt diſaffect a <hi>Tyrant.</hi> Theſe therefore you advance, and give us proofe and example, what courſe of life, what kinde of men you are beſt pleaſed withall. Therefore you have not as yet accepted of the Cenſourſhip or Superintendency of manners, becauſe you like better to worke upon our diſpoſitions by <hi>benefits,</hi> then by <hi>remedies;</hi> beſides I know not if a Prince contribute more to manners, that ſuffers men to be good, or that<note n="h" place="margin">This touches the perpetuall Cenſourſhips of <hi>Domitian,</hi> who being him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe moſt viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous compelled others to doe well; thus as Cenſour he put <hi>Caecilius Rufi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nus</hi> from his place in Senate, becauſe he uſed to dance; and though <hi>Claudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Pacatus</hi> was <hi>de facto,</hi> a Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turion, yet proofe being brought that he was <hi>de jure</hi> a Slave, <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> by his Cenſour's po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer reſtored him to his Lord <hi>Dion.</hi>
               </note> compells them. We are all flexible and ductile where the Prince drawes us, and follow him where he leades, for we are ambitious to be indeared to, and approved of him, which thoſe that are not like him have hoped for in vaine; and by continua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of obſequiouſneſſe we are come to that paſſe, that almoſt all live according to the precedent of one mans manners. Beſides we are not ſo ill natured, that we which can be imitatours of a bad Prince, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not imitate a good. Doe you, <hi>Caeſar,</hi> but goe forwards, and your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes and actions ſhall have the force and effect of a <hi>Cenſourſhip.</hi> For the life of a Prince is a Cenſourſhip, and that perpetuall, by that we are directed, upon that our eyes are fixed, nor have we ſo much need of <hi>precept,</hi> as <hi>example:</hi> becauſe feare is an unfaithfull guide to virtue; men are better inſtructed by examples, which primarily have in them this good, that they ſhew what is <hi>commanded</hi> may be <hi>done.</hi> And what terrour could effect that, which reſpect to you hath brought about? ſome one got the people to ſuffer the ſpectacle of<note n="i" place="margin">The <hi>Panto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mimes</hi> were ſuch as our fooles in plaies, or the Italian Pantalounes, Imitatours of all garbes, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures and tones how wanton ſoever.</note> 
               <hi>Pantomimes</hi> to be taken away, but yet he got it not as he deſired; you <hi>entreated</hi> what another <hi>inforced,</hi> and that became a <hi>favour</hi> which had beene <hi>neceſſity.</hi> Nor were you leſſe unanimouſly petitioned to take them away, then your Father was to reſtore them. And both your acts were well, for they ought to be reſtored that were taken away by an evill Prince, and when they were reſtored, to be taken away againe. For in what ill men doe well, this courſe is to be held, that it may appeare the <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> is diſpleaſing, not the <hi>action.</hi> The ſame people therefore that were ſometimes ſpectatours and applauders of a mimicke <hi>Caeſar,</hi> now diſlike the <hi>Pantomimes,</hi> and condemne effeminate arts and ſtudies misbecoming the Times. From which premiſſes we may conclude the diſcipline of Princes takes with the very vulgar,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:158486:24"/>
ſince if he alone doe a ſevere act, they all will doe the like. Increaſe this glory, <hi>Caeſar,</hi> wonne by your gravity. And what formerly was called compulſion and <hi>command,</hi> ſhall be now ſtiled <hi>manners.</hi> Their owne vices are corrected by them that ought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be corrected, and thoſe very men are the <hi>reformers</hi> that ſhould have beene <hi>reformed.</hi> None therefore complaynes of your ſeverity, yet all have freedome to complayne. But notwithſtanding that men do not leſſe complayne of any Prince, then of him that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes them greateſt freedome: yet [ſo farre we are from cauſe of complaint, that] there is nothing in your times that cauſeth not a generall rejoycing. The good are advanced, the evill (which is the calmeſt condition of an Empire) neither<note n="k" place="margin">For they know the good <hi>will</hi> not be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers, and they themſelve <hi>dare</hi> not.</note> feare, nor are feared. You cure our errours, but wee our ſelves beſeech you; thoſe whom you make good, you do it with this honour to your ſelfe, that it appeareth you have not compelled them. What the life? what the manners of our youth? how prince-like do you forme them? what honour do you to<note n="l" place="margin">Such as <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny's</hi> tutor <hi>Quintilian,</hi> who publikely taught Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rike in <hi>Trajan's</hi> reign.</note> Rhetoricke Maſters, what advancement do you give<note n="m" place="margin">As that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Philoſopher <hi>Plutarch</hi> Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jans Tutor.</note> Philoſophyers! inſomuch as under you our ſtudyes have found<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Domitian</hi> condemning <hi>Ruſticus Aruli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> meerely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was a philoſopher &amp; writt the life of <hi>Thraſeas, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rennius Senecio</hi> for writing the life of <hi>Helvidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Priſcus,</hi> and <hi>Pompuſian</hi> for hanging up a Mappe of the world in his chamber, and reading the Kings ſpeeches in <hi>Livy,</hi> and other learned Profeſſours he baniſhed from Rome. <hi>Dion.</hi>
               </note> life, ſpirit, and their <hi>native Country,</hi> which the barbarity of former Ages puniſhed with <hi>exile;</hi> when the Prince, conſcious of a world of his owne vices, baniſhed vice-perſecuting arts, not ſo much for hate, as feare; but you have thoſe very arts in your<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iuv.</hi> 7. Sat. <hi>Caeſar</hi> is both our ſtudyes cauſe and end, For he alone is the ſad Muſes freind.</note> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces, in your eye, and in your eare. For you <hi>do</hi> whatſoever they <hi>enjoyne,</hi> and<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iuvenal</hi> Sat. Youth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſtudy, <hi>Caeſar's</hi> bounty ſpurrs you on, That ſeekes but matter it may worke upon.</note> love them as much as you are approved of by them. Doth not every profeſſor in humanity admiring all things in you, eſpecially extoll your facility in giving of acceſſe? With a great ſoule your father over the Palace gates ſet up the title of publike buildings, but vainly, unleſſe he had adopted one that might live as in publike. How well do your manners ſuite with that inſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, although indeed it lookes as if no other had ingraven the title. For what Court of Iuſtice, what temple is ſo open? not the Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll, the very place of your adoption is more publike, more every bodyes, no bolts, no degrees of contumely, and having paſſed a thouſand dores, yet to meet with an affront and be lockt out. A great ſtilneſſe is before and behind you, but the greateſt is about your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and every where ſuch ſilence ſuch Civility, that the Princes Court may be a patterne of modeſty and tranquillity to narrow Lares,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:158486:25"/>
and private dwellings. But you your ſelfe how you receive us all, how you ſtay among us! ſo that in ſo many cares of government you ſpend a great part of the day as if you had no buſineſſe. we therefore come not running to Court, as formerly,<note n="q" place="margin">See the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natours, when <hi>Domitian</hi> ſent for them to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe him how the great Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>but ſhould be dreſſed. <hi>Iuv.</hi> Sat. 4. For which in ſuch haſt and aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, For them our migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Generall had ſent &amp;c.</note> aſtoniſhed; nor as if we ſhould looſe our head if we mended not our paces; but ſecure and cheerefull, at our owne convenient leaſure; and when the Prince vouſchafes his preſence, many times there is ſomething as more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that detayneth us at home. Yet to you we are alwaies to be excuſed, never to be accuſed. for you know it is every ones joy to ſee you, to attend you frequently, and therefore you doe us this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the freer and the longer. Nor doth<note n="r" place="margin">Retirement, as when <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius</hi> With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew with the Asſtrologers to <hi>Caprae. Iuv.</hi> Sat. 10. where he ſitts, Thron'd on a rocke with his <hi>Chaldaean</hi> Wits.</note> retirement and<note n="ſ" place="margin">Solitude ſuch as this of <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitians</hi> which he proceedes to deſcribe.</note> ſolitude follow your admiſſions; we make you tarry for us, and ſtay with you; as if the Court were a houſe common to us all, which lately that moſt cruell monſter had fortified with multiplicity of terrour, when lurking as it were in a kind of denne, now he licked up his kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens blood, now ſallied forth to worry and devour the nobleſt Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans. Horrour and threatning waited at his gates, and the ſame fear ſeized the admitted, and thoſe that were<note n="t" place="margin">Which were the nobleſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, this <hi>Iuv.</hi> obſerves Sat. 4. The preſence hinges nimbly turne about. The Fiſh goes in, the Senate waite w thout.</note> kept out. Then he himſelfe was terrible to meete or to behold, pride in his forehead, fury in his eyes, a feminine paleneſſe in his body, impudence in his face floating vpon much<note n="v" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tacitus</hi> l. XII. notes this Colour in <hi>Domitian,</hi> and ſayes; by thoſe that knew him not, his fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent bluſhes were taken for modeſty.</note> ſanguine colour, none durſt make approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, none durſt ſpeake to him, ſtill keeping himſelfe retired and in the darke, never coming abroad out of his ſolitude, unleſſe it were to make a ſolitude. Yet within thoſe walls and works he<note n="*" place="margin">Maintaining in his houſe the Conſpiratours againſt him, to wit, <hi>Stephanus</hi> freed-man to his ſiſter <hi>Domitilla</hi> (whom his tyranny had then made a widow) <hi>Parthenius, Saturius Entellus, Claudius Cornicularius,</hi> and <hi>Maximus Parthenus,</hi> his domeſtikes.</note> har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour'd plots and ſtratagems againſt his owne life, and incloſed the revenger of his miſchiefes, God. His puniſhment broke through the guards, through the narrow and obſtructed paſſages as eaſie as if the doores had beene opened, and they invited over the threſholds, then he had no<note n="x" place="margin">His ſtile of <hi>Dominus &amp; Deus noſter</hi> could not then protect him; Pliny might very well have added, twas that Lord and God whoſe titles he uſurped that deſtroyed him by the hands of thoſe wicked Inſtruments.</note> Divinitie, no inacceſſible and bloody withdrawing roomes where he retired for fear, and pride, and hatred of mankind. How much ſafer, how much ſecurer now is the ſame houſe, ſince it came to be defended not with ſolitude and trenches, nor the guards of cruelty, but of love. Do we not therefore learne this by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:158486:25"/>
that the ſureſt guard is the Princ'es innocence. This is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expugnable fort, this is the impregnable bulwarke, not to need a bulwark. In vaine he incompaſſeth himſelfe with terrour that is not incompaſſed with love; for by armes, armes are provoked. But do you only ſpend the ſerious part of the day in our eies and aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyes? In your recreations is there not preſent the ſame frequency, the ſame ſociety? do you not alwayes eat in publike? is not your table common? is there not a mutuall pleaſure when you feaſt us? do you not invite and anſwer our diſcourſe? your very meale time when your temperance contracts it for your ſelfe, doth not your humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie lengthen it out for us? for you do not fill your ſelfe alone at<note n="y" place="margin">For the ninth houre (being our three in the afternoone) was the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes meale ime.</note> noone day, and then ſtand over as ſuperviſour and Cenſurer of your gueſts, nor being<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Suetonius T.</hi> ſayes. <hi>Domiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> uſed ſo to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe at dinner <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat he durſt venture upon nothing at ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per unleſſe it were an apple or ſome little running colla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> full and flatuous your ſelfe, do you not ſo much bid your friends to your table, as affront them with the meats you ſcorne to touch, nor, hardly diſguiſing that proud hypocriſy of entertainment, do you haſten away againe to clandeſtine gluttony, and ſecret rarityes? We therefore admire not your gold and ſilver plate, nor the exquiſite wit and invention of your diſhes, but the ſincerity and ſweetneſſe of your entertainment; in which is no ſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, all your profeſſions being ſincere and true, and adorned with gravity. For neither the myſteries of forrein<note n="a" place="margin">Such as the Mathematici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans inſtilled in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Tiberius.</hi>
               </note> ſuperſtition, nor obſcene<note n="b" place="margin">Like to that which <hi>Juvenal</hi> excludes from his owne Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 11. per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps thou doeſt expect that I ſhould bring the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Courtezans to dance and ſing. <hi>ex paulo infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius.</hi> The poor houſe is not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with their ioyes. Their obſcene Songs and Caſtinet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta's noiſe.</note> petulancy waites at our Princes table, but a gratious wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, free mirth, and the honour of learning. Thus, your ſleepes are ſparing and ſhort, and your love to us makes you thinke no time more tedious, then that which you ſpend out of our ſight, but we that enjoy what's yours as freely as what we have our ſelves, how abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute is our owne propriety? For you turne not out the old Lords to incloſe every<note n="c" place="margin">Like <hi>Nero,</hi> who deſigned a Fiſh-pond in <hi>Campana</hi> from that Promontory now called <hi>Monte Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeno,</hi> to <hi>Lago di Tripergola,</hi> then <hi>Avernus</hi> or <hi>Pluto</hi>'s Lake, to be covered over head, and galleried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout that ſhould comprehend all the warme water of <hi>Baiae,</hi> and likewiſe began a Lake, like a ſea ſhoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with a City, incloſing groves, vineyards, paſtures, and woods, repleniſhed with all kinds of beaſts, tame and wild. Theſe diſſeiſures kept by <hi>Nero's</hi> ſucceſſours, <hi>Traian</hi> reſtored to the right owners.</note> pond, every lake, nay every forreſt, making your title boundleſſe. Nor doe the flouds, the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, and the ſea, ſerve now for one mans proſpect. Yet what doth <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſee that is not his? and now at laſt the <hi>Empire</hi> of the Prince is greater then his <hi>Patrimony:</hi> For he beſtowes upon his Empire many things that were his Patrimony, which former Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces kept in their poſſeſſions, not that they might injoy them, but leſt another ſhould. Therefore into the manſions and ſeates of Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, their noble Lords returne; nor are the houſes of great perſons
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:158486:26"/>
poſſeſſed by a ſervant, rather <hi>spoiled</hi> then <hi>inhabited,</hi> nor fall they to the ground in ſordid ruines. We may ſee faire houſes, their ſcituati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons bruſhed up, rebeautified, enlarged, and flouriſhing: You merit highly <hi>Caeſar,</hi> not onely of <hi>men,</hi> but even of <hi>houſes,</hi> to arreſt ruine, to expell ſolitude, and vindicate great workes from deſtruction with the ſame gallant ſoule wherewith they firſt were built. Even thoſe mute and ſenſeleſſe creatures ſeeme to have a ſenſe of joy, that they are neate, that they are frequented, that at laſt they belong to a <hi>Lord,</hi> not to a <hi>ſervant.</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Traian.</note> 
               <hi>Caeſar</hi> authorizes a vaſt Inventory of thoſe goods to be expoſed to ſale that were the deteſted avarice of him<note n="e" place="margin">Domit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an.</note> that <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veted</hi> ſo much when he had ſo much <hi>ſuperfluous.</hi> Then it was<note n="f" place="margin">Rich men, as I have former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly noted, being ſentenced one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for being rich and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate.</note> death to have a larger houſe, a fairer Villa. Now the Prince himſelfe ſeekes out, and brings Lords into the ſelfe ſame houſes. Thoſe ſometimes<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>N ro</hi>'s Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens.</note> gardens of a mighty Emperour, that no bodies but <hi>Caeſars</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">He under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands not the very Suburbs of <hi>Rome,</hi> but the Towne of <hi>Alba,</hi> diſtant from the City 140 furlongs, where <hi>Domit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an uſually</hi> kept his Court.</note> ſuburbs, we bargaine for, buy, and people it. So great is the Princes goodneſſe, ſo great the ſecurity of the times, that he thinkes us worthy of impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall poſſeſſions, and we feare not to be thought ſo. Nor doe you one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grant your Subjects leave to purchaſe, but you give &amp; beſtow upon them many handſome and beneficiall things, thoſe very things, I meane, to which you were choſen, to which you were adopted; you transferre what was judiciouſly made over to you, and you beleive nothing to be more your owne, then what you enjoy by the proxy of your freinds. You your ſelfe are as thrifty in <hi>building,</hi> as carefull in <hi>preſerving.</hi> Therefore the City is not with the carriages<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Juv.</hi> paints out theſe carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages exactly, <hi>Sta.</hi> 3. Now meets he car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s where the tall firre-trees quake; Now ſome that pine-trees at the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhake.</p>
                  <p>Suppoſe the ax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el-tree ſhould breake that beares <hi>Liguri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> ſtones, if pour'd about his eares.</p>
                  <p>That mountaine ſhould thy ſhiver'd ſlave intombe. What think'ſt thou of his carcaſſe would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come. Where any limbe lyes who can find the hole? His body ſure would vaniſh l ke h s ſoule.</p>
               </note> of monſtrous ſtones, as formerly, put into an earthquake, our houſes now ſtand ſafe, nor are our temples feaveriſh. It ſeemes you thinke that which you received as ſucceſſour to a moſt frugall Prince, to be enough, and too much for you that you can part with ſome of that he left as neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary. Beſides your Father when he debarred himſelfe of what the fortune of the Empire gave him, did it ſafely becauſe he was<note n="k" place="margin">Yours that would have provided for your father <hi>Nerva,</hi> if he had given away all, as he did a great part of his poſſeſſions.</note> your Father. But how magnificent are you towards the publicke! Here Ports, there Temples, are diſpatched with that ſecret ſpeed, as one would thinke them not <hi>built,</hi> but <hi>repaired</hi> onely: here thoſe vaſt flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the<note n="l" place="margin">In their great Show-place, the <hi>Circus,</hi> the <hi>Romanes</hi> beheld horſe-matches, coach-races, ſword-play, with all kinds of preſentments. It was at firſt flanked with pent-houſes for the Spectatours, then galleried about with 30 diſtinct Fori by <hi>Tarquinius Priſcus,</hi> and now beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified and inlarged with five thouſand benches by <hi>Traian,</hi> with this Inſcription. <hi>vt populo Romano ſufficeret.</hi> Dion.</note> 
               <hi>Circus</hi> that compare in beauty with the temples: It is
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:158486:26"/>
now a <hi>ſhow-place</hi> worthy the Conquerours of the world, it ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſight no leſſe rare then what from thence is ſeene. But to behold the Architecture ſhewes not fairer, then to behold the Princes and peoples benches of the ſelfe ſame modell, ſince there is now in the whole fabricke but one face, all even and equall. Nor is <hi>Caeſars</hi> ſeat more his owne, then the ſpectatours ſeates are theirs. You therefore and your Subjects freely view one another. They have not the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour now to ſee the Princes private box; but to ſee the Prince him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſitting among his people: his people, on whom he hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed the addition of five thouſand benches, for you have here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed their number as you did in the Congiary; and have thus like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe encouraged them to multiply themſelves hereafter, confident of your Magnificence. If one of theſe Princely gifts had been vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed by another, he had long ſince worne a glory on his head circled about with ſun beames, his throne of gold or Ivory had beene ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Gods, and invocation made unto him on higher altars and with greater ſacrifices. You come not into the Temple but to pray, the honours you let your Statues have is to waite without the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to ſtand centrie for the Gods, and to bee preferred before the marble pillars. So the Gods with greateſt reverence are adored by men, ſince you have not aſpired to be a God. Therefore in the porch of <hi>Jupiter</hi> the beſt and greateſt, we ſee one or two of your Statues, and thoſe braſſe, but not long agoe every doore, every ſteppe the whole pavement of the Temple <hi>ſhined,</hi> or rather was <hi>polluted</hi> with gold and ſilver, when the Images of the Gods were grown ſordid by mixing with the ſtatues of an<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Domitian</hi> who (as I have noted) lived in inceſt with his Niece <hi>Julia.</hi>
               </note> inceſtuous Prince. Therefore your brazen ones, and thoſe but few, remaine and ſhall remaine, ſo long as the Temple it ſelfe continues, but their golden ones, and thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable are ruin'd, and dyed Sacrifices to the publique joy. 'Twas gallant ſport to knock the ground and thoſe proud heads together, to pick holes in them with ſwords, to hew them with hatchets, as if at every ſtroake blood and paine had beene to follow. None, at the too late arrivall of his comforts, was ſo modeſt in his joy, but he thought it a kind of revenge to ſee their torne limbes, their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred joynts; Laſtly their cruell and horrid Images caſt into the flame and<note n="n" place="margin">This melting of Statues for uſe, <hi>Juv.</hi> deſcribes <hi>Sat.</hi> 10. Their Chariot-wheeles groane under th'Axes ſtroke, And ev'n their Innocent horſes legs are broke, The fire to crackling flames the bellowes turnes. The head adored by the people burnes; The great <hi>Sejanus</hi> melts, and of the face, Which of the whole world had the ſecond place, Baſins and Ewres, Pots, Frying-pans are made—</note> melted, their terrour and threatning changed, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:158486:27"/>
fitted for man's uſe and pleaſure: With like reverence to the Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; you, <hi>Caeſar,</hi> will not ſuffer us to give thanks for your goodneſſe to your <hi>Genius</hi> in your<note n="o" place="margin">As <hi>Domitian</hi> commanded, who cauſed a woman to be put to death for undreſſing her ſelfe before his Statues <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> who ſaies he filled the world with his ſilver and gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſtatues, but concludes (as <hi>Pliny</hi> here) that they were broke, and ſold, and a vaſt ſum of money ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed out of their conflation.</note> ſtatues, but to the divinity of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> the beſt and greateſt; what we are indebted to you we pay to him, and acknowledge your well doing to be his gift that gave us you. Whereas formerly mighty flocks of Sacrifices ſo crowded the high way to the Capitol, that a great part of them was inforced to turne back and and ſeeke out blind Lanes to get thither, when our<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Domitian</hi>'s whoſe Deity was ſo intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</note> Lord's feirce Images were worſhipped with as much blood of beaſts, as hee ſhed blood of men. My Lords, all I have or ſhall ſpeake of former Princes, tends only ſo farre as to ſhew what cuſtomary and long cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted manners our parent hath corrected and reformed. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, thoſe prayſes want their beauty that are not ſhadowed with compariſon. Beſides, it is the generall duty of pious Subjects to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their beſt Emperour to taxe thoſe that were vnlike him, for they cannot ſufficiently love good Princes, that diſreliſh not the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill. Add, that no merit of our Emperour is more great and glorious, then that 'tis ſafe under him to ſpeake againſt ill Princes. Hath our griefe forgotten the late<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epaphroditus Nero</hi>'s freed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, whom <hi>Domitian</hi> had once acquitted, he then execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, charging him as acceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to <hi>Nero</hi>'s death, that pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing him, it might before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand bee a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition of terror to his own freed-men not to aſſiſt him if he ſhould intreat them. <hi>Dion.</hi>
               </note> revenge for <hi>Nero?</hi> Can I conceive hee would permit <hi>Nero</hi>'s fame and life to be cenſured that did revenge his death? and would not interpret that to be ſpoken of himſelfe, which was ſpoken of one ſo like him. Therefore <hi>(Caeſar)</hi> you have equall'd, nay exceeded the moſt of your bounties, that you permit us daily, both to vindicate our ſelves of our evill Emperours for the time paſt, and to admoniſh future Princes, by their example, that there is no place, no time, wherein the ſpirits of Tyrants can reſt quiet from the execrations of poſterity: Therefore, My Lords, ſince we may as boldly utter our griefe, as our joy, let us likewiſe mourn for what we have ſuffer'd. We may doe both together under a good Prince; This let our ſecret diſcourſes doe, this our publique ſpeeches, this our thankſgivings, and let us remember the living Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour is then higheſt prayſed when his ill-deſerving predeceſſors are reprehended; for, when ſucceſſion ſayes nothing of an evil Prince, 'tis manifeſt he that ſucceeds him is the like. And what place, then, was left for miſerable<note n="r" place="margin">Flattery was come to an incredible height in <hi>Domitian</hi>'s time, as you may ſee by the Fiſher man that ſpeakes to him in <hi>Juv.</hi> Sat. 4. With ſpeed thy ſtomack cleare of common meate, And this untill thy time kept <hi>Turbut</hi> eate, 'Twould needs be caught, could any Raſcall gloſe More plainly? yet this Peacocks-feathers roſe. Nothing ſo groſſe but will beleefe encline, When that powr's prays'd equalls the powrs Divine.</note> flattery, when the prayſes of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:158486:27"/>
were celebrated in playes, at banquets, and in jigges, with all kind of broken and effeminate voices, garbs and faſhions. But what ſhame, that at the ſame time they ſhould be prayſed in the <hi>Scene</hi> and in the <hi>Senate;</hi> by the <hi>Player</hi> and by the <hi>Conſul?</hi> Farre from your prayſes you have removed all thoſe mock-Arts; ſerious verſes therefore, and the eternall honour of our Annals, not a ſhort and laſcivious ſpeech paies veneration to your name; nay the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges themſelves riſe up to doe you honor, ſince the ſcenes were ſilent. But why doe I make this a wonder? When thoſe very honours which we offer you, eyther you take them very ſparingly, or not at all. Of old, nothing ſo vulgar or triviall was agitated in Senate, but the proceedings were hindred with the prayſe of Princes, a neceſſity lying upon every Senator, firſt to paſſe his vote for them. We con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted about increaſing the number of Gladiators, about inſtituting a colledge of Smithes; and as if the bounds of the Empire had beene enlarged, we dedicated to the names of <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s now mighty Arches with inſcriptions w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> Temples ſcarce could hold now the<note n="ſ" place="margin">Becauſe <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> was born in <hi>October</hi> he na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth <hi>Domitian. Dion.</hi> He like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe named <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tember Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicus,</hi> from the ſtile which hee had aſſumed.</note> months of the yeare, two or three at once; all which they ſuffered, and as if they had deſerved it, rejoyc't: But now, which of us, forgetting the cauſe in agitation, paſſeth his vote in honour of the Prince? This is the prayſe of your moderation, and our conſtancy, that wee obey you by aſſembling in Senate, not to flatter you, but for the uſe and offices of Juſtice; and that being to doe our duties to you, we owe this to your candour and truth, that we may beleeve that you accept<note n="t" place="margin">Contrary to the practice of <hi>Tiberius</hi> &amp; <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitian,</hi> whoſe Letters &amp; ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches were no re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monſtrances of their intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> what is pleaſing, and refuſe what you diſlike. We beginne and end our conſultations ſo, as we neither might beginne nor end them under another Prince. For true it is, there have beene others that recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not divers honours decreed by us, none before you was of ſo great a Soule, that we beleeve he wiſhed them vndecreed. And truly ſhould we compare with the neceſſity of former times, wee ſhould be much exceeded. For <hi>diſſimulation</hi> is more ingenious, then <hi>truth, ſervitude</hi> then <hi>liberty, feare</hi> then <hi>love;</hi> Beſides, all invention being long ſince ſpent in flattery, no other new honour remaines for us to give you, but only to take the boldneſſe ſometimes to ſay nothing. Notwithſtanding if at any time our piety breake ſilence, it prevailes upon your modeſty; Whatſoever we decree, you refuſe not, that it may appeare, you have not, out of pride and diſdaine, waved the higheſt honours, that doe not ſcorne the loweſt. This, <hi>Caeſar,</hi> is more honour to you, then if you refuſed all; for to refuſe all argues ambition, but it is moderation to chooſe the ſmalleſt; which temper
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:158486:28"/>
of yours is both a benefit to us and to the Treaſury; you thereby limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the expenſe thereof, not drayning it, to be repleniſhed with the fortunes of the innocent. Your effigies therefore ſtand, as thoſe of old that were dedicated to private perſons for their glorious merits towards the publique. We ſee the Statues of our <hi>Caeſar</hi> made of the ſame matter with the<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>L. Brutus</hi> (that expelled the <hi>Tarquins</hi>) had a brazen Statue ſet up in the Capitol. <hi>M. Bru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tus,</hi> that conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againſt <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi>) his Statue was at <hi>Millain. Plutarch Furt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Camillus</hi> that preſerved <hi>Rome</hi> from the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Galls,</hi> his Statue ſtood in the place for O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, <hi>Pliny</hi> lib. 24.</note> 
               <hi>Brutuſes,</hi> with the <hi>Camilli;</hi> nor doth the cauſe differ, for they expel'd the tyrants, &amp; beat the victorius enemy from our walls; you have baniſhed and removed tyranny it ſelfe and all the other fruits of our captivitie, and taken the place of a <hi>Prince,</hi> leſt there ſhould be roome left for a <hi>Tyrant.</hi> And when I looke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your wiſdome I leſſe wonder at your ſhunning or moderating thoſe mortall and frayle titles, for you know wherein the true and eternall glory of a Prince conſiſts, and where thoſe honours are, over which no flames, no time, no ſucceſſours have power. For trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phall Arches and Statues; nay even Altars and Temples oblivion ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines and obſcures, poſterity neglects and cenſures. Contrarily the contemner of ambition, the conquerour and brideler of unlimited power the minde flouriſheth in age, nor is by any more extolled, then by thoſe whom it cannot advantage, the ſucceeding times. A Prince therefore ſhould not covet fame which is <hi>eternall,</hi> for that he needs muſt have, but which is <hi>good;</hi> and that is perpetuated, not by Images and Statues, but by virtue and merit. But theſe trifles, the forme and figure of a Prince, are not expreſſed ſo lively and venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly in gold or ſilver, as in the hearts of men, wherein you are engra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the life, your amiable lookes and cheerefull aſpect being printed in the tongues, eyes and ſoules of all men. I conceive your Lordſhips have already taken notice that I make no choice of my diſcourſe, for my deſigne is to prayſe the Prince, not the <hi>Prince</hi>'s a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; for the evill doe many things prayſe-worthy, but the man himſelfe cannot be prayſed, unleſſe he be excellently good. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, dread Soveraigne, you have no glory greater, then that in the preſentation of our thanks we neede to conceale nothing, to omit nothing. For what is there in your reigne that any ſpeaker ſhould diſguiſe or paſſe it over? For what moment, nay what point of time hath beene fruitleſſe in benefits, or void of glory? Are not all of ſuch a nature, that hee appeares to prayſe you beſt, that ſpeakes truth moſt ſincerely. Which is the reaſon that my Oration growes almoſt boundleſſe, and yet I have not gone through your ſecond yeare. How much have I ſpoken of your moderation, and yet how much more remaines! as that of receiving your ſecond Conſulſhip,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:158486:28"/>
becauſe the Prince your<note n="*" place="margin">In <hi>Trajan</hi>'s firſt Conſulſhip (under <hi>Domiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi>) his Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legue was <hi>Gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brio,</hi> in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Emp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Nerva</hi> his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopted Father <hi>Vitruvius.</hi>
               </note> Father conferred it. But after the Gods had transferred the Soveraigne power to you, and with all other things the free diſpoſall of your ſelfe, you refuſed a third Conſulſhip, when you knew ſo well how to diſcharge the office. It is a great act to wave honour, a greater to put off glory. Should I admire your Conſulſhip <hi>executed,</hi> or <hi>refuſed.</hi> Executed not upon idle Couches, and in the private boſome of peace here in towne, but upon the borders of<note n="x" place="margin">Germany.</note> barbarous Nations, as<note n="y" place="margin">That were both Conſuls and Generals.</note> thoſe were wont to doe that uſed to change the long purple Robe, for the ſhort purple Caſſocke, and to diſcover unknowne lands by victories. It was honourable for the Empire, glorious for your ſelfe, when our confederates made their addreſſes to you, in their owne Country, in their owne habitations. How comely ſhewed the Conſul's face, when for a long time his tribunall was erected upon the living turfe, nor attended with our<note n="z" place="margin">The Axe in the midſt of the bundle of rods, ſtill borne by the <hi>Lectors,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſul, ſignifying the different pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of capitall and pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty offenders.</note> 
               <hi>faſces</hi> only, but with the honour of our<note n="a" place="margin">Javelins hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angular iron of nine ounces, a weapon peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar to the <hi>Roman</hi> Foote.</note> 
               <hi>Piles</hi> and <hi>Enſignes.</hi> The Majeſtie of the Judge, was increaſed by the various habits of Petitioners; and diverſity of language, ſcarce any ſpeaking but by his interpreter. 'Tis magnificent to give the law to your Subjects, what to the enemie! It ſhewes gloriouſly to heare cauſes in the ſettled peace of the <hi>Forum,</hi> what then to ſet the<note n="b" place="margin">An Ivory Chaire, which becauſe when the Conſul or Pretour went abroad, it was carried along in a Chariot, was called <hi>Sella Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulis,</hi> the Curule or Chariot-chaire.</note> Curule chaire in wild <hi>Campanias,</hi> on the ground which you had conquered? and to overlooke the threatning banks of <hi>Danubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> ſafe and quiet? what to deſpiſe the fury of Barbarians, and to checke their hoſtile terrour, not more with the ſhow of <hi>armes,</hi> then of <hi>gownes.</hi> Nor did our legions reverence you only in your<note n="c" place="margin">The firſt Cohort ever bore in their ſheilds the Emperours Image. <hi>Vegetius.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>images,</hi> but ſaluted the <hi>Generall</hi> himſelfe, that ſaw and heard them; and that name which others deſerved for <hi>conquering,</hi> you merited for <hi>deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> of the enemie. That is the praiſe of your <hi>executed;</hi> and this of your <hi>adjourned</hi> Conſulſhip, that it was the beginning of your reigne, ſo as now full <hi>of,</hi> and therefore excuſed <hi>from</hi> honour, you were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to refuſe the Conſulſhip, which our new Emperours, when others have beene elected, tooke unto themſelves. There was one, that in the end of his reigne, had ſuch a longing to the place, as when the<note n="d" place="margin">I ſuppoſe he meanes the Conſulſhip of <hi>Traian</hi>'s firſt Collegue, <hi>M. Acilius Glabrio,</hi> whom <hi>Domitian</hi> baniſhed, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſupplied his place.</note> Conſulſhip was almoſt ended he wreſted the remainder into his owne hands. This honour therefore, which both at their beginning and ending Princes ſo covet, that they ſnatch it away, you (when the place was void) left to<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Making Conſuls</hi> C. Socius Senecio <hi>11. and</hi> A. Cornelius Palma. Vitru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius.</note> private men. Was it that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:158486:29"/>
you envyed <hi>Trajan</hi> the third Conſulſhip, or the <hi>Prince</hi> the firſt? For the ſecond, 'tis true, that when you had it you were an Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, but yet under an Emperour, and therein you can attribute to your ſelfe nothing, either of honour or example, but in your obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. So then in this City, which hath ſeene the ſame men the fifth and ſixt time Conſuls, not ſuch as were in our expiring liberty, crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by force and tumult, but ſuch, as retired and<note n="f" place="margin">Such as <hi>L. Quintius Cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinnatus</hi> (who <hi>Pliny</hi> preſently names) who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing at worke in his grounds be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond <hi>Tyber</hi> was by meſſengers from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Rome</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted Dictator.</note> abſent, had the Conſulſhip brought into the Country to them; In this very City, have you, being Prince of mankinde, refuſed a third Conſulſhippe. Was<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>L Papyrius</hi> for his unparal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leld ſtrength &amp; agility of body ſurnamed <hi>Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor,</hi> was yet the moſt moderate man that lived, moſt favorable to the weakneſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes of others. This is the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyrius</hi> whom <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vy</hi> endevours to prove able to have encountred <hi>Alexander,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f he had attemp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of the W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt.</note> 
               <hi>Papirius</hi> himſelfe, or <hi>Quintius</hi> more moderate? <hi>Auguſtus</hi> and <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and Father of your Country. But the Republique called them, what you? did not the ſame <hi>Republique?</hi> did not the <hi>Senate,</hi> did not the very Conſulſhip, that conceives it ſelfe advanced and made greater by your acceptation. I doe not ſet<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Dion,</hi> In <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitian,</hi> ſayes, he was ſo foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly proud that he made himſelfe Conſul [which Office ought but to continue for one yeare] ten years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> him for your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern, who by his continued Conſulſhip, made a kind of long and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtinguiſhable yeare, but I compare you to thoſe who (we are ſure) as oft as they were Conſuls, were not ſo with relation to themſelves. There was in the Senate<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Virginius Rufus,</hi> who was Conſul the third time with <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rva,</hi> and being deſigned for his fourth Conſulſhip by <hi>Trajan</hi> died before he was declared.</note> one that had thrice been Conſul, when you refuſed your third Conſulſhip. A heavy taske our votes would have impoſed upon your modeſty, that you the Prince ſhould be as often Conſul, as your Senatour; The refuſall whereof would have argued too much baſhfulneſſe, even when you were a private man, the ſonne of a Conſular and a tryumphant Father: when hee a third time is created Conſul, doth hee aſcend? is it not his due? yea though he could pleade no other merit, but the nobilitie of his birth. Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate perſons therefore had the honour to open the<note n="k" place="margin">The <hi>Romans</hi> dated their Records and Deedes from Conſulſhips, as we doe from kings Reignes, and the Conſuls began with the yeare, in January.</note> yeare, and to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock the<note n="l" place="margin">The <hi>Roman Kalender</hi> began with the Conſuls names, proceeded with the <hi>Feſtivals,</hi> &amp; Court dayes, which properly were the <hi>Faſti.</hi>
               </note> Kalender, and this likewiſe was an inſtance of liberty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored, that another was Conſul, and not <hi>Caeſar.</hi> Thus the Tyrants being expelled, the free yeare beganne, thus heretofore, ſervitude ſhaken off, our Kalender was inſcribed with the names of private men. Miſerable they were in their ambition that continued their Conſulſhippes like their Principalitie, yet ſeemes it not to be more their ambition, then their envy and malignitie, to ingroſſe to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves all yeares, and not to put off that ſupreame ornament of the purple, but when it was worne and ſoiled like their old robes. But in you, which ſhall I firſt admire, magnanimity, or modeſtie, or
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:158486:29"/>
bounty, It was magnanimity to abſteine from an honour ſo much affected by Princes, modeſty to wave it, bounty to enjoy it by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. But now it is time that you do a favour to the Conſulſhip it ſelfe, that by undertaking to mannage it, you may make it greater; for ſtill to refuſe, would beare an ambiguous interpretation, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſignifie, that you thought it too meane. It is true, you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed it as the greateſt, but none will be ſo perſwaded, unleſſe ſometimes you will likewiſe not refuſe it. When you excuſe your ſelfe from triumphall Arches, from Trophies, from ſtatues we may par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don your modeſty, for indeede thoſe are dedicated to <hi>your ſelfe:</hi> But we now make it our ſuite, that you will teach future Princes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce idleneſſe, a while to adjourne their pleaſures, awhile, at leaſt for a little while, to awake out of their ſlumber of felicity, to put on our pretexted purple, (which when they ſhould have beſtowed they have invaded) and to aſcend the Sella Curulis, [the Chariot tribunall] which 'tis fit they ſhould poſſeſſe; laſtly, to be <hi>indeed</hi> what they have coveted to <hi>ſeeme,</hi> not to deſire the name of Conſul only for the name. You have diſcharged a ſecond Conſulſhippe, I know it, but that you may alleage, as a favour to our Armies, to our Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to forreyne nations, not to us. We have heard indeed, you have done all that concerns the office of a Conſul, but wee have <hi>heard;</hi> It is reported you were moſt juſt, moſt gratious, moſt pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, but it is <hi>reported.</hi> 'Tis fit, that ſometimes we ſhould credit our owne judgment, our owne eyes, not alwaies fame and rumor. How long abſent from one another ſhall we joy in you, give us leave to make triall, whether that ſecond Conſulſhippe have put no pride in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you. Halfe a yeare hath much influence upon the manners of men, much more of Princes. Indeed, we ſay he that hath one ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue hath all, yet we deſire a proofe, whether once againe a good <hi>Conſul</hi> and a good <hi>Prince</hi> be one and the ſame thing. For beſides the difficulty of mannageing two, and both of them ſoveraigne powers, there is likewiſe diverſity in the powers themſelves, for that may become a <hi>Prince,</hi> which a <hi>Conſul</hi> muſt not doe. But I ſee the cheefeſt reaſon that moved you, next yeare, to refuſe the Conſulſhippe, was, that you could not diſcharge it in your abſence; but now being reſtored to the Citty and our publicke wiſhes, wherein can you clearlyer ſhew us, what and how great the bleſſing was, that we deſired? It were little favour to <hi>Come</hi> into the Senate, unleſſe you pleaſe to <hi>aſſemble</hi> it, to be <hi>preſent,</hi> unleſſe <hi>preſident,</hi> to heare us paſſe our votes, unleſſe you would give ſentence. Would
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:158486:30"/>
you as our Conſul, in time reſtore to i'ts majeſty, that dread Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall? aſcend. Would you have awefulneſſe in the Magiſtrate, autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in the Lawes and modeſty in the Petulant? ſit in perſon in the Senate. For ſo much as it would have concerned our Republike if you were a private man, not to have you only our Conſull unleſſe you likewiſe were a Senator, ſo much it concernes your ſelfe not to be only our Prince, unleſſe you likewiſe be our Conſull. With theſe ſo many and prevalent reaſons though our Prince's modeſty long ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, yet at laſt it yielded; but how? not to equall himſelfe with private men, but to make private men his equalls. For he a third time <hi>received</hi> the Conſulſhip, that he might a third time give it; for he knew mens moderation, he knew their baſhfullneſſe that would not indure a third time to be Conſuls, unleſſe a third time he were Conſul with them. Anciently this honour was beſtowed and that ſparingly upon adjutants to <hi>Generalls,</hi> and partners in their dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,<note n="*" place="margin">Vide ſis (m)</note> which you have given to two particular men, that indeed have ſerved you faithfully and valiantly, but in the <hi>gowne.</hi> Both their cares both their induſtryes have layed an obligation <hi>Caeſar</hi> upon you; but in a Prince 'tis rare and ſeldome heard of, to think himſelfe obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, or thinking ſo to love. You therefore, <hi>Caeſar,</hi> owe and pay, but when a third time you make Conſuls, you thinke not in ſo doing, that you are a <hi>great Prince,</hi> but that you are not an <hi>ingratefull freind.</hi> Nay even the low deſervings of your ſubjects you raiſe higher by the ſupremacy of your fortune, for you make every one thought to have done you ſervice according to the greatneſſe of your retribution. What prayers ſhall I make for ſuch benignity? but that you may ever oblige, ever be obliged, and leave it doubtfull whether it were more expedient for your ſubjects to be your debters, or to have you theirs. Truly methought I ſaw that ancient Senate, when one thrice Conſul ſitting, one a third time deſigned Conſul ſtood to deſire ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frages. As great as they were then, ſo great are you. It happens in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed that bodies though vaſt and high, approaching higher bodies then themſelves, decreaſe, in like manner the greateſt ſubjects dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities compared with your greatneſſe, looſe their height, and the nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer they aſcend to your elevation, the more they ſeeme to deſcend from their owne. Yet thoſe, which though you would you could not raiſe to your owne height, you have yet placed ſo conſpicuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as they appear as much above others, as below you: If a third time you had made one Conſul in the ſame yeare with your ſelfe, it had argued a great ſoule. For as it is a declaration of felicity to have
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:158486:30"/>
as much power as will, ſo it is of greatneſſe to have as much will, as power. Even he is to be prayſed I muſt confeſſe, that merited a third Conſulſhippe, but he more under whom 'twas merited; he muſt be great and worthy of a hiſtory that <hi>received</hi> ſo great a retribution, but he much greater that <hi>beſtowed</hi> it. What ſhall I ſay that in the yeare of your third Conſulſhippe you honoured<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>M. Corneliu Fronto</hi> was Conſul the third time when <hi>Traian</hi> entered upon his owne third Conſulſhip; but who the other was, appeares not to my read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> two by making them Collegues to your Sacred Majeſty. That none can doubt, but it was your only reaſon for proroguing of your Conſulſhippe, that it might containe the Conſulſhippe of both, and make you awhole yeare Collegue to one of them. Both received their ſecond Conſulſhipps from your father, that is, how much was that honour leſſe, then what you give! Their but now reſigned faſces wandred yet before both their eies, that ſolemne cry of their late uſhering Lictours rung yet in both their eares, when the chariot chayre, when the purple came againe. As of old at the enemys approach, when the Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick brought to extremitie, required a knowne man of honour, we reſtored not the men to their Conſulſhipps, but reſtored the very Conſulſhipps unto the men. Such is the power of your goodneſſe, that neceſſity and your bountie are excuſed from the orders of the houſe. They have juſt now put off their pretexted purples, they muſt on with them againe, the Lictours were but now diſmiſſed, they muſt be called backe. Is this the nature of a man? the power of a man? to renue our joyes, to revive our Iubily, and to give no reſt to our gratulations, nor to ſuffer a further intervall of reattaining the Conſulſhipps, then the very inſtant time of reſignation. This may you ever do, nor may your mind or fortune ever be wearied in this action. May you give third Conſulſhips to many, and when you have given them to many, may there remaine ſtill more that deſerve them at your hands. In all the benefits that are beſtowed upon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervers the joy is not more their owne, then theirs that are of like de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts; but from the Conſulſhips of theſe two not to any particulars, but to all the Senate flowed ſo great joy as they conceived the ſame honour beſtowed upon and received by themſelves. For indeed theſe were they that the Senate firſt elected, when they choſe men to bring downe the publike expenſes. This is it therefore, this is it that ſo much indeared them to <hi>Caeſar.</hi> Have we not lately made too many trialls, that the Senate's judgement could with the Prince do neither good nor harme. A little while a go was any thing more fatall, then if the Prince had that way a ſuſpicion? This man the Senate approves of, this is in favour with the Senate, he hated
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:158486:31"/>
               <hi>our</hi> favourites, and we <hi>his.</hi> Now the Prince and Senate contend which ſhould moſt love worthy perſons, and indeare each other we make mutuall remonſtrances, we give mutuall evidence, and which is the greateſt argument of our mutuall affection we both love the ſame. Therefore, my Lords, publiſh your affections, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect with conſtancy. You neede not diſſemble your good opinion now for feare it hurt your ſelves, nor conceale your diſlike leſt it profit others. For <hi>Caeſar</hi> liketh and diſliketh with the Senate. When you are preſent, when you are abſent, he adviſeth with you, he made thoſe thrice Conſuls whom you had elected, and made them ſo, as they were elected by you. Both his favours appeare great, whether he love thoſe beſt whom he knowes deareſt to us, or preferres none before them, though he may love ſome better. Rewards are propoſed to old men, examples to young men: they may at length freely goe and give viſits at their friends ſecure and open houſes, every one welcomes the men that are in eſteeme with the Senate; ſuch a one moſt deſerves the Prince, for he thinks the honour that is done to any good man, done unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, nor placeth he any glory in being greater then all, unleſſe they alſo be great that muſt confeſſe him greater. <hi>Caeſar,</hi> continue in the reaſon of that reſolution, and eſteeme us ſuch as every ones <hi>fame</hi> is; To that vouchſafe your eare and eye, regard not clandeſtine eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and <hi>whiſpers,</hi> that do intrappe none ſooner, then ſuch as liſten to them. 'Tis better confiding in generalls then particulars. For parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars may coſen and be Coſened; none hath deceived all, all have deceived none. I now returne to your Conſulſhip, though many things there be appertaining, yet antecedent to it. Firſt that you were preſent at your Election, not only as<note n="n" place="margin">The Candi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dati (ſo named from their white or chalk<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed gownes which they wore in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection time) were thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat ſtood in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ior for Of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fices. from h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re <hi>Quin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an</hi> drawes his M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>phor when he calls a Schollar a Candidate of Eloquence; but his Schollar <hi>Pliny</hi> goes higher here, and calls <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jan</hi> a <hi>Candi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date</hi> of Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</note> Candidate of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulſhip, but of immortality, and glory, and example; which good Princes cannot but imitate, nor evill but admire. The people of <hi>Rome</hi> behold you in that<note n="o" place="margin">The Juſtice-hall wherein ſtood the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bun all erected on high lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our Pulpits, and within that was ſet the curule or chariot chaire of Ivory.</note> place of their antient power, where you patiently endured thoſe tedious<note n="p" place="margin">Doubtleſſe he meanes the prayers or Hymnes at E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, which were (by Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute) to be read by the preſident of the Aſſemblies; this appeares clearely towards the end of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negyrick, where he ſaies, You vouchſafed to be Preſident at our Election, and to read unto us thoſe moſt ſacred Verſes.</note> verſes read before Election, and that now not fained nor ridiculous demurr, &amp; you were made Conſul after the ſame manner as you make one of us. Where was a Prince among your Predeceſſors that either did that honour to the Conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe, or to the people? Did not others dull with ſleepe and<note n="q" place="margin">As <hi>Nero,</hi> who (ſayes <hi>Suet Tranquillus</hi>) ſpunne out his dinner from noone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day to midnight; this fat <hi>Montanus</hi> remembred <hi>Juv. Sat.</hi> 4. Who th'old court-riot knew And <hi>Nero's</hi> mid-nights and a hunger new When <hi>Falerne</hi> wine inflam'd the lights—</note> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloyed
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:158486:31"/>
with their laſt nights ſupper, make the meſſengers of their Election waite?<note n="r" place="margin">As <hi>Caligula</hi> who ſtept not above; houres a night, and <hi>Domitian,</hi> who walkt much in the night time, whom all that followes here concernes, as you may ſee by naming of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nubius</hi> and the <hi>Rheyne,</hi> inceſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous nights &amp;c.</note> Others waking indeed, and ſleepleſſe, but within the walls of their bed-chambers ploting the baniſhment, and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of thoſe very Conſuls that declared them Conſuls. O de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved ambition and ignorant of true Majeſtie! to covet the honour thou ſo diſdaigneſt, to diſdaigne the honour thou ſo coveteſt; and when out of thy gardens thou ſeeſt the feilds and the Election, yet to be ſo abſent from them, as if thou wert to paſſe a ford in <hi>Danubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> or the <hi>Rhene!</hi> Doſt thou hate the ſuffrages of thy deſired ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour? and being contented to have newes brought of thy Conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe wilt thou not permit a free Citty to diſſemble bondage? laſtly, doſt thou conceale and hide thy ſelfe from the Election, as if they were not to give thee a Conſulſhippe, but to deprive thee of thy Empire? Our proudeſt Lords had this perſwaſion, that they ceaſed to be <hi>Princes,</hi> if they did any thing like a <hi>Senatour</hi> Yet many kept away not ſo much out of <hi>pride,</hi> as out of <hi>feare,</hi> whether (being guilty of adulterous and inceſtuous nights,) they might preſume to pollute the auguryes and with their wicked feet to contaminate the ſacred<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Campus</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, the Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on place con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated to the God <hi>Mars.</hi>
               </note> Feilds. They had not heaven and earth in ſuch contempt, as in that ſpatious plaine they durſt ſtand the darted eyes of men and Gods. On the contrary your moderation perſwades you to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, both when religion is to be excerciſed towards the Gods and ſentence paſſed by men. Others before they received, but you me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited the Conſulſhippe in your very manner of receiving it; the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne forme was needleſſe if you had conſidered you ſelfe as a Prince, and now the aſſembly was diſſolving, when you (to the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement of us all) came vp to the Conſuls Chayre, offering your ſelfe to take the<note n="t" place="margin">The matter of the oath taken by the Conſul is expreſſed in the the words fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, <hi>viz.</hi> that he devoted his head and his houſe to the wrath of heaven, if (during the yeare of his Conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip) he did any thing contrary to Law.</note> oath in words unknowne to Princes, but when they inforced others to ſweare. You ſee how neceſſary it was, not to refuſe, for we ſhould never have imagined you would have done it, if you had refuſed the Conſulſhippe. My Lords, I am aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, nor can yet ſufficiently credit my owne eies or eares, but now and then I queſtion my ſelfe if I have truly heard and ſeene it. Our<note n="u" place="margin">The Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted in the Titles of <hi>Caeſar Auguſtus Pontifex Maximus,</hi> and had <hi>Tribunician</hi> and <hi>Proconſular</hi> power annexed to their crownes.</note> Emperour, and <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> and <hi>Pontifex Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> roſe up, and the Conſull ſate while the Prince ſtood before him, and ſate untroubled unmoved, and as if he had beene accuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo to doe. Nay ſitting he adminiſtred the Oath, and the Prince tooke it, and clearely uttered words wherein he devoted his head
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:158486:32"/>
&amp; his houſe to the Gods wrath, if his Oath were violated. Your glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>Caeſar,</hi> is mighty and the ſame whether future Princes ſhall or ſhall not do it, what words are worthy to expreſſe, that you would doe the ſame the <hi>third time,</hi> as when you <hi>firſt</hi> were Conſul! the ſame when a <hi>Prince</hi> as when a <hi>private man,</hi> the ſame when an <hi>Emperour</hi> as when a <hi>Subject</hi> to an Emperor. Now I confeſſe I know not what was moſt be comming, that you ſhould doe it without or with a<note n="*" place="margin">The eare of antiquity in things ſacred, was ſo great that they ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a prompter or one that ſhould reade it ſoftly to thoſe that were to pronounce it cleerely, as you may perceive by the great Lady that made her offring for the fidler. <hi>Juv. Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 6. She ſtood at th'<hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar,</hi> as the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner is. And ſpake the prompted words of Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</note> prompter. In the <hi>Forum</hi> likewiſe you ſubjected your ſelfe to the Lawes which no Legiſlator ever made for Princes. But you will have your priviledge no greater then a <hi>Subjects,</hi> therefore we will have it greater then an <hi>Emperours.</hi> This is the firſt time I ever heard, the firſt I ever knew; we have no<note n="x" place="margin">For he hath deſcended to be a Conſul.</note> Prince, we have Lawes, but Lawes<note n="y" place="margin">Becauſe as Conſul he had ſubjected him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by Oath unto the Lawes</note> above the Prince; <hi>Caeſar</hi> the Conſul may not do what others may, he ſweares to obſerve the Lawes in preſence of the Gods (for where are they more preſent then with <hi>Caeſar?</hi>) hee ſweares in preſence of the men that are to ſweare the ſame, nor is he ignorant that none ought more religiouſly to keepe his oath, then he that is moſt concerned not to breake it. And therefore when you were to reſigne your Conſulſhip, you made oath you had done nothing contrary to Law. It was a great act to <hi>make</hi> ſuch a promiſe, but a greater to <hi>performe</hi> it, Then to go ſo often to our Courts of Juſtice, in the <hi>Forum,</hi> and make a new path to that place unaſcended by the pride of Princes, there to receive, there to lay down your Magiſtracie, how worthy your ſelf, how different was it from their cuſtomes, by whom their for a few daies exerciſed (nay unexerciſed) Conſulſhip was diſclaimed by Edict! The like they did for the convention of Senate, for the Tribunall, for the Oath, that ſo the laſt might be agreeable to the firſt, and they only known to have beene Conſuls, becauſe others were not. My Lords, I have not paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed over our Princes Conſulſhip, but I have brought together unto this one place all that concerned his Oath. For we muſt not as in a barren ſubject, ſpinne out and ſcatter the ſame ſpecies of praiſe, and handle one thing twice. In the glorious dawning of the firſt day of your third Conſulſhippe, when you came unto the Senate, now ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verallie, now univerſallie you encouraged us all to reſume our liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, to take upon us, as it were, the care of the common Empire, to be vigilant and intend the publique benefit. All before you ſaid the very ſelfe ſame things, but none before you was beleeved. There was yet floating in our eyes the ſhipwracks of many Senatours, whom (flattered with ſuch promiſed Calmes) a ſudden ſtorme had ſunke. For what Sea ſo faithleſſe as the<note n="z" place="margin">You read in <hi>Domitian's</hi> Character (the words are <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on's</hi>) he ever ſeemed to love him moſt, whoſe bloud he moſt deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> ſmiles of thoſe Princes, that
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:158486:32"/>
had ſo much ſeeming lenity, ſo much reall cunning, as it was eaſier to have them angry then propitious! But ſecure and chearefull we exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute whatſoever you command. You bid us uſe our freedome, we take it; you bid us ſpeake our thoughts, we doe it; nor have we o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted it out of any habituall ſloath or naturall dulneſſe; It was ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and feare, and that miſerable wiſedome taught by dangers, that from the Common-wealth (but it was indeed no Common-wealth) made us turne our eies, our eares, and hearts. But now ſtrengthened by your hand, and relying on your promiſes, we open our lips ſo long lockt up in ſervitude, and let looſe our tongues bridled in with ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dangers. For you would have us ſuch as you bid us be; in your encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements nothing is diſſembled, or betraying; in ſhort, nothing contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to undoe the credulous, not without danger to the contriver, for never yet was Prince deceived, but he himſelfe had firſt deceived o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. In this ſence I underſtood our publike parent, when I obſerved his Hortatives, and the energy of his pronunciation. For what im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported that weight of ſentences! How inaffected was the truth of his words! What aſſeveration in his accent! What affirmation in his looke! What confirmation in his eies, habit, meene, laſtly in his whole body! He therefore will be alwaies mindfull of what he hath incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged us unto, and will remember that as often as we uſe the liberty he gave us, we doe but his commands. Nor will he hold them to be unwiſe that confide in the freedome of theſe times, when he knew them to have done otherwiſe under a bad Prince. We uſed to pray for preſervation of the Empire, and the ſubject, nay for preſervation of Emperours, and for their ſakes of the Empire. We yet pray for the Empire in the ſame words, with theſe (worthy to be noted) added to them, if you governe the Republicke well and for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of all. Vowes for ever to be owed, for ever to be paid. The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publicke, <hi>Caeſar,</hi> hath made a Covenant with the Gods of your owne drawing, that their deities ſhould keepe you in peace and ſafety, if you kept others ſo. If otherwiſe, that they ſhould draw away their eies from the guard of your perſon, and leave you to ſuch praiers as are not made in publike. Other Princes wiſhed and endevoured to ſurvive the Republicke, to you your owne health and ſafety is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing, if it goe not along with the common health and ſafety. You ſuffer no prayer to be made for you, unleſſe expedient for thoſe that pray it, and ſolemnely every yeare you call a court of Gods (your E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectours) to give ſentence againſt you, if you ceaſe to be ſuch as you were when they elected you. Thus with a great and immaculate
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:158486:33"/>
ſoule you article with the Gods to give you the protection you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, knowing the Gods are the beſt Judges of your merit. Doe you thinke, my Lords, that day and night he conſiders not theſe, his owne words, <hi>Truly if the generall good ſhould ſo require, I have armed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my ſelfe the very hand of the</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>L. Licinius Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> from a Cen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turion, made Praefect of Praetorians by <hi>Traian,</hi> to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when he put the ſword in his hand, <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ian</hi> ſaid, Take this, and if I go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne well uſe it for me, if all, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me. And truly I doe not wonder at this perſonall confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in one he ſo dearely loved (as you will ſee before the end of the Panegy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke) when <hi>I</hi> conſider <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ian</hi>'s nature, &amp; how fa re he truſted the very ſervants of <hi>Sura</hi> even when <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> himſelfe was calumniated by ſome other of the Emperours freinds; for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven then <hi>Traian</hi> diſmiſſing his guard, went to <hi>Sura</hi>'s houſe, to ſupper, and calling firſt for <hi>Sura</hi>'s Phiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made him waſh his eies, then ſent for his bar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber and he ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved his beard, and next day told thoſe freinds that ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected <hi>Sura,</hi> that if he had meant to kill him he would undoubtedly have done it yeſterday. <hi>Dion.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Captaine of my Guard, nor doe I either deprecate the anger of the Gods, or pray for their connivance, nay I pray that I may command him nothing prejudiciall to the Empire, or if I doe, that he may not obey it;</hi> Therefore you, <hi>Caeſar,</hi> reape the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious fruit of ſafety by the Gods conſent, for when you condition the Gods ſhould preſerve you ſo long as you governe well, you are ſure you governe well ſo long as they preſerve you. To you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhall the day be joyfull and ſecure, that diſtracted other Princes with cares and feares, when in ſuſpence and aſtoniſhment, not confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of our patience, from this and that place they expected meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of the publike ſervitude; and if by chance the waters, winds, or ſnow, had hindred them, preſently they ſuſpected what they had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. Nor did their feare make any difference of perſons; for when by an evill Prince every worthy man is feared as a ſucceſſour, there being none but worthier, all muſt needs be feared. Your ſecurity no ſlow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of meſſengers, no ſtoppe of letters can ſuſpend; you know that every where men are ſworne and bound to ſerve you, becauſe you have ſworn &amp; bound your ſelfe to protect them. No one but reſpects his owne good. Indeed we love you for your deſerts, yet ſtill we love you not for your ſake, but our owne. Nor ever, <hi>Caeſar,</hi> ſhall we ſee the day wherein our loyalty more then our benefit ſhall engage our prayers. Protection for their owne intereſt would derogate from Princes. Let us now put the queſtion why no Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces looke into theſe ſecret thoughts of ours, but onely thoſe we love not; for if the good obſerved us as attentively as the bad, what joy, what exultation, what admiration of your ſelfe would you find every where! what diſcourſes of you even among women and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in their private houſes, ſitting by their fires! you would know we ſpare your tender eares, and that love and hate being contraries yet in this agree that we love good Princes more intemperate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, after we have more freely hated bad ones. Yet you have had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience both of our affection and opinion, as much as could be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in your preſence, that day when you ſo prevented the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and bluſhes of the Candidates, that no mans joy was encountered with anothers ſorrow; ſome went off the feild with pleaſure, others with hope, many were to be gratulated, none to be comforted. Nor
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:158486:33"/>
did you therefore ſlowlier incourage our youth to ſtand for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulſhip, to ſupplicate the Senate, and ſo to hope for honours from the Prince by their addreſſes to the Senate. And if any want an example you have propoſed your ſelfe to his imitation. A hard ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, <hi>Caeſar,</hi> no more imitable by Candidates, then by Princes. For what Candidate is more obſervant of the Senate for a day, then you are for your life time, and then eſpecially when you are to judge of Candidates? Hath any thing but that reverence you beare the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, moved you to offer honours to our youth, due to their noble families, but paid before the day? At length therefore Nobility is not obſcured, but illuſtrated, by the Prince. At length, <hi>Caeſar</hi> nor terrifies, nor feares thoſe nephewes of great men, thoſe Deſcendents of Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but amplifies and heightens them with early honours, and reſtores them to their Anceſtours. If there be any branch of an ancient ſtock, he cheriſhes and brings it forth for the uſe of the Republicke. Great names are now in honour with men, and fame recovered out of the darkeneſſe of oblivion by <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s goodneſſe, which hath a property to preſerve and make Nobility. There was a<note n="b" place="margin">Treaſurer of a Province.</note> Queſtour of a Province among the Candidates, by whoſe care and induſtry a great City had eſtabliſhed their revenues by an excellent conſtitution, this you your ſelfe in his behalfe thought fit to alleadge unto the Senate. For in the reigne of our Prince whoſe virtue excells the greatneſſe of his birth, why ſhould they be in a worſe condition that deſerve a noble Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, then they that have had noble Anceſtours? O you moſt worthy for ever thus to encourage our Magiſtrates, nor doe you make men good by the puniſhment of vice, but by the reward of virtue. Our youth is enflamed and ſpirited to emulate what they ſee you praiſe. Nor could any one be otherwiſe, when he knew whatſoever was done abroad in the Provinces came entirely to your knowledge. 'Tis advantageous <hi>(Caeſar)</hi> for the Governours of Provinces to be confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent there is prepared for their piety and induſtry the greateſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, their Princes love and ſuffrage. But heretofore ſincere and juſt natures were, though not depraved, yet extreamely dulled and caſt downe, with a miſerable but true reputation. For what difference, whether <hi>Caeſar</hi> know not my good actions, or know but will not take notice of them. This very negligence or malignity of Princes, when it gave impunity to the evill, and promiſed no advancement to the good, deterred not thoſe from vice, yet deterred theſe from ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. But now if any one governe his Province well, the dignity won by his merit is offered him; for to all li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en a field of honour and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:158486:34"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:158486:34"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:158486:35"/>
glory, out of which every man may reape his wiſhes, and having reaped poſſeſſe them. You have likewiſe, for the future, freed our Provinces from the feare of injury, and neceſſity of accuſations; for they that give thanks to their Governours cannot poſſibly complain againſt them, and then the Candidate knowes, nothing can ſooner advance him for the <hi>future,</hi> then the good diſcharge of his <hi>paſt</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracie. Magiſtracie by Magiſtracie, honour is wonne by honour. I would not have Governours of Provinces to bring us the hands of their friends, or flattering Petitions ſigned by courted perſons, but to ſhew the Decrees of Colonies, the Decrees of Cities; That Cities, Countries and Nations may not come to mixe their ſuffrages with ours. The moſt efficacious way of petitioning for a Candidate will be to give him thanks. Now with what unanimous joy it affected the Senate, that ſtill as you named a Candidate, you met and kiſſed him, comming downe into the fields as one that joyed them. Shall I more admire <hi>you,</hi> or deſpiſe <hi>them</hi> who have made this favour ſeeme ſo great? When nailed as it were to their Curule chaires, they only vouchſafed their hand, and that ſlowe and ſtately, as if it were a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be deſerved honour. A ſtrange ſight therefore was preſented to our eyes, a Prince and a Candidate ſtanding on even ground, no difference betweene the receiver of honour and the giver. Which act of yours with what unfained acclamations was it celebrated by the whole Senate! You were ſo much more great, ſo much more ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ſtill; For he that is ſupreame hath only one way of riſing higher, if he ſubmit himſelfe, ſecure of his own greatneſſe. Nor is there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing that leſſe endangers a Prince's fortunes, then humilitie. To me, I muſt confeſſe, your humanity ſeemed not ſo rare as the way wherein you expreſſed it. Becauſe when your eyes, your voice, your hand were taken up with your Oration, yet as if you had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded another to ſpeake it for you, you omitted not the leaſt cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of civility. Nay, when the names of the voted were to be approved of, you were one of the approvers, and out of the Princes mouth paſſed the ſuffrage of a Senatour. And we that formerly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced if the Prince would take our teſtimony, the Prince's teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny was now given to us. Therefore while you affirmed the men to be deſerving, you made them ſo. Nor did you only approve of their virtues, but of their election by the Senate, whoſe joy, even theirs, which you had praiſed, exceeded not. Your very prayer, that the ordination of Magiſtrates might well and happily ſucceede, was it not a prayer for your ſelfe? ought we not to pay back thoſe wiſhes?
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:158486:35"/>
and laſtly to beſeech the Gods, that all you doe, or ſhall doe, may be proſperous to you, the Commonwealth, and us, or (to abbreviate the wiſh) to you alone, in whom both the Commonwealth and we ſubſiſt? There was a time (and too long a time) when the <hi>Prince</hi>'s and our felicity and infelicity were contraries, with you we now communicate both joy and griefe; nor could we any more be happy without you, then you could without us, and if you could, you had not (in the cloſe of your prayers) added, that the Gods would be ſo propitious to your vowes, as you perſevered to merit our opinions. So primarilie ſacred is your Subjects love in your eſteeme, that we are in the firſt place, then the Gods; and you only deſire the Gods may love you, in caſe you be beloved by us. And truely former Princes ends have taught us, that the Gods love them not, unleſſe men love them. 'Twas hard to equall this love of yours with prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, yet we have equalled it. What heate of love, what fire, what flame raiſed in us thoſe acclamations? It was not <hi>(Caeſar)</hi> the voice of our affection, but the voice of your merits, of your virtues, ſuch as no flatterie e're invented, no terrour ever yet expreſſed. Whom have we ſo loved thus to counterfeit? Whom have we ſo loved thus declare our ſelves? You know the neceſſity of ſervitude, when did you heare any thing of this kind? When did you ſpeake any thing like unto it? feare hath a great and quick invention, but ſuch as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares done unwillinglie. Feare hath one kind of wit, ſecurity ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; the invention of the dejected differs from that of the cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and that of the diſſembler from them both: the miſerable have their dialect, the happy theirs, all proper and peculiar to themſelves. Witneſſe your ſelfe, what joy in each mans countenance! neither the habit of the body, nor the habit of the mind the ſame it was. Hence it was that all our houſes were made vocall, no place ſo ſecret ſo barricadoed, that kept out the clamor. Who then leaped not over his threſhold? who was ſenſible that he did ſo? many things we did voluntarilie, many things by inſtinct and compulſion (for even joy it ſelfe hath a compulſory power.) Was your modeſty able to limit our exultation? No; for the more you ſtrove to quench it, the more it flamed, not out of contumacie, but as it is in your power whether we ſhall rejoyce, ſo it is not in our powers how much. You your ſelfe teſtified the faith of our acclamations, with the truth of your teares. We ſaw your eyes moiſtned, We ſaw you bluſhing for joy, with ſo much blood in your cheekes, as you had modeſtie in your heart, and this more inflamed our zeale to pray, that you might never want
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:158486:36"/>
the ſame cauſe of teares, never be leſſe out of countenance. Let us to theſe benches, as if they could anſwere, put the queſtion; have they ever ſeene a Prince's teares? the Senates teares they have ſeene often; you have burthened future Princes, and undone our po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, for they likewiſe will expect that Princes ſhould deſerve like acclamations, and Princes will be offended that they doe not heare them. The world can ſpeake nothing more proper to your merit, then what was ſpoken by the whole Senate. <hi>O happy you,</hi> which we ſaid not in admiration of your fortune, but of your mind. For it is true felicity to appeare worthy of felicitie. But, that day many things were ſpoken wiſely and gravely, this eſpecially, <hi>Credit us, Credit your ſelfe.</hi> We ſpake this with a mighty confidence in our ſelves, but more in you; for one may deceive another, but no one himſelfe, let him but looke into his life and aske himſelfe what he deſerves. Beſides, theſe very expreſſions gave us credit with the beſt Prince which diſcredited us with the bad, for though we beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved our ſelves affectionately towards them, yet they beleeved them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves they could not be beloved. Againe we prayed the Gods might ſo love you as you love us: Who would pray thus upon a mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate affection either to themſelves, or to their Prince? We deſired no greater good, but that the Gods would love us, as you doe. Is't not true, that with theſe acclamations we intermixed, <hi>O happy Wee!</hi> for what can be happier then we are, that have now no need to wiſh our Prince may love us, but the Gods equall with our Prince. This religiouſly devoted City, alwaies piouſly dependent on heaven's providence, conceives her happineſſe cannot bee increaſed, unleſſe the Gods pleaſe to imitate <hi>Caeſar.</hi> But why doe I follow or collect particulars, as if either my ſpeech could containe, or my memory comprehend them. Which, leſt they ſhould be intercepted by obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vion, your Lordſhips have commanded they ſhould be put into our publique Records, and likewiſe graven in braſſe. Heretofore Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Orations only had ſuch monuments, but our acclamations were ſtill incloſed within the walls of the Senate-houſe, for they were ſuch as neither Senate nor Prince could glory in. But that theſe acclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhould come to the cares of all men living, and be tranſmitted to poſterity, will ſuite both the publique benefit and dignity. Firſt, that the whole world may know and be witneſſe to our pietie, then that it may appeare we dare cenſure both good and evill Princes in their life time; Laſtly, that we may experimentally demonſtrate, that we have formerly beene gratefull but unfortunate, not being ſuffered to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:158486:36"/>
expreſſe our gratitude. But with what contention, what earneſtnes, what clamor did we move you, that you would not let our affections nor your merits be ſuppreſſed? Briefly that they might be left as an example to the future, that Princes might learne to diſtinguiſh true acclamations from falſe, and bee obliged to you for the diſcovery. Princes now are not to begin the way to good fame, but not to devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate from it, not to remove flattery, but not to reduce it. They have a certaine rule what they ſhall doe, and what they ſhall heare when 'tis done. Beſides theſe prayers wherein the Senate have joyned with me, what ſhall I now pray for the Senate? May that joy ever be inherent in your Soule, which then floated in your eyes. May you love that day, but be the cauſe of one more joyfull; may you deſerve againe, and heare againe (for the ſame words cannot bee uttered but for the ſame actions.) Then how like old <hi>Rome</hi> it was, how Conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar; that the Senate by your example ſate three daies together, and all that time you only executed the office of a Conſul? Every one might put to the queſtion what he pleaſed, it was free for any to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, to retract his judgement, to beſtow his advice upon the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, we were all conſulted, all numbred; not the firſt votes carried it, but the beſt. But heretofore who durſt ſpeake, who durſt open his lippes; ſave only thoſe wretches that were firſt required to ſpeake? the reſt dejected and aſtoniſhed, did they not ſuffer a ſeden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie neceſſitie of aſſenting with griefe of Soule and horror of the fleſh? One alone paſſed Sentence, all complied with what they hated as unjuſt, and eſpecially he that did pronounce it; nothing ſo much diſpleaſing a generalitie, as that which is done (againſt their wills) as if it were generally approved of. Some Emperour, haply for reſpect to the Senate brideled himſelfe in this houſe, but no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner out of it, but he reſumed the Princes power, ſcorning and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming all offices of a Conſul. But our Prince was Conſul, as if he had beene nothing elſe, and thought nothing below himſelfe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it were below the Conſul, and ſo appeared in publique as that he brought no ſhew of State, no<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Domitian</hi> was uſhered with 24 Lictors</note> uſhering tumult crowded up his way, he only ſtayed at doore to conſult the<note n="d" place="margin">The obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the flight &amp; chirp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Byrds was one part of the duty of the <hi>Augur,</hi> who ſat with his face to the Eaſt in his Laena (a gowne lined with furres, and bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered with pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple &amp; crimſon) and having quartered the heavens into re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, obſerved from whence the Byrds ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced not good fortune without two lucky ſignes, but evill for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune with one unlucky token of all the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Prieſts he only could not looſe his office during life.</note> birds, and take admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions from the Gods; none was diſturbed, none thruſt aſide; the paſſenger had ſo much freedome, the Lictours were ſo modeſt, that oftentimes a crowd of ſtrangers ſtopt both Prince and Conſul: nay he himſelfe was ſo moderate in his office, ſo well tempered as we thought we ſaw the comportment of ſome ancient and great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſul under the ſhape of a good Prince. He went often to the Forum,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:158486:37"/>
but frequently to <hi>Marſes</hi> fields, for he himſelfe diſcharged the Conſuls office at the election of Conſuls, and tooke as much plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to declare them, as formerly he had done to be created. The Candidates ſtood before the Curule chaire of the Prince, as he had ſtood before the Conſuls, and the oath was given to them which had beene lately taken by the Prince, who knowes the tye of that oath to be ſo great that hee requires it of others. The remainder of the day he ſpent in the Tribunal, and there, how great a Religion of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie! how great a reverence of the Lawes! ſome made addreſſes to the Prince, he anſwered that he was the Conſul. The right of no Office, no ones authoritie was by him leſſened, increaſed it was, for he referred many to the<note n="e" place="margin">Judges of <hi>Rome</hi> in the nature of our Lords chiefe Juſtices.</note> Praetours by the name of his Colleagues, not becauſe it would be popular and pleaſing to the hearers, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſo accounted them: hee acknowledged ſo much honour in that place, that hee eſteemed it no more for one to be ſtiled the Princes Colleague, then Praetour. Beſides he ſate ſo frequentlie in the Tribunal, that he ſeemed to be new ſpirited and refreſh't with labor. Which of us hath taken the ſame care, the ſame paines? ſuch longed-for honours who either attends or merits. And truely 'tis fit hee ſhould thus exceede all Conſuls, that makes Conſuls, for otherwiſe he ſhould be unworthy of his fortune, if he could give honours, and could not manage them. When he makes Conſuls he inſtructs them, and when they are made teaches them to know that he underſtands what hee gives, that they may likewiſe know what they receive. Therefore, with more juſtice the Senate beſeeches and commands you to accept of the fourth Conſulſhippe, 'tis the ſuite of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, not of flatterie; credit your former obedience, that a greater favour the Senate neither can deſire, nor you beſtow. For as in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſo in Princes (that are Gods) life is ſhort and fraile, therefore it behoves every excellent man to endeavour and ſtrive to ſerve the Republique after death, by leaving behinde him the monuments of juſtice and moderation, which a Conſul may beſt erect. This indeed is your intention, to repeale and reduce libertie. What honor ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould you more affect, or what title oftner aſſume, then that, which by recovered<note n="f" place="margin">After the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion of the <hi>Tarquins,</hi> the <hi>Romanes</hi> agreed upon two year<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly Officers, firſt called Praetors, then Judges, laſtly Conſuls. <hi>Roſinus Ant. Rom. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 9.</note> libertie was firſt invented. 'Tis not more no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be both Prince and Conſul, then Conſul only. You likewiſe have regard to the modeſtie of your Colleagues (your Colleagues I ſay, for ſo you your ſelfe doe intitle them, and it is your pleaſure that we doe ſo too) the memorie of their owne third Conſulſhip would have oppreſſed them untill they had ſeene your fourth; for it cannot
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:158486:37"/>
be but too much for a private man, which a Prince thinks enough. You, <hi>Caeſar,</hi> condeſcend, and according to the greatneſſe of your power, you ſtill grant us our praiers, as the Gods grant yours. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps with your third Conſulſhippe you could reſt contented, but we ſo much the leſſe, it makes us repeate and redouble our requeſts that you will againe be Conſul. We ſhould be more cold in our ſuite, if we knew not how you would prove. It had beene better to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied us the experience of you, then the uſe. Shall we once more be ſo happy as to ſee him Conſul! Shall he againe heare and ſpeake the ſame, and give as much joy, as he receives? Shall he commaund in chiefe the Publique Jubily, whereof he is the cauſe and end? Shall he, as formerly, endeavour to reſtraine our affections, nor have power to doe it! Betwixt the Senate's pietie, and the Princes mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie, the combat is glorious which ſo ever conquers or is conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Truely, I conceive, there will be yet an unknown joy; for who hath ſo weake a fancy but he muſt imagine him by how much the oftner, by ſo much the better Conſul? Another, if he had not given himſelfe over to ſloath and pleaſure, would yet have refreſhed his labours with reſt and idleneſſe: This, when he was reſpited from his <hi>Conſular,</hi> reſumed his <hi>Princely</hi> cares, ſo regardfull of juſt temper that neither the Conſul's Office enterfeired with the Princes, nor this check't the Conſul's. We ſee how he ſatisfies the deſires of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces with recruiting their Garriſons, and ſecuring every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar City. No difficulty in giving audience, no delay in returning an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweres. They are immediatly admitted, immediatly diſmiſſed, and at length the Princes doores are not beſieged with crowdes of way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Petitioners. What his whole comportment! how gentle his ſeverity! how judicious his mercy! You ſate not to inrich the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, nor had your ſentence any end but Juſtice. Thoſe that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute their rights and titles ſtand before you, not ſo carefull to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their fortunes, as your eſtimation, nor ſo much fearing your cenſure of their cauſe, as of their manners. How like a Prince it is; how like a Conſul! to reconcile emulous Cities, and to calme ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling nations, not ſo much by command as reaſon! To cure the iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Magiſtrates, and to undoe things that ought not to have beene done. In ſhort, like the ſwifteſt of the Planets, to ſee all things, heare all things, and whereſoever invocated, inſtantly, like a God to be preſent and aſſiſtant. Such Orders, I beleeve, are given by the creator of the world, when he pleaſeth to caſt his eyes upon the earth and to number among his divine works the actions of mortall crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:158486:38"/>
a care you now diſcharge, while he diſpoſes the heaven, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the race of men appointed you for his Vicegerent. And you are ſuch a Vicegerent as beſt pleaſes your great maſter, ſince every day ends with our greateſt benefit and your praiſe. But, when at any time you make even with influent buſineſſes, you eſteeme the change of Labour a kinde of recreation. For what is your recreation but to ride abroad, to rowſe wilde beaſts out of their dennes, to climbe up mighty mountaines, and to ſet foot on horrid rocks with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the helpe either of the hand or track of man; and as occaſion preſents it ſelfe religiouſly to viſit the<note n="g" place="margin">Woods were accounted ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred places by the <hi>Romans</hi> who had ſcarce any Temple without an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning grove, where they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leived the Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties would give meetings to their favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, as <hi>Aege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> had done to their King <hi>Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma.</hi>
               </note> woods, and there to reverence the deities? This was of old the experience of our youth, this was their pleaſure, in theſe<note n="h" place="margin">Of hunting, <hi>Xenophon</hi> ſayes, that by unting health is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, &amp; men's bodies ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellently train<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed for the wars, and that hence they come to be both good Souldiers and Generalls. The moſt famous Huntſmen were <hi>Cephalus, Aeſculapius, Melanion, Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, Theſeus, Hippolitus, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamed, Vliſses, Mneſtheus Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>omed, Caſtor, Pollux, Adonis Machaon, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalirius, Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hus, Achilles Aeneas.</hi>
               </note> exerciſes were our future Generalls trained up, to contend in ſpeed with the ſwifteſt beaſt, in ſtrength with the fierceſt, in ſtratagem with the ſubtileſt. Nor was it accounted a meane ornament of peace, to cleare the fields from the irrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of wild beaſts, and to relieve the Husbandman's beſieged labours. This glory likewiſe was uſurped by thoſe Princes that could not attaine it, and ſo uſurped, that the beaſts were diſlod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to their hands as artificially as if they had forced them from their trenches, being turned looſe to the triumph of a fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed victory. Our Prince ſweates as much in <hi>hunting,</hi> as in <hi>killing</hi> them, and takes great but pleaſing paines to find them out. And if ſometimes he hath pleaſed to carry the ſame ſtrength on Shipboard, he followes not the ſtreaming ſailes with his eyes or hands, but now ſits at the helme now contends with the ableſt of his mates to breake the waves, to tame the ſtrugling winds and to cut through the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the ſea. How different was<note n="i" place="margin">Domitian.</note> he, that could not brooke the ſtillneſſe of the Alban<note n="k" place="margin">It was no mervaile he intimated formerly that <hi>Domitian</hi> feared to paſſe a ford in <hi>Danubius</hi> or the <hi>Rhene</hi> with his Army, when it ſeemes he durſt not truſt himſelfe in a boate to the ſmootheſt of his owne country waters.</note> Lake, nor the tranquillity and ſilence of the Port at <hi>Baiae,</hi> not being able to indure the leaſt ſhake or ſound of oares, but at every ſtroake they made, trembling with ſordid feare? therefore all noiſe removed, with ſailes furled, and ſleeping oares, himſelfe not ſo much as moving, he was carried like ſome<note n="l" place="margin">Something that had the peſtilence or was ſo foule or unholy that none durſt touch it.</note> conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated thing. A ſhamefull ſpectacle to behold the <hi>Roman</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour following the courſe and ſteerage of another ſhip, as if his owne had been taken by the enemy. Nor did even floods and rivers ſcape this deformed ſight. <hi>Danubius</hi> and the <hi>Rhene</hi> rejoyced to carry ſo much of our ſhame. Nor was it leſſe diſhonour to the Empire, that this goodly proſpect ſhould be ſhewen to armies, colours, and banks
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:158486:38"/>
of the Romans, then to the armies colours and banks of the enemy, the enemy, whoſe cuſtome is to ſlide along thoſe waters when they freeze, &amp; when they fall into their channell, to wade, row, or ſwim o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them. Nor ſhould I for it ſelfe ſo much commend your ſtrength, unleſſe your ſtrong bodie was governed by a farre ſtronger ſoule, which neither the indulgence of fortune ſoftens, nor aboundance ſeduces into ſloath and luxury, ſo that whether his recreation car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry him to the mountaines, or to the Ocean, I ſhall admire his body kept in health with exerciſe, and his limbes ſtrengthened with la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. For I finde, that anciently the Goddeſſes<note n="m" place="margin">As <hi>Peleus</hi> who for his va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and skill in Navigation deſerved to have the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe of the Sea <hi>Thetis</hi> for his wife, of whom he begot <hi>Achil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les;</hi> and <hi>Cepha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> and <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litus,</hi> who for their Huntſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip were beloved by the Goddeſſes <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rora</hi> &amp; <hi>Diana.</hi>
               </note> husbands and the Gods children were not more honoured by their marriages, then for theſe arts of hunting and navigation. Withall, I conſider when theſe are our Princes ſports and paſtimes, what (thoſe from which he retires himſelfe to theſe) his ſerious and intended pleaſures are. For there are pleaſures that clearely ſhew every ones gravity, ſanctity, and temperance. Now who ſo diſſolute in whoſe recreations there is not ſome reſemblance of ſeverity? Idleneſſe betrayes us. Have not divers Princes ſpent this very time in diceing, courting of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes, or riotous feaſtings, while their ſerious cares were releived with a ſupply of oppoſite Vices? The very firſt article of a great fortune is, that nothing ſhall be hidden, nothing ſecret. But the fortune of Princes not only opens their Palaces, but even their bed-chambers, and Cabinets, and propoſes and explaines to fame all their myſterious counſells. But you <hi>Caeſar,</hi> have no nearer way to glory then to be throughly looked into. Thoſe things indeed are excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent which you do abroad, nor thoſe leſſe excellent which are done within your Court. 'Tis glorious, <hi>Caeſar,</hi> that you keepe your ſelfe from any infection of vice, but more glorious, that you reſtraine all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout you: by how much it is harder to make others good, then ones ſelfe, by ſo much it is more admirable that you being the beſt have made all like your ſelfe that have relatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to you. Many have diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red themſelves either with a wife inconſiderately taken, or with too tame a patience ſuffered; So that men famous abroad were loſt in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick infamy, and this only hindred them from being eſteemed the greateſt <hi>Romans,</hi> that they were<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sylla</hi> ſurnam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the happy had yet this ſpot in his feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, that he was an unhappier huſband to the wanton <hi>Metel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la:</hi>
               </note> unhappier husbands.<note n="p" place="margin">Cheife Biſhop, a title (as <hi>I</hi> have noted) inherent in the Roman Emperours, declaring their ſupremacy in di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vine matters.</note> Your<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Plotina,</hi> who when ſhe went up the ſteps to the Palace, turning to the multitude ſaid Such <hi>I</hi> go in hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as I hope to come forth, and ſo carried her ſelfe all his reigne as ſhe deſerved no kind of reprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Dion.</hi>
               </note> wife is your ornament and glory, for what more holy, what more ſacred then ſhe is? If our <hi>Pontifex Maximus</hi> were to chuſe a wife he would chuſe her, or her equall, but where is her equall? In all your fortune how ſhe claimes her ſhare in nothing, but the joy! How conſtantly ſhe loves not your power, but your ſelf! you are both
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:158486:39"/>
to one another ſtill the ſame you were, equall in your affections. Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city addes nothing to you, but that now you know how well each of you can digeſt felicity. How modeſt ſhe is in her apparell, how fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall in her traine, how civill in her Garbe! This honour is the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, that gives theſe principles and inſtructions, for a wife compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends all glories in the glory of obedience. When ſhe ſees you goe abroad with no terrour, with no pompe, muſt not ſhe needs learne to paſſe without noiſe, and even your going on foote, (as farre as her weake ſex permits) ſhe imitates, which would become her though you ſhould doe otherwiſe; but where a husband is ſo exemplare, what modeſty ought a wife to ſhew for his honour, a woman for her owne? Your<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Martiana</hi> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for her vir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tues the Senate intitled <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta,</hi> &amp; after her deceaſe deified her.</note> ſiſter likewiſe, how ſhe remembers that ſhe is your ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter! how is your integrity, your truth, your candour viſible in her! ſo that if one ſhould compare her with your wife, he might doubt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to a good life were more efficacious to be nobly bred, or nobly borne. Nothing is ſo apt to quarrell as Emulation, eſpecially in wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, nay it is begot by proximity of alliance, cheriſhed by equality, enflamed by envy, and terminates in hatred. Therefore it muſt needs be thought more admirable, that two women, in the ſame houſe, of like fortune, ſhould have no difference, no contention; they love each other, ſtrive which ſhould give place, and while both moſt paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately love you, they thinke neither is concerned which of them you love beſt. They both propoſe to themſelves the ſame end, the ſame courſe of life, there is nothing whereby you can diſtinguiſh them to be two, for with one ſoule they imitate and ſtudy you. Both there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have the ſame virtues, becauſe both have yours. Nor can they ever come in danger to be private perſons, that will not be other. The Senate preſented them the titles of<note n="r" place="margin">This ſtile of <hi>Auguſtae</hi> was given to the wives &amp; ſiſters of the Roman Emperours by decree of the Senate, whereas that of <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> deſcended upon Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtae,</hi> but they earneſtly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed themſelves, ſo long as you refuſed the appellation of father of your Country, perhaps conceiving it more honour to be ſtiled your Wife and Siſter, then <hi>Auguſtae.</hi> But what reaſon ſoever perſwaded them to ſo much modeſty, they are by ſo much more worthy to be, and in our ſoules to be eſteemed <hi>Auguſtae,</hi> becauſe not ſo entitled. For what in women is more noble, then to beleive true honour conſiſts not in the ſplendour of titles, but the judgements of men, and to make themſelves parallel with great names, even by refuſing them? Now, in the hearts of private perſons, that old felicity of mortalls, freind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, was antiquated [growne out of date] in place whereof there was ſprung up flattery, complement, and (what is worſe then hatred,) diſſembled love; eſpecially in Princes Courts there remained
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:158486:39"/>
onely the empty and laught-at name of Freindſhip. For what articles of freindſhip could be drawne betweene Lords on the one part, and Vaſſals on the other? You Sir, have repealed this ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed virtue. You have freinds, becauſe you are one. Nor can love (like other commands) be enjoined to ſubjects, for there is no affection more free, more noble, more impatient of dominion, and that more requires equality. Perhaps a Prince may be unjuſtly hated, nay hated by ſome although he hate not them, but beloved he cannot be unleſſe he love, we therefore know you love be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you are beloved, and which is in both moſt princely, the whole glory is your owne, who being ſuperiour in dignity not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding do deſcend to all offices of freindſhip, and from an Emperour ſtoope to be a freind, and then are moſt an Emperour when you lay aſide this Title for the other. And ſince a Princes fortune ſtands in neede of many freinds, it is a Prince's cheifeſt bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe to provide himſelfe ſtore of freinds. May this opinion e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver pleaſe you, and as to your other virtues, ſo to this be conſtant, nor let any thing perſwade you, that a Prince can fall below him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, unleſſe he hate. To be beloved is the ſweeteſt of all humane bleſſings, nor is it leſſe ſweete to love; both which you ſo enjoy, that whereas you moſt paſſionately love, yet you are more paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onately beloved. Firſt, for that 'tis eaſier to love one, then many; then, becauſe you have ſo great a power and faculty of obligeing, that none but an ingratefull man can chuſe but love you beſt. 'Tis worth our induſtry, to relate what torments you put your ſelfe unto, that you might deny nothing to your freind. You parted with a moſt excellent<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>L. Licinius Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Captaine of the Guards, to whom <hi>Trajan's</hi> affection is here at large deſcribed.</note> man, moſt deare in your eſteeme, unwill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly and ſadly, and as if you could not tell how much you loved him you tryed it by abſence, with much paine and diſtraction yeilding to be ſeperated. A thing never till this preſent heard of, the Prince and the Prince's freind deſire contradictories, and the freind's deſire carries it. O memorable freindſhip, worthy an immortall Hiſtory, to chuſe the praefect of the Praetorians not out of thoſe that ſought places, but that declined them, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the ſame man to that Reſt which he ſo paſſionately<note n="t" place="margin">How <hi>Sura</hi> doated on a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired life ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing w th ſo great, ſo affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate and ſo unalterable a freind, as <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jan</hi> was to him, but its eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manifeſt by that inſcription which after his 7. yeares pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate life he cauſed to be graven on his monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Here lies one aged many yeares, that liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but ſeaven of them.</note> doates upon; and when you your ſelfe are overburdened with the cares of Empire, not to envy another the glory of his quiet! We un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand how much we owe you, <hi>Caeſar,</hi> for your owne laborious and reſtleſſe ſtations, ſince you granted this petitioner a writt of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:158486:40"/>
Eaſe as the higheſt favour. What confuſion did they tell me you were in, when you brought him on his way, for you could not forbeare going with him to the Sea ſide, where at his very take<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing boate you imbraced and kiſſed him on the ſhore. Upon that vantage ground of friendſhippe <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſtood, wiſhing him a ſafe voyage, and (if he ſo pleaſed) a quick returne: Nor could hee leave him thus, but many leagues followed him with his prayers and teares. I ſay nothing of his munificence, becauſe no bounty can equall this care and patience of a Prince; whereby you have deſerved that he ſhould condemne himſelfe as too pertinacious, too hard-hearted. And doubtleſſe he repented and was readie to bid the Pilot tack about, had he not conceived, there might bee almoſt as much happineſſe as in the Prince's ſocietie, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the Prince. And truely as he enjoyes that greateſt good hee aymed at, ſo he attaines a greater glorie in the reſignation of his place, to which when you conſented, you declared that you would tye no man to your ſervice longer then he pleaſes. This was Princely, and well became our publique Parent to compell nothing, but alwaies to remember that ſo great a power [or place] cannot be given to any, but he may before that power [or place] preferre his freedome. <hi>Caeſar,</hi> you are worthy to conferre offices on ſuch as ſhall wiſh to reſigne them, and when they make it a ſuite, againſt your will indeede, but yet to grant it; you are worthy not to conceive your ſelfe abandoned by your friends that beg leave to retire themſelves, but ſtill to finde thoſe you may call from, and thoſe you may reſtore to Reſt. You like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, my Lords, on whom our Parent daignes to caſt a gracious and familiar eye, improve his opinion of you, this is now your buſineſſe, for the Prince having given us proofe that hee can love, is to be excuſed if he love others in a leſſe degree. But who can ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a moderation in loving him, for as much as his love muſt not receive but give the Law? This man would be affected pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and that abſent, either ſhall have his owne deſire: None by preſence ſhall growe cheape, none by abſence be forgotten; every one holds the place he merits, and he may eaſier blot the face of the abſent out of his memory, then cancell from his heart the affection which he beareth him. Many Princes when they were Tyrants over their Subjects, were yet their freed-men's<note n="u" place="margin">As <hi>Domitian</hi> was to <hi>Criſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> and to the player <hi>Paris,</hi> of whom <hi>Juv. Sat.</hi> 7. Many to honour in the warres hee brings, With ſummer annu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets and winter rings He binds the Poets fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; what there lives No Lord that will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow, a Player gives.</note> bondmen, governed by their counſells, by their wills
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:158486:40"/>
and pleaſures. Through theſe they ſaw, through theſe they ſpake, through theſe mens hands went Praetorſhippes, Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods, Conſulſhippes, Nay unto them were made all addreſſes of that nature. Your freed-men are indeede much honoured by you, but ſtill as freed-men, and you beleeve, it may aboundantly ſuffice them if they be accounted honeſt and carefull ſervants. For you know 'tis a demonſtrative argument of no great Prince, to have great freed-men. And in the firſt place, you admit none of them to be neere your perſon, unleſſe you your ſelfe doe, or your father, or ſome good Prince did affect him. And theſe very men you daily ſo mould and forme, as that they meaſure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, not according to your condition, but their owne. So much more cauſe we have to reſpect them, becauſe we are not tyed to doe it. Have not the Senate and People of <hi>Rome</hi> upon juſt ground conferred on you the Surname of the <hi>Beſt?</hi> It is true, it was a title<note n="*" place="margin">Ready indeed, for <hi>Suetonius</hi> ſaies that <hi>Caius</hi> tooke the Title of <hi>Beſt</hi> &amp; <hi>Great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eſt,</hi> but <hi>Pliny</hi> here implies that <hi>Caeius</hi> only <hi>arrogated</hi> that ſtile of <hi>Beſt,</hi> whereas <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jan won</hi> it by his merit.</note> ready for you, wherewith our tongues were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly acquainted, yet a new title; we may be ſure no other Prince deſerved it, for elſe it had beene<note n="x" place="margin">Not taken,</note> 
               <hi>given</hi> him, as it was to you, <hi>without praemeditation.</hi> Was<note n="y" place="margin">The Style of <hi>Sylla.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Happy</hi> a ſtile comparable to it, which was beſtowed upon the <hi>fortune,</hi> not the <hi>virtue.</hi> Or<note n="z" place="margin">The Surname of <hi>Pompey.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Great,</hi> which had in it more of <hi>envy</hi> then of <hi>glory.</hi> An excellent Prince adopted you into his owne name, the Senate into the name of <hi>Beſt,</hi> and 'tis as proper to you as your paternall Sirname, nor doth he more diſtinguiſh you that calls you <hi>Trajan,</hi> then he that calls you <hi>Beſt.</hi> So, antiently frugalitie denominated the<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Piſo</hi> was Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named the fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was a good husband only for himſelfe, but becauſe he was frugall that he might be beneficiall to others.</note> 
               <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo</hi>'s, wiſedome the<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>C. Lalius, Serpio</hi>'s friend, who intending to reforme the <hi>Lex Agraria</hi> (the Law for diviſion of Lands propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable to the qualities and conditions of men) finding himſelfe oppoſed by a ſtrong faction of the richer ſort, he deſiſted and was therfore ſurnamed the <hi>Wiſe. Plutarch.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Laelij,</hi> pietie the<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Metellus</hi> was ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named the <hi>Pious</hi> for reſcuing the Palladium, or wooden Image of <hi>Pallas,</hi> when her Temple was on fire, in which ſervice the well-meaning man loſt his eyes.</note> 
               <hi>Metelli;</hi> all which Names are comprehended in this one. Nor can he be <hi>Beſt</hi> that excells not every perſon in a peculiar way of merit. Deſervedlie therefore after all your other apellations this was added, as moſt great. For, 'tis leſſe to be Emperour, <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> then of all Emperours, <hi>Caeſar's</hi> and <hi>Auguſtuſe's</hi> the <hi>Beſt.</hi> Therefore that parent both of Gods and men, is firſt adored by the name of <hi>Beſt,</hi> and then of <hi>Greateſt.</hi> The more glorious ſtill your praiſe, that are known to be no leſſe <hi>Beſt,</hi> then <hi>Greateſt;</hi> you have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:158486:41"/>
a name that never can deſcend or be transferred to another, for in a good Prince it will appeare <hi>borrowed,</hi> in a bad Prince <hi>uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped;</hi> which ſhould all your ſucceſſours aſſume, it muſt ever be acknowledged yours. For as the title of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> mindes us of him to whom it was firſt conſecrated, ſo this of <hi>Beſt,</hi> man's memorie never ſhall reflect upon without remembring you. As often as poſterity ſhall be compelled to ſtile another beſt, ſo oft they ſhall remember him that merited that title. Divine <hi>Nerva,</hi> how much is now thy joy in heaven! to ſee that he is <hi>Beſt,</hi> and ſo intituled, whom thou didſt elect as <hi>Beſt!</hi> how it rejoyceth thee, that, compared with thy ſonne, thou art tranſcended, for in nothing more didſt thou declare the greatneſſe of thy ſoule, then that, being excellent thy ſelfe, thou didſt not feare to chooſe a better. And thou likewiſe,<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>L. Trajan</hi> of whom in the Praeface,</note> 
               <hi>Trajan</hi> the father (for though not among the ſtarres, yet thou haſt attained the next place to them) what pleaſure takeſt thou to behold this thy Tribune, this thy Souldier, ſo great a Generall, ſo great a Prince! nay thou haſt a friendly contention with the ſpirit of his adoptive father, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be more noble to have begot or elected ſuch a ſonne. Both of you have infinitely merited of the Common-wealth, on which you have conferred ſo great a good, who though his filiall pietie can but give triumphall ornaments to the one, yet to the other he gives heaven. Nor is your praiſe the leſſe that you deſerve them by your ſonne, then if the merit were your owne. My Lords, I know all <hi>Romanes,</hi> but eſpecially the Conſuls ought to be ſo affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, as to eſteeme themſelves rather publiquely then privatelie oblieged. For, as it is better and more noble to diſtaſte ill Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, for common then particular injuries, ſo the good are more generouſly beloved for their favours done to <hi>mankinde,</hi> then to <hi>men.</hi> But foraſmuch as 'tis growne into a cuſtome, that the Conſuls having preſented the publique thanks, ſhould likewiſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge in their owne names the greatneſſe of their private obligations, give me leave to diſcharge this part of my dutie, not with more reſpect to my ſelfe, then to <hi>Cornutus Tertullus</hi> my Collegue and formerly a Conſular perſon. For why ſhould I not likewiſe give thanks for him, that am equally obliged on his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, eſpecially ſince our moſt gracious Soveraigne hath done that for both, which if one of us only had received yet both had beene obliged: that pillager &amp;<note n="e" place="margin">Domitian.</note> murtherer of every virtuous man
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:158486:41"/>
had blaſted both of us by the ſlaughter of friends; ſo neere us fell the thunderbolt: for we gloried in the ſame friends, and for the ſame loſt men we mourned; as now our joy and hope, ſo then our griefe &amp; feare was common. This honour to our ſufferings di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Nerva</hi> did, that he would<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nerva</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Pliny</hi> &amp; <hi>Cornutus Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullus</hi> Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the Treaſury.</note> advance us, though peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture leſſe worthie, to let the World ſee them flouriſh that before his reigne only wiſh't they might ſlide out of the Princes memory. We had not beene two yeares compleate in that moſt painefull and great Office, when you (beſt of Princes, valianteſt of Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals) offered us the Conſulſhip, that to the higheſt honour the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of celeritie might be added. So much you differ from thoſe Princes, who conceived that difficulty ſet a value on their favours, and that honours would be more welcome to men, if firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire and dancing of attendance, and a delay reſembling a deniall, had affronted and ſet a marke of diſgrace upon them. Modeſtie forbids me to repeate the teſtimonie wherewith you honoured us both, making us (both in our love of truth, and love of the Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique) equall to thoſe antient Conſuls; whether deſervedly, or no, I dare not determine; for it would be unſeemly to contradict what you affirme, and inſolent to owne the character you gave us being ſo magnifique. But you are worthy to create ſuch Conſuls of whom you may report ſuch Miracles. Pardon it, <hi>Sir,</hi> that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong your favours we acknowledg this the higheſt, that you have pleaſed to make us once againe Colleagues, 'twas the ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our mutuall love, of the agreeable method of our life, of one and the ſame end of our endeavours; the power whereof is ſo great, that our ſimilitude of diſpoſition takes from us the glory of our friendſhippe, and it were no leſſe a wonder, ſhould one of us diſſent from his Collegue, then from himſelfe. Therefore 'tis no new or temporary thing, that each of us as much rejoyces in the Conſulſhippe of his Collegue, as if his owne were againe to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed, only they who are twice made Conſuls have a obligations, but at ſeverall times: we have each of us received two Conſulſhips together, we diſcharge them together, joyntly in the union of our ſoules, yet ſeverally and by Collegueſhippe. But how rare it was, that while we were Praefects of the Treaſury, you gave us the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulſhippe, before you named our Succeſſours! One dignity grew into another, nor was the honour <hi>continued,</hi> but <hi>doubled,</hi> and (as if it had beene a meane favour to give us another office when this
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:158486:42"/>
was ended) you would not ſuffer it to expire. So great was the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence you had in our integrity, that you doubted not but to give a good account to your reaſon, if you did not ſuffer us (after ſo great a place in the Republique) to become private men. What? that you were pleaſed to make us Conſuls in the current yeare of your owne Conſulſhippe! we therefore ſhall be in the ſame Roll that records you Conſul, and our names ſhall be added to the Acts you ſigned. You vouchſafed to be Preſident at our Election, and to reade unto us thoſe moſt ſacred verſes. We were made Conſuls by your judgement, that we might have the honour both of your vote in <hi>Court,</hi> and declaration in the <hi>fields.</hi> But how were we graced that particularlie you would aſſigne over to us the moneth which is made glorious by your birth-day! So that we had the happineſſe by our Edicts and by our publique ſhewes to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate that<note n="g" place="margin">Which being the ſame day with that of <hi>Domitian</hi>'s death, muſt be the 18 of <hi>Sept.</hi> for <hi>Sueto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> records him <hi>obtrunca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ad decimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quartum Kalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das Octobris. ij Nerva</hi> being crowned upon the 18 of <hi>Sept.</hi>
               </note> day, bleſt with a three fold joy, that rid us of the worſt Prince, gave us the beſt, and brought forth a better then the beſt. The chariot-Chayre, with more then uſuall reverence carried us in your ſight, and being in the midſt of thoſe fortunate Omens and contentions of good wiſhes that thronged into your preſence, we were ſo over-joyed that we knew not whether the ſound came to our eares from the right hand or the left. Beyond all, it appeares your greateſt nobleneſſe, that you ſuffer thoſe you have created to be Conſuls, for no danger no terrour from the Prince debilitates or ſhakes the Conſular power or ſpirits, nothing is ſpoken againſt our wills, nothing decreed againſt our judgements. The veneration is now and ſhall be inherent in the Honour, nor ſhall we by our au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie cancell our ſecuritie. If the dignitie of the Conſulſhippe looſe any thing, it muſt be our fault, not the times, for 'tis free on the Prince's part, 'tis free for Conſuls to be ſuch, as they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we had Princes. Can we returne you any thanks anſwerable to theſe favours, but only, ever to remember we have bin Conſuls, &amp; <hi>your</hi> Conſuls? So let us thinke, ſo judge as Conſuls ought, and ſo ſerve the weale publique, as beleeving there is now a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale. Let us not withdraw our counſels or endeavours, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive our ſelves to be freed and ſevered, but tyed and bound unto the Conſulſhippe; keeping the ſame eminence in care and induſtry, that we doe in reverence and dignitie. To ſhut up my diſcourſe. I humbly beſeech the governours and guardians of the Empire, the Gods, our heavenly Conſuls; in particular I pray thee, <hi>Capitolin
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:158486:42"/>
Jupiter,</hi> that thou wilt cheriſh what thou haſt beſtowed upon us, and to ſo great a bountie add eternitie. Thou heardſt our impre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations made againſt the <hi>Worſt</hi> of Princes, heare now our prayers for the <hi>Beſt.</hi> We doe not wearie thee with Supplications, we pray not for peace, not for concord, not for ſafety, not for riches, not for honours, all theſe are comprehended in one ſingle wiſh, the preſervation of the Prince; nor doe we aske new favours, for thou didſt then receive him into thy protection, when thou didſt ſnatch him out of the tallons of a vulturous<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Domitian,</hi> of whoſe ſubtile hatred to <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jan</hi> in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face.</note> Tyrant; for not without thy ſpeciall aſſiſtance, when every noble height was battered downe, could this of all the nobleſt have remained unſhaken; being paſſed over by the worſt Prince, that the beſt might find him. Thou gaveſt us evident teſtimonies of thy approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion when thou didſt entitle him (then going towards the Army) to thy owne name, to thy owne honour; thou ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the Emperour's mouth didſt adopt to him a <hi>Sonne,</hi> to us a <hi>Parent,</hi> to thy ſelfe a <hi>Pontifex Maximus.</hi> Wherefore in the very words, wherein hee prayed for himſelfe, I pray, if hee governe the Republique well and for the benefit of all, firſt that thou wilt preſerve him for our Grand-children and great Grand-children, then that at length thou wilt give him a Succeſſour whom hee hath begotten, as happilie as hee himſelfe hath beene adopted; or if fate deny him this, be of counſell with him in his choice, and ſhew him ſuch a one as it may become him to elect in the <hi>Capitoline</hi> Temple.</p>
            <p>How much I am indebted to your Lordſhips is likewiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in our publicke monuments. You have given me an au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenticke teſtimony of peaceableneſſe in my Tribuneſhippe, modeſty in my Praetourſhippe, and conſtancy in thoſe offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces you enjoined me, in defending the cauſes of our Aſſociates; &amp; you approved of my following Conſulſhippe with ſo manie joyfull expreſſions, that I conceive my ſelfe ingaged to my utmoſt power to cheriſh, confirm, and dayly to improve the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of your approbation. For I know tis then beſt judged whether one doth or doth not merit honour, when he hath attained it. Do you but favour this my intention, and beleive it, if I was once put into a way of advancement by that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Domitian,</hi> who at firſt ſo diſſembled, that he forbad the ſacrificing of <hi>Beaſts,</hi> where as afterward be himſelfe ſet up a ſhambles for <hi>Men.</hi>
               </note> Prince, before he profeſſed his hatred to good men, if after
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:158486:43"/>
he profeſſed it I retired my ſelfe; when I ſaw the compendious way to honour, I choſe to goe a longer journey; if in bad times I be numbred with the ſad and indangered, in good times with the joyfull and ſecure; to conclude, if I as much love the beſt Prince, as I was hated by the worſt, I ſhall ever ſerve your Lordſhips not as Conſul or a Conſular perſon, but as a Candidate of the Conſulſhip.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:158486:43"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PReface Pag. 1. Lin. 5. for, <hi>Conqueſt of the king of Dacia.</hi> reade <hi>Conqueſt of Dacia.</hi> Panegyrick pag. 3 lin. 5. for <hi>ſay too much,</hi> read <hi>pleaſe or diſpleaſe as I ſhall ſay too much.</hi> p. 4. l. 17. for <hi>that end.</hi> r. <hi>this end.</hi> p. 30. b. l. 33. for <hi>ſucceſſion.</hi> r. <hi>poſterity.</hi> p. 27. b. for <hi>ex.</hi> r. <hi>et.</hi> marg.</p>
            <p>Some ſuch other ſmall faults there are, which the Reader may with eaſe diſcover and correct.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
